This work derives from Principle Events 1914-1918, compiled by The Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence, and originally published by H.M. Stationery Office, in 1922; as part of the History of the Great War. It was prepared from the OCR text of the PDF copy held by the Internet Archive (urn:oclc:record:1050840522).

Only Part I of the book - the general chronological list - is reproduced in this work. Parts II and III give different presentations of entries in Part I. An ongoing effort will introduce semantic mark-up, with a view to being able to derive the presentation in Parts II and III (and more) from the chronological list.

1914, 1915, 1916, 1917, 1918

Principal Events 1914-1918

1914

June 28

The Archduke Franz Ferdinand assassinated at Sarajevo.

July 5

The Kaiser receives at Potsdam special envoy from Austrian Emperor and promises "the full support of Germany" in the event of Austrian action against Serbia. He consults his military and naval advisers before leaving for a cruise in northern waters.

July 14

Council of Austro-Hungarian Ministers finally determine on action against Serbia.

July 19

Council of Austro-Hungarian Ministers approve of draft ultimatum to Serbia.

July 23

Austro-Hungarian Government send ultimatum to Serbia (see 25th).

July 24

German Government submit note to Entente Governments approving Austrian ultimatum to Serbia (see 23rd).

British Foreign Minister (Sir E. Grey) initiates proposals for an international conference in order to avert war (see 27th and 28th).

Belgian Government declare that, in the event of war, Belgium will uphold her neutrality "whatever the consequences" (see 31st).

July 25

Serbian Government order Mobilisation (see 23rd).

Austria-Hungary severs diplomatic relations with Serbia. Austro-Hungarian Minister leaves Belgrade (see 26th).

Serbian Government transferred from Belgrade to Nish (see November 3rd, 1915).

July 26

Austro-Hungarian Government order Partial Mobilisation as against Serbia (see 28th and 31st).

Montenegrin Government order Mobilisation (see August 5th).

British Admiralty countermand orders for dispersal of Fleets (see 28th).

The Kaiser returns from the Baltic to Berlin (see 5th).

July 27

French and Italian Governments accept British proposals for an international conference (see 24th).

German High Seas Fleet recalled from Norway to war bases.

July 28

Austria-Hungary declares war on Serbia (see 25th and 26th).

German Government reject British proposals for an international conference (see 24th and 27th).

British Fleets ordered to war bases (see 26th).

July 29

Russian Government order Partial Mobilisation as against Austria.

(Evening) Russian Minister for War orders General Mobilisation without the knowledge of the Tsar (see 30th and 31st). Hostilities commence between Austria-Hungary and Serbia: Belgrade bombarded by Austrian artillery (see 25th, and December 2nd).

German Government make proposals to secure British neutrality (see 30th).

British Admiralty send "Warning Telegram" to the Fleets.

British War Office send out telegrams ordering "Precautionary Period" (2.10 p.m.).

July 30

The Tsar signs order at 4 p.m. for mobilisation of Russian army (see 29th and 31st).

British Government reject German proposals for British neutrality (see 29th).

Australian Government place Australian Navy at disposal of British Admiralty.

July 31

Belgian Government order Mobilisation (see 24th).

Russian Government order General Mobilisation (see 29th and 30th).

Austro-Hungarian Government order General Mobilisation (see 26th and 28th).

German Government send ultimatum to Russia (presented at midnight, 31st-lst) (see August 1st).

State of "Kriegsgefahr" proclaimed in Germany (see August 1st).

Turkish Government order Mobilisation (to commence August 3rd) (see October 29th).

London Stock Exchange closed (see January 4th, 1915).

August 1

British Government order Naval Mobilisation.

German Government order General Mobilisation and declare war on Russia (see July 31st).

Hostilities commence on Polish frontier.

French Government order General Mobilisation.

August 2

German Government send ultimatum to Belgium demanding passage through Belgian territory (see 3rd, and July 24th).

German troops cross frontier of Luxembourg (see November 20th, 1918).

Hostilities commence on French frontier.

Libau bombarded by German cruiser "Augsburg" (see November 17th).

British Government guarantee naval protection of French coasts against German aggression by way of the North Sea or English Channel.

Moratorium proclaimed in Great Britain (see November 4).

General von Moltke (Chief of the Great General Staff since 1906) appointed Chief of the General Staff of the German Field Armies (see September 14th).

August 3

Belgian Government refuse German demands (see 2nd and 4th).

British Government guarantee armed support to Belgium should Germany violate Belgian neutrality.

Germany declares war on France.

British Government order General Mobilisation.

British Government issue Proclamation authorising requisition of shipping.

Italy declares neutrality.

The Grand Duke Nicholas appointed Commander-in-Chief Russian armies (see 14th).

August 4

British Government send ultimatum to Germany.

Great Britain declares war on Germany at 11 p.m. (midnight 4th-5th by Central European time).

Belgium severs diplomatic relations with Germany (see 2nd and 3rd).

Germany declares war on Belgium.

German troops cross Belgian frontier and attack Liége (see 3rd and 7th, and November 26th, 1918).

Two German airships pass over Brussels by night (first hostile act in the air).

German warships "Goeben" and "Breslau" bombard Philippeville and Bona respectively (see 7th and 11th).

Secret Alliance between Germany and Turkey signed at Berlin.

British Grand Fleet constituted under Admiral Sir John Jellicoe (see November 29th and December 4th, 1916).

Staff of British Expeditionary Force appointed: — Commander-in-Chief: Field-Marshal Sir John French (see December 15th, 1915). Chief of General Staff: LieutGeneral Sir Archibald Murray (see January 24th. 1915). Adjutant-General: Lieut.-General Sir Nevil Macready (see February 21st, 1916). Quartermaster-General: LieutGeneral Sir William Robertson (see January 24th, 1915).

British Government issue Proclamation specifying articles to be treated as contraband (see 20th, and September 21st).

German armed merchant cruiser "Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse" leaves Bremen (see 26th).

August 5

Montenegro declares war on Austria-Hungary (see July 26th).

Minelaying in the open sea commenced by the Germans (east of Southwold) (see October 3rd). German minelayer "Königin Luise" sunk.

First meeting of British War Council (see May 14th, 1915). Formed to exercise the functions of the Committee of Imperial Defence, but with additional executive powers.

August 6

Austria-Hungary declares war on Russia. (Declaration presented at St. Petersburg).

Serbia declares war on Germany (see July 28th).

"Battle of the Frontiers" (General name covering all operations of the French armies up to the Battle of the Marne.) begins in France.

Field-Marshal Earl Kitchener succeeds Mr. Asquith as Secretary of State for War, Great Britain. (Mr. Asquith held the appointment from March 31st, 1914.) (See June 5th, 1916.)

H.M.S. "Amphion" sunk by mine off Yarmouth.

Naval Convention between France and Great Britain concluded in London. French Admiral to command Allied Naval Forces in the Mediterranean. (See November 9th.)

Action between H.M.S. "Bristol" and German cruiser "Karlsruhe" in the West Indies (see November 4th).

German armed merchant cruiser "Prinz Eitel Friedrich" leaves Tsingtau (see January 28th and April 8th, 1915).

Admiral von Spee's squadron ("Scharnhorst" [flag], "Gneisenau," "Nürnberg." "Dresden" and "Leipzig" joined on October 12th and 14th respectively.) leaves Ponape (Caroline islands) (see September 22nd).

August 7

City of Liége occupied by German forces (see 4th and 16th).

First units of British Expeditionary Force land in France (see 16th).

French troops cross the frontier of Alsace (see 2nd).

Action between H.M.S. "Gloucester" and the "Goeben" and "Breslau" off the coast of Greece (see 4th and 11th).

August 8

Montenegro severs diplomatic relations with Germany.

"State of War" commences between Montenegro and Germany (see 5th).

Mulhouse (Alsace) occupied by French forces (see 7th and 11th),

British forces cross frontier of Togoland and occupy Lome (see 13th and 26th).

Swiss Government order Mobilisation.

Hostilities commence in East Africa (see 15th) . H.M.S. "Astraea" bombards Dar es Salaam (see September 4th, 1916).

August 9

British aerial cross-Channel patrol for the protection of transports instituted.

Belgian Government proposal for neutralisation of African free trade zone formulated (see 22nd).

H.M.S. "Birmingham" sinks German submarine "U.-15" in the North Sea. (First submarine destroyed.)

August 10

British aerial coast patrol established.

France severs diplomatic relations with Austria-Hungary (see 12th).

August 11

German warships "Goeben" and "Breslau" enter the Dardenelles (see 4th and 7th).

Mulhouse retaken by German forces (see 8th and 19th).

French Government issue first list of contraband (see 25th and November 6th).

August 12

Great Britain and France declare war on Austria-Hungary (see 10th).

Austrian forces cross the Save and seize Shabatz (see 25th).

August 13

Austrian forces cross River Drina and begin first invasion of Serbia (see 25th).

Four squadrons Royal Flying Corps fly from Dover to France. (First units to cross by air.)

Allied advance on Kamina (Togoland) from Lome begins (see 8th and 26th).

August 14

Proclamation issued by Russian Commander-in-Chief (The Grand Duke Nicholas) promising autonomy to Poland (see April 3rd, 1915).

Battles of Morhange and Sarrebourg begin (see 20th).

August 15

Japanese Government send ultimatum to Germany demanding evacuation of Tsingtau (see 23rd, and September 2nd).

German troops cross frontier of British East Africa and occupy Taveta (see 8th, November 2nd, and March 10th, 1916).

Junction of British and French squadrons effected at entrance to the Adriatic.

August 16

Landing of original British Expeditionary Force (4 Divisions and 1 Cavalry Division) in France completed (announced August 18th) (see 7th).

Last forts of Liége captured by German forces (16th/17th) (see 4th and 7th).

Naval action in the Southern Adriatic: Austrian light cruiser "Zenta" sunk by Allied squadron.

August 17

Battle of the Tser and the Jadar (Serbia) begins (see 13th and 21st).

Belgian Government transferred from Brussels to Antwerp (see October 7th).

August 18

Battle of the Gette (18th/19th).

Vossuq ed Douleh, Persian Foreign Minister, resigns. (Appointed January 11th, 1913.) (See 19th, and August 29th, 1916.)

August 19

Belgian Army retreats from the Gette on Antwerp.

Mulhouse again taken by French forces (see 11th and 25th).

First unit of Indian Expeditionary Force "C" (This unit, the 29th Punjabis, was the first to leave India for any theatre of war.) leaves India for East Africa (see September 1st).

Ala es Sultaneh, Persian Prime Minister, resigns (appointed January 11th, 1913) and is appointed Foreign Minister (see 18th, and February 20th, 1915).

Mustaufi ul Mamalek appointed Persian Prime Minister (see March 14th, 1915).

August 20

Brussels occupied by German forces (see November 18th, 1918).

Battles of Morhange and Sarrebourg end (see 14th).

Longwy invested by German forces (see 26th).

Battle of Gawaiten-Gumbinnen (East Prussia) (19th/20th).

Death of Pope Pius X (see September 3rd).

First British Order in Council revising "Declaration of London" issued (see October 29th).

August 21

German forces begin attack on Namur (see 25th).

Battle of Charleroi begins (see 24th).

Battle of the Tser and the Jadar ends. Austrian Armies in Serbia retreat (see 17th).

German forces from German South-West Africa cross frontier of British South Africa (see September 19th).

British Government issue orders for the raising of the first New Army of six Divisions (see May 9th, 1915).

August 22

Austria-Hungary declares war on Belgium (see 28th).

Battle of the Ardennes begins (see 24th).

German Government agree to Belgian proposal, made through Spanish Government, re African free trade zone (see 9th, and November 20th).

August 23

Battle of Mons (see 24th).

German airship "Z.-8" shot down in the Vosges.

Battle of Tannenberg begins (see 31st).

First Battle of Krasnik (Poland) begins (see 25th).

Germany severs diplomatic relations with Japan (see 15th).

Japan declares war on Germany (see 15th).

General C. M. Dobell appointed to command Allied land forces operating in the Cameroons.

General von Hindenburg takes over command of German Eighth Army (see September 18th).

August 24

British army retreats from Mons (see 23rd, and September 5th).

Battle of Charleroi ends (see 21st).

Battle of the Ardennes ends (see 22nd).

Austria-Hungary severs diplomatic relations with Japan (see 25th).

First units of Indian Expeditionary Force "A" leave India for France (in first place for Egypt) (see September 26th).

August 25

Namur captured by German forces (see 21st, and November 21st, 1918.)

Battle of the Meuse begins (see 28th).

Battle of Malines begins (see 27th).

Valenciennes taken by German forces (see November 3rd, 1918).

Maubeuge invested by German forces (see September 7th).

Battle of the Mortagne (Vosges) begins (see September 3rd).

Mulhouse again retaken by German forces (see 19th, and November 17th, 1918).

First use of aircraft for patrol purposes (over retreating British forces in France).

First Battle of Krasnik (Poland) ends (see 23rd).

Shabatz (see 12th) retaken by Serbian forces. Last Austrian forces recross the Drina (see 13th). End of First Austrian invasion of Serbia (see September 8th).

Japan severs diplomatic relations with Austria-Hungary (see 24th).

Japan declares "State of War" with Austria-Hungary.

Nigerian frontier of the Cameroons crossed by British forces. Affair of Tepe. Chad frontier crossed by French forces.

French Government issue new decree defining contraband (see 11th, and November 6th).

August 26

Louvain sacked by German troops.

Battle of Le Cateau.

Noyon taken by German forces (see September 21st).

Longwy capitulates to German forces (see 20th).

Cambrai occupied by German forces (see November 20th, 1017, and October 9th, 1918).

Douai occupied by German forces (see October 17th, 1918).

First Battle of Lemberg (Galicia) begins (see 30th).

Battle of Zamosc-Komarow begins (see September 2nd).

Naval action off the Aaland Islands. German cruiser "Magdeburg" destroyed by Russian squadron.

German forces in Togoland capitulate to the Allied forces (see 8th, 13th and 31st).

Action between H.M.S. "Highflyer" and German armed merchant cruiser "Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse" off the Rio de Oro: latter sunk (see August 4).

General Galliéni appointed Governor of Paris (see October 30th, 1915).

M. Messimy, French Minister for War (Appointed June 14th, 1914), resigns (see 27th).

M. Delcassé succeeds M. Doumerguef (Appointed August 3rd, 1914) as French Foreign Minister.

August 27

Battle of Malines ends (see 25th).

British Marines landed at Ostend, accompanied by R.N.A.S. unit.

Lille occupied by German cavalry (see September 5th).

Mezieres occupied by German forces (see November 10th, 1918).

M. Millerand appointed French Minister for War (see 26th, and October 29th, 1915).

First attack on Mora (Cameroons) (see September 8th, 1915).

August 28

Battle of the Meuse ends (see 25th).

Austro-Hungarian declaration of war received by Belgian Government (see 22nd).

Naval action off Heligoland (German light cruisers "Köln," "Mainz," and "Ariadne" sunk by British squadron).

August 29

Arras evacuated by the French forces (see September 30th).

Battle of Guise begins (see 30th).

Sedan taken by German forces (see November 6th, 1918).

German airship "Z.-5" brought down by gunfire at Mlawa (Poland).

August 30

Laon, La Fère, and Roye occupied by German forces (see March 17th, 1917, and October 13th, 1918).

Battle of Guise ends (see 29th, and November 4th, 1918).

First German aeroplane raid on Paris (see September 16th, 1918).

First Battle of Lemberg (Galicia) ends (see 26th, and September 3rd).

First attack on Garua (Cameroons) (see April 18th, 1915).

Samoa occupied by New Zealand Expeditionary Force.

August 31

Amiens entered by German forces (see September 13th).

Battle of Tannenberg ends (see 23rd).

Franco-British Agreement defining provisional zones in Togoland concluded (see 26th, and December 27th, 1910).

September 1

Lord Kitchener visits France to confer with British Commander-in-Chief.

Craonne taken by German forces (see May 4th, 1917).

Soissons taken by German forces (see 13th).

First unit of Indian Expeditionary Force "C" arrives at Mombasa (see August 19th and December 31st).

General J. Stewart takes over command of British forces in East Africa (see October 31st).

September 2

Battle of Zamosc-Komarow ends (see August 26th).

Japanese forces land in Shantung to attack Tsingtau (sea August 15th, September 23rd and November 7th).

French Government transferred from Paris to Bordeaux (see November 18th).

September 3

Battle of the Mortagne ends (see August 25th).

Lemberg captured by Russian forces (see August 30th, 1914, and June 22nd, 1915).

H.M.S. "Speedy" sunk by mine the Humber.

Benedict XV elected Pope (see August 20th and November 5th).

Prince William of Wied leaves Albania (see October 4th).

French Government inform United States Government that they will observe "Declaration of London" subject to certain modifications.

September 4

Battle of the Grand Couronné (Nancy) begins (see 12th).

German Government agree to observe "Declaration of London" if other belligerents conform thereto, and issue their list of contraband.

September 5

End of Retreat from Mons (see August 24th, 1914, and November 11th, 1918).

Battle of the Ourcq begins.

German forces reach Claye, 10 miles from Paris (nearest point reached during war).

Reims taken by German forces (see 14th).

Lille evacuated by German forces (see August 27th and October 12th).

H.M.S. "Pathfinder" sunk by submarine in North Sea (first British warship so destroyed).

Battle of the Masurian Lakes begins (see 15th).

German forces cross frontier of North Rhodesia. Defence of Abercorn begins (see 9thh).

British, French, and Russian Governments sign "Pact of London." Decision not to make separate peace (see April 26th, October 19th, and November 30th, 1915).

September 6

Battle of the Marne begins (French date) (see 9th and 10th).

Serbian passage the Save. Serbian operations in Syrmia begin (see 11th).

Affair of Tsavo (East Africa).

September 7

Maubeuge capitulates to German forces (see August 25th, 1914, and November 8th, 1918).

Battle of Tarnavka (Galicia) begins (see 9th).

Naval operations off Duala (Cameroons) begin, in preparation for attack by Allied military forces (see 27th).

September 8

Austrian forces begin second invasion of Serbia (see August 25th and December 15th). Battle of the Drina begins (see 17th).

Second Battle of Lemberg begins (see 11th).

General Sir John Maxwell takes over command of British forces in Egypt (see March 19th, 1916).

September 9

German retreat from the Marne begins (see 6th).

Battle of Tarnavka ends (see 7th).

Turkish Government announce abolition of "The Capitulations."

Affairs near Karonga (Nyassaland). First important fighting.

Defence of Abercorn (Rhodesia) ends. German force retreats (see 5th) .

First units of Indian Expeditionary Force "A" arrive at Suez (see 19th).

September 10

Battle of the Marne ends (British date) (see 6th).

Battle of the Ourcq ends.

Semlin (Syrmia) occupied by Serbian forces (see 17th).

German light cruiser "Emden" makes her first capture in the Indian Ocean (Greek collier "Pontoporos") (see 22nd, and October 28th).

German and Austrian representatives expelled from Egypt (see November 1st).

September 11

Second Battle of Lemberg ends (see 8th). Austrian forces in Galicia retreat (see October 3rd).

Serbian advance in Syrmia abandoned (see and 17th).

British Government issue orders the raising of the second New Army of six divisions (see August 21st September 13th).

Australian Expeditionary Force lands on Bismarck Archipelago (German Guinea).

September 12

Battle of the Grand Couronné (Nancy) ends (see 4th).

Battle of the Aisne, 1914, begins (see 15th).

Affair of Herbertshöhe (German Guinea) (see 11th and 17th).

September 13

Soissons (see 1st, and January 8th, 1915) and Amiens (see August 31st) reoccupied by French forces.

British Government issue orders raising third New Army of six divisions (see llth).

September 14

Reims evacuated by German forces (see 5th and 19th).

Action between British armed merchant cruiser "Carmania" and German armed merchant cruiser "Cap Trafalgar" in the South Atlantic: latter sunk.

General von Moltke resigns as Chief of the General Staff of the German Field Armies, and is succeeded by General Falkenhayn (see August 2nd, 1914, and August 20th, 1916).

September 15

Battle of the Aisne, 1914, ends (see 12th).

Battle of the Masurian Lakes ends (see 5th).

Czernowitz (Bukovina) taken by Russian forces (see October 22nd).

Rebellion in South Africa begins (see December 1st and 28th).

September 17

German New Guinea and surrounding Colonies capitulate to Australian Expeditionary Force (see 21st, and October 11th).

Serbian forces in Syrmia withdrawn. Semlin evacuated (see 16th).

Battle of the Drina ends (see 8th).

British Naval Mission leaves Turkey.

Admiral Souchon (Imperial German navy) assumes control of Turkish navy.

September 18

General Hindenburg appointed Commander-in-Chief of German Armies in Eastern Theatre (see August 23rd and November 27th).

September 19

First units of Indian Expeditionary Force "A" leave Egypt for Marseilles (see 9th).

First bombardment of Reims Cathedral by German artillery (see 14th).

Cattaro bombarded by French squadron.

Lüderitzbucht (German South-West Africa) occupied by South African forces. First German territory to be entered by Union troops.

British and French Governments guarantee to Belgium the integrity of her colonies.

Secret agreement for mutual support concluded between Russian and Rumanian Governments.

September 20

H.M.S. "Pegasus" sunk by German light cruiser "Königsberg" at Zanzibar (see October 31st, 1914, and July 11th, 1915).

September 21

Noyon retaken by French forces (see 25th, and August 26th).

Jaroslaw (Galicia) taken by Russian forces (see May 14th, 1915).

German armed forces in New Guinea surrender to the Australian Expeditionary Force (see 17th, and October 11th).

British Proclamation issued adding to list of contraband (see August 4th and December 23rd).

September 22

Battle of Picardy begins (see 26th).

H.M.S. "Aboukir," "Hogue," and "Cressy" sunk by German submarine "U.-9."

Admiral Spee's squadron bombards Papeete in Tahiti (see, August 6th and November 1st).

German light cruiser "Emden" bombards Madras (see 10th, and October 28th).

First British air raid on Germany (Düsseldorf and Cologne airship sheds attacked) (see October 8th).

First use of wireless telegraphy from aeroplane to artillery (by British Royal Flying Corps).

September 23

British force joins Japanese army before Tshigtau. Force landed September 22nd; in action September 24th. (see 2nd, and November 7th).

September 24

Péronne taken by German forces (see March 18th, 1017).

Przemysl isolated by Russian forces. First siege begins (see October 9th).

Russian forces begin first Invasion of North Hungary (see October 8th).

September 25

Noyon retaken by German Eorces (see 21st, and March 18th, 1917).

Actions on the Niemen begin (see 29th).

September 26

Battle of Picardy ends (see 22nd).

Bapaume occupied by German Eorces (see March 17th, 1917).

First units of Indian Expeditionary Force "A" land at Marseilles (see 19th, and October 19th).

September 27

Siege of Antwerp begins (see October 10th).

First Battle of Artois begins (see October 12th).

Duala (Cameroons) captured by Allied forces (26th/27th) (see 7th).

September 28

Malines taken by German forces. Distinctive markings on German aircraft first reported (see November 12th).

Lieut.-General Sir A. Barrett appointed Commander-designate of Indian Expeditionary Force "D" for Mesopotamia (see November 13th).

September 29

German offensive on the Niemen abandoned (see 25th).

September 30

Arras reoccupied by French forces (see August 29th).

October 2

Termonde (Belgium) taken by German forces.

Indian Expeditionary Force "E" formed in Egypt from details of Indian Expeditionary Force "A" (see August 24th, 1914, and March 25th, 1915).

October 3

Ypres occupied by German cavalry (see 13th).

British army begins to leave the Aisne and to move northwards (see 19th).

First units of British Royal Naval Division (Marine Brigade) arrive at Antwerp (3rd/4th).

First contingents of Canadian and Newfoundland Expeditionary Forces leave for England (see 15th).

Retreat of Austro-Hungarian forces in Galicia ends (see September 11th).

Maramaros-Sziget taken by Russian forces (see 7th).

Minelaying in the open sea (between the Goodwins and Ostend) commenced by British (see August 5th).

October 4

Lens and Bailleul occupied by German forces (see 14th, and September 3rd, 1918, and August 30th, 1918).

Austro-Hungarian counter-offensive in Galicia begins (see 3rd).

Provisional Government under Essad Pasha set up in Albania at Durazzo (see February 24th, 1916).

October 6

Units of British 7th Division disembark at Ostend and Zeebrugge to co-operate with Belgian army (see 12th).

October 7

Maramaros-Sziget retaken by Austrian forces (see 3rd).

Belgian Government transferred from Antwerp to Ostend (see August 17th and October 12th and 13th). Evacuation of Antwerp begun.

Japanese naval forces occupy Yap Island (Pacific).

October 8

General Foch appointed to command Allied forces (less Belgians) defending the Flanders coast (see May 15th, 1917).

Second British air raid on Germany (Düsseldorf and Cologne airship sheds attacked) (see September 22nd).

First Russian invasion of North Hungary ends (see September 24th and November 15th).

October 9

Merville, Estaires, Armentières, and Hazebrouck taken by German forces (see 10th, 11th and 17th).

Menin occupied by German forces (Approximate date.) (see October 15th, 1918).

Last forts of Antwerp taken by German forces (see 10th, and September 27th).

First German offensive against Warsaw. Battles of Warsaw and Ivangorod begin (see 19th and 20th).

Przemysl relieved by advancing Austrian forces (see 4th). End of First siege (see September 24th and November 10th).

October 10

Antwerp capitulates to German forces (see 9th, and September 27th, 1914, and November 19th, 1918).

Hazebrouck and Estaires captured by British forces (see 9th).

Battle of La Bassée begins (see November 2nd).

Protocol signed by United States of America and Panama as to use of Panama Canal by ships of belligerent Powers.

King Charles of Rumania dies, and is succeeded by his son Ferdinand.

October 11

Merville retaken by British forces (see 9th, and April 11th, 1918).

Bussian cruiser "Pallada" sunk by German submarine off Hangö.

German gunboat "Komet" captured by H.M.A.S. "Nusa" near Talassia (Neu Pommern). Last, act of hostilities in Australasian waters.

October 12

Battle of Messines, 1914, begins (see November 2nd).

First Battle of Artois ends (see September 27th).

Ostend and Zeebrugge evacuated by Belgian forces (see 6th and 15th).

Lille capitulates to German forces (see September 5th, 1914, and October 17th, 1918).

Ghent evacuated by Belgian forces and occupied by German forces (see November 10th, 1918).

October 13

Battle of Armentières begins (see November 2nd).

Ypres reoccupied by Allied forces retreating from Ghent (see 3rd and 19th).

First appearance of a German submarine on the Southampton-Havre troop-transport route reported.

Battle of Chyrow (Galicia) begins (see November 2nd).

Belgian Government set up at Havre (see 7th, and November 21st, 1918).

October 14

Bailleul occupied by British forces (see 4th, and April 15th, 1918).

Bruges occupied by German forces (see October 19th, 1918).

Yabasi (Cameroons) captured by Allied forces.

October 15

Belgian coast-line reached by German forces (see October 20th, 1918).

Zeebrugge and Ostend occupied by German forces (see 12th, and October 17th and 19th, 1918).

First units of Canadian and Newfoundland Expeditionary Forces land in England (see 3rd, and February 9th, 1915).

H.M.S. "Hawke" sunk by German submarine in North Sea.

October 16

Battle of the Yser begins (Belgian date) (see November 10th).

New Zealand Expeditionary Force leaves New Zealand for France (see December 1st).

Indian Expeditionary Force "B" leaves India for East Africa (see 31st).

First units of Indian Expeditionary Force "D" leave India for the Persian Gulf (see 23rd).

Marquis di San Giuliano, Italian Foreign Minister (appointed March 24th 1914), dies (see November 3rd).

October 17

Armentières recaptured by Allied forces (see 9th, and April 11th, 1918).

Action by H.M.S. "Undaunted" and destroyers with four German destroyers off Butch coast; latter all sunk.

First British submarines ("E.-1" and "E.-9") enter the Baltic.

German submarines attempt raid on Scapa Flow (see 18th).

First units of Australian Imperial Force embark for France (see December 1st).

October 18

First bombardment of Ostend by British warships (see 15th).

Roulers taken by Germarj forces (see October 14th, 1918).

Grand Fleet withdraws from Scapa Flow to West of Scotland (see 17th, and November 3rd).

Japanese light cruiser "Takachiho" sunk by German destroyer off Tsingtau.

October 19

Battles of Ypres, 1914, begin (see 31st, and November 22nd).

Transfer of British army from the Aisne to Flanders completed (see 3rd).

First Indian units reach the Flanders front (see September 26th, and November 10th, 1915).

Battle of Warsaw ends (see 9th).

October 20

Battle of Ivangorod ends (see 9th).

First merchant vessel sunk by German submarine (British S.S. "Glitra") (see February 19th and March 13th and 28th, 1915).

October 21

Battle of Langemarck, 1914 (Ypres) begins (see 24th).

October 22

Czernowitz (Bukovina) reoccupied by Austrian forces (see 28th, and September 15th).

United States Government issue Circular Note to belligerent Governments stating that they will insist on existing rules of International Law (see July 28th, 1916).

October 23

Advanced troops of Indian Expeditionary Force "D" arrive at the Bahrein Islands (Persian Gulf) (see 16th, and November 6th).

October 24

Battle of Langemarck, 1914 (Ypres), ends (see 21st).

October 25

General Sir C. Douglas, Chief of the Imperial General Staff, Great Britain (Appointed April 6, 1914), dies (see 26th).

October 26

German forces begin an unprovoked invasion of Angola (Portuguese West Africa) (see December 4th).

Edea (Cameroons) occupied by French forces.

General Sir J. Wolfe Murray appointed Chief of the Imperial General Staff, Great Britain (see 25th, and September 25th, 1915).

October 27

H.M.S. "Audacious" sunk by mine off coast of Donegal.

October 28

Czernowitz (Bukovina) reoccupied by Russian forces (see 22nd, and February 17th, 1915).

German cruiser "Emden" raids Penang Roads and sinks Russian cruiser "Zhemchug" (see September 10th and November 9th).

October 29

Battle of Gheluvelt (Ypres) begins (see 31st).

Turkey commences hostilities against Russia (see July 31st, and November 2nd and 5th) . Turkish warships bombard Odessa, Sevastopol, and Theodosia.

New British Order in Council revises list of contraband and modifies "Declaration of London" of 1909 (see August 20th, 1914, and July 7th, 1916).

Prince Louis of Battenberg, First Sea Lord, Great Britain (Appointed December 9th, 1912.), resigns (see 30th).

October 30

Stanislau (Galicia) taken by Russian forces (see February 19th, 1915).

Serbian forces begin retreat from the line of the Drina (see November 30th).

Allied Governments present ultimatum to Turkey (see 29th).

Great Britain and France sever diplomatic relations with Turkey. British and French Ambassadors demand passports (see 31st, and November 5th).

Italian Cabinet resign. New Cabinet formed. Signor Salandra remains Premier (previously appointed March 24th, 1914) (see May 13th, 1915).

British hospital ship "Rohilla" wrecked off Whitby.

Lord Fisher appointed First Sea Lord, Great Britain (see 29th, and May 15th, 1915).

October 31

Critical day of Battles of Ypres, 1914: British line broken and restored (see 19th, and November 11th). Battle of Gheluvelt ends (see 29th).

H.M.S. "Hermes" sunk by German submarine in Straits of Dover.

British Government issue orders for hostilities to commence against Turkey (see 30th, and November 1st and 5th).

First units of Indian Expeditionary Force "B" arrive at Mombasa (see 16th, and December 31st).

General Stewart succeeded in command of British forces in East Africa by General Aitken (see September 1st and December 4th).

German light cruiser "Königsberg" located in Rufiji River (see July 11, 1915).

Lord Kitchener sends to Sherif of Mecca conditional guarantee of Arabian independence (see July 14th, 1915).

November 1

Messines taken by German forces (see June 7th, 1917).

Great Britain and Turkey commence hostilities (see 5th, and October 30th and 31st).

Naval action off Coronel. H.M.S. "Good Hope" and "Monmouth" sunk by Admiral von Spee's Squadron (see September 22nd and December 8th).

Martial law proclaimed in Egypt (see September 10th and December 18th ).

November 2

Battles of Messines and Armentières end (see October 12th and 13th).

Battle of La Bassée ends (see October 10th).

Battle of Chyrow ends (see October 13th).

Austrian cruiser "Kaiserin Elizabeth" sunk in Tsingtau harbour.

First units of Indian Expeditionary Force "F" leave India for Egypt (see 16th).

Government of India announce immunity of the Mussulman Holy Places during hostilities with Turkey.

Russia declares war on Turkey (see October 29th).

"State of War" commences between Serbia and Turkey.

British Admiralty declare the North Sea a military zone.

British force begins attack on Tanga (German East Africa) (see 5th).

November 3

First German naval raid British coast near Gorleston and Yarmouth.

Grand Fleet ordered back to Scapa Flow (see October 18th, 1914, and November 21st, 1918) .

Northern frontier of German East Africa first crossed by British troops. (Affair of Longido.) (See August 15th.)

Allied squadrons bombard forts at entrance of the Dardanelles (see December 13th).

Baron Sonnino appointed Italian Foreign Minister (see October 16th and 30th, 1914, and May 13th, 1015).

November 4

German cruiser "Karlsruhe" sunk in the Atlantic by internal explosion (see August 6th).

German cruiser "Yorck" sunk by mine off the German coast.

Russian forces cross frontier of Turkey-in-Asia and seize Azap.

Moratorium in Great Britain ends (see August 2nd).

November 5

Great Britain and France formally declare war on Turkey (see 1st and 11th, and October 31st).

Great Britain annexes Cyprus.

Attack on Tanga ends. British force repulsed (see 2nd, and July 7th, 1916).

Belgian Government reject Papal mediation (see July 30th, 1915).

November 6

Advanced troops of Indian Expeditionary Force "D" effect landing in Mesopotamia at Fao (see 22nd, and October 23rd).

Turkey severs diplomatic relations with Belgium.

British submarine "B.-11" proceeds two miles up the Dardanelles. (First warship to enter Straits.) (See December 13th).

Keupri-Keui (Armenia) taken by Russian forces (see 14th).

French Government issue declaration modifying list of contraband (see August 25th, 1914, and January 3rd, 1915).

November 7

Tsingtau capitulates to Japanese forces (see September 2nd and 23rd, 1914, and August 6th, 1915).

November 9

German cruiser "Emden" destroyed by H.M.A.S. "Sydney" at the Cocos Islands (see October 28th).

German gunboat "Geier" interned at Honolulu.

British and French Governments conclude convention as to naval "prizes" (see August 6th, 1914, and January 15th, 1917).

November 10

Battle of the Yser ends (French date) (see October 10th).

Dixmude stormed by German forces (see September 29th, 1918).

Przemysl again isolated by Russian forces (see October 9th). Second Siege begins (see March 22nd, 1915).

British force storms Sheikh Saïd (Southern Arabia) and destroys the defences (10th/11th).

November 11

Battle of Nonneboschen (Ypres). Attack by German Guard repulsed (see 22nd, and October 19th and 31st).

Memel (East Prussia) occupied by Russian forces (approximate date) (see February 17th, 1015).

The Sheikh ul Islam issues Fatwa declaring Jehad (Holy War) against all the Allies (see 2nd, 5th, and 14th).

H.M.S. "Niger" sunk by German submarine off Deal.

November 12

Orders issued for all British aeroplanes on Western front to bear distinguishing marks (see September 28th).

November 13

Dutch Government protest against modifications of the Declaration of London (see October 29th).

Lieut.-General Sir A. Barrett takes over command of Indian Expeditionary Force "D" in Mesopotamia (see September 28th, 1914, and April 9th, 1915).

November 14

Keupri-Keui (Armenia) retaken by Turkish forces (see 6th).

Field-Marshal Earl Roberts dies in France.

Sultan of Turkey as Khalif proclaims Jehad against those making war on Turkey or her allies (see 11th).

Japanese Cabinet decide against despatch of troops or warships to Europe (see February 8th, 1916, and April 17th, 1917).

November 15

Battle of Cracow begins (see December 2nd).

Second Russian invasion of North Hungary begins (see October 8th and December 12th).

Affair of Saihan (Mesopotamia).

November 16

First units of Indian Expeditionary Force "F" land in Egypt (see 2nd, and March 25th, 1915).

Second German offensive against Warsaw. Battle of Lodz begins (see December 15th).

November 17

Libau (Baltic) bombarded by German squadron (see August 2nd).

German cruiser "Friedrich Karl" sunk by mine in the Baltic.

Trebizond (Black Sea) bombarded by Russian squadron (see April 6th, 1916).

Affair of Sahil (Mesopotamia).

November 18

Re-transfer of French Government from Bordeaux to Paris begins (see September 2nd).

November 20

British, Belgian, and French Governments withdraw proposal for neutralisation of African free trade zone in view of altered situation (see August 22nd).

November 21

British naval air raid on Friedrichshaven.

November 22

Battles of Ypres, 1914, ends (see October 19th, 31st, and November 11th, 1914, and April 22nd, 1915).

War Office assume control of the British operations in East Africa. Basra (Mesopotamia) occupied by British forces (see 6th). Formal occupation took place on the 23rd.

Keupri-Keui (Armenia) again taken by Russian forces (see 14th, and December 17th).

November 23

Netherlands Overseas Trust formed (see June 3rd, 1915).

Portuguese Government announce prospective co-operation of Portugal with Great Britain (see August 8th, 1916).

November 26

H.M.S. "Bulwark" destroyed by internal explosion in Sheerness harbour.

November 27

General von Hindenburg promoted Field-Marshal (see September 18th, 1914, and August 29th, 1916).

November 28

Affair of Miranshah (North-West Frontier of India) (28th/29th). First outbreak on North-West Frontier of India caused by German intrigues.

November 30

Battle of Lowicz-Sanniki begins (see December 17th).

Belgrade evacuated by retreating Serbian forces (see October 30th).

December 1

Battle of Limanova-Lapanov begins (see 17th).

First units of Australian and New Zealand Expeditionary Forces arrive at Suez (see October 10th and 17th, 1914, and February 20th and April 25th, 1915).

General de Wet, the leader of South African rebellion, captured by Union troops (see 28th, and September 15th).

December 2

Austrian forces cross the Danube and occupy Belgrade (see 15th, and November 30th).

Battle of Cracow ends (see November 15th).

December 3

Battle of the Kolubara (Serbia) begins (see 6th).

British Government agree to Japanese request that Australia should not occupy German islands north of the Equator (see 16th).

December 4

First action of Qurna (Mesopotamia) begins (see 8th).

General Wapshare succeeds General Aitken in command of the British forces in East Africa: latter recalled (see October 31st and November 5th, 1914, and April 16th, 1915).

Portuguese Expeditionary Force leaves Lisbon for Angola (see October 26th, 1914, and August 8th, 1916).

December 5

Entente démarche in Athens, Sofia, and Bukharest to secure help for Serbia (see 6th, and January 24th, 1915).

Serbian Government declare that Serbia will never make peace without Allied consent.

December 6

Battle of the Kolubara ends. Austrian forces routed by the Serbians and driven northwards (see 3rd).

Rumanian Government decline to guarantee Greece against German attack (see 5th).

December 7

British Envoy (Sir H. Howard) appointed to the Vatican.

December 8

First action of Qurna ends (see 4th).

Battle of the Falklands. Admiral von Spee's squadron destroyed. "Scharnhorst," "Gneisenau," "Leipzig," and "Nürnberg" sunk. Admiral von Spee killed (see November 1st). "Dresden" escapes (see March 14th, 1915).

December 9

Qurna occupied by British forces (see 8th).

December 10

Field-Marshal von der Goltz leaves Germany to take over control of the Turkish Army (see November 24th. 1915, and April 19th, 1916).

Batum (Georgia) bombarded by the "Goeben" and "Breslau."

December 11

Dr. B. L. Machado Guimarães, Portuguese Premier, resigns (appointed June 23rd, 1914) (see 12th).

December 12

Second Russian invasion of North Hungary ends (see November 15th).

Senhor V. H. d'Azevedo Coutinho appointed Portuguese Premier (see 11th, and January 25th, 1915).

December 13

Turkish battleship "Messoudieh" sunk by British submarine "B.-11" in the Dardanelles (see November 6th).

December 14

Allied demonstrations on Flanders front begin. Attack on Wytschaete.

German armed merchant cruiser "Cormoran" (ex-Russian S.S. "Ryasan") interned at Guam.

December 15

Battle of Lodz ends (see November 16th).

Belgrade occupied by Serbian forces (see 2nd). End of Second Austrian invasion of Serbia (see October 6th and 9th, 1915).

German airship sighted off East Coast of England (first appearance of hostile aircraft in vicinity of British Isles (see 21st).

December 16

Scarborough and Hartlepool (East coast of England) bombarded by German battle cruiser squadron.

Japanese Foreign Minister declares Japan will not give up German islands occupied north of the Equator (see 3rd, and February 14th, 1917).

December 17

Battle of Lowicz-Sanniki ends (see November 30th).

Battle of Limanova-Lapanov ends (see 1st).

Turkish Offensive in the Caucasus begins. Keupri-Keui retaken (see 29th, November 22nd, 1914, and January 17th, 1916).

December 18

British Protectorate over Egypt proclaimed.

Meeting of Scandinavian Kings at Malmo.

Battle of the Rawka-Bzura begins. This battle had no definite end; operations subsided into trench warfare.

December 19

British Government declare Khedive Abbas Hilmi deposed, and proclaim Prince Hussein Kamel Pasha as Sultan of Egypt (see October 9th, 1917).

Great Britain declares adherence to Franco Moorish-Treaty of 1912.

December 20

First Battle of Champagne begins (see March 17th, 1915).

British defence of Givenchy, 1914 (20th/21st).

December 21

First German air raid on England. Aeroplane drops bombs in sea near Dover (see 24th, January 19th, 1915, and July 20th and August 5th, 1918).

Jasin (East Africa) occupied by British forces (see January 18th and 19th, 1915).

December 23

British Proclamation issued containing revised list of contraband (see September 21st, 1914, and March 11th, 1915).

December 24

Second air raid on England (see 21st). First bomb dropped on English soil (near Dover).

December 25

British seaplane raid on Cuxhaven.

December 26

Italian force lands at Valona; Italy notifies Austria of provisional occupation (see May 29th, 1915).

Garibaldi's Italian Foreign Legion in action for first time on French front.

December 28

End of organised rebellion in South Africa (see September 15th, 1914, and January 11th, 1915).

December 29

Battle of Sarikamish (Caucasus) begins (see 17th, and January 2nd, 1915).

British Government send memorandum to United States Government in defence of British blockade policy.

December 30

Russian Commander-in-Chief (Grand Duke Nicholas) suggests a British expedition against the Turks to ease Russian situation in the Caucasus (see January 13th, 1915).

December 31

Indian Expeditionary Force "C" (East Africa) absorbed into Indian Expeditionary Force "B" (see September 1st and October 31st).

1915

January 1

H.M.S. "Formidable" sunk by German submarine in the English Channel.

January 2

Battle of Sarikamish ends (see December 29th, 1914, and April 4th,1918).

Urmia (North Persia) evacuated by Russian forces (see April 16th). This city was occupied by Russian forces before the outbreak of the War.

January 3

French Government issue further revised list of contraband (see November 6th, 1914).

January 4

London Stock Exchange reopens (see July 31st, 1914).

January 5

German attack on Edea (Cameroons) repulsed by French garrison.

Tabriz (North Persia) evacuated by Russian forces (see 8th and 30th). This city was occupied by Russian forces before the outbreak of the War.

January 6

German S.S. "Dacia" (interned in the United States) sold to Mr. Breitung, an American citizen (see February 11th).

January 8

Battle of Soissons begins (see 14th).

Tabriz (North Persia) occupied by Turkish forces (see 5th and 30th).

Battle of Kara Urgan (Caucasus) begins (see 13th).

January 10

British defence of Muscat (Eastern Arabia) (10th/11th).

January 11

Rumanian Government negotiate loan of £5,000,000 in Great Britain.

Last rebels in the Transvaal captured (see December 28th, 1914).

January 12

Mafia Island (German East Africa) seized by a British force.

January 13

Battle of Kara Urgan ends (see 8th).

British War Council resolve that the Admiralty should prepare for a naval expedition in February against the Dardanelles (see 28th, and December 30th, 1914).

Baron Burian succeeds Count Berchtold (appointed February 19th, 1912) as Austro-Hungarian Minister for Foreign Affairs (see December 22nd, 1916).

January 14

Battle of Soissons ends (see 8th).

Swakopmund (German South-West Africa) occupied by South African forces.

January 15

Existence of secret agreement for mutual support between Italy and Rumania announced by respective Governments.

January 18

German attack on Jasin (East Africa) begins (see 19th).

January 19

First airship raid on England (see December 21st, 1914, and August 5th, 1918).

Jasin (East Africa) captured by German forces (see 18th, and December 21st, 1914).

January 21

LieutGeneral von Falkenhayn (appointed in 1906) succeeded as German Minister for War by Lieut-General Wild von Hohenborn (see October 30th, 1916). General von Falkenhayn remains Chief of the General Staff (see August 29th, 1916).

January 23

Defence of Upington (South Africa) (23rd/24th).

January 24

Action of the Dogger Bank. German cruiser "Blücher" sunk.

German airship "P.L.-19" brought down near Libau.

Lieut.-General Sir A. J. Murray resigns as Chief of the General Staff, British Expeditionary Force, France (see 25th, and August 4th, 1914).

LieutGeneral Sir W. Robertson resigns as Quartermaster-General, British Expeditionary Force, France (see 25th and 27th, and August 4th, 1914).

British Government offer Greek Government concessions in Asia Minor in return for help to Serbia (see 25th and 29th, April 12th, 1915, and December 5th, 1914).

January 25

LieutGeneral Sir W. Robertson appointed Chief of the General Staff, British Expeditionary Force, France (see 24th, and December 22nd).

Rumania refuses Entente suggestion that she should join Greece in support of Serbia (see 24th and 29th, October 15th, 1915, and December 6th, 1914).

General Pimenta da Castro succeeds Senhor Coutinho as Portuguese Premier (see December 12th, 1914, and May 14th, 1915).

January 26

Turkish advance on Egypt through Sinai begins (see February 2nd).

Entente Governments agree to hold "Pact of London" applicable to war with Turkey (see September 5th, 1914).

January 27

Lieut.-General Sir R. C. Maxwell appointed Quartermaster-General, British Expeditionary Force, France (see 24th, and December 22nd, 1917).

January 28

British Government definitely decide to make naval attack on the Dardanelles (see 13th).

United States S.V. "William P. Frye" sunk by German armed merchant cruiser "Prinz Eitel Friedrich" (see August 6th, 1914, and April 8th, 1915).

January 29

Walney Island battery (Barrow-in-Furness) shelled by German submarine (first operation of German submarines in the Irish Sea).

Greek Government decline to intervene on behalf of Serbia (set 24th and 25th, and February 15th).

January 30

Tabriz (North Persia) reoccupied by Russian forces (see 8th, and June 14th, 1918).

British Admiralty warn British merchant vessels to fly neutral or no ensigns in vicinity of British Isles (see February 6th, 7th and 11th).

January 31

Arab forces (Idrisi) occupy Farasan Islands in the Red Sea (see April 28th).

February 1

British Admiralty issue orders forbidding neutral fishing vessels to use British ports.

February 2

Turkish advance-guards reach the Suez Canal (see 3rd, and January 20th).

Aden Protectorate invaded by Turkish forces.

Entente communication to Greek, Serbian, and Montenegrin Governments deprecating their intervention in Albania (see June 26th).

February 3

Actions on the Suez Canal begin (see 4th).

Bulgarian Government negotiate loan of £3,000,000 in Germany (see August 6th).

Agreement concluded between Great Britain and Belgium concerning delimitation of Uganda-Congo boundary.

February 4

The Winter Battle in Masuria (East Prussia) begins (see 22nd).

Actions on the Suez Canal end (see 3rd). Turkish forces retreat into Sinai.

German Government announce that submarine blockade of Great Britain will begin on the 18th February.

February 5

British, French and Russian Governments agree to pool their financial resources (see June 3rd).

February 6

British S.S. "Lusitania" arrives at Liverpool flying United States flag (see 7th, January 30th and May 7th).

February 7

British Foreign Office issue statement justifying use of neutral flag at sea (see 6th, 11th, and January 30th).

February 9

1st Canadian Division crosses from England to France (9th/llth) (see October 15th, 1914).

February 11

United States Government send Note to British Government deprecating use of neutral flag (see 7th).

S.S. "Dacia" sails from United States for Bremen (Germany) with cargo of cotton (see 27th, and January 6th)

February 15

Entente Governments suggest to Greek Government that Greece should intervene in support of Serbia, and promise military support at Salonika (see January 29th and March 5th).

Mutiny of the 5th Light Infantry (Indian Army) at Singapore.

Agreement concluded between Great Britain and France supplementing "prize" convention of November 9th, 1914.

February 16

Oyem (Cameroons) occupied by French forces.

British Government decide to send a division (the 29th) to the Dardanelles (see 20th, and April 25th).

British Government extend prohibition of "trading with the enemy" to territories in British, enemy, or friendly occupation.

February 17

Czernowitz (Bukovina) retaken by Austrian forces (see October 28th. 1914, and June 17th, 1916).

Memel reoccupied by German forces (see November 11th, 1914, and March 18th, 1915).

German airship "L.-3" stranded and destroyed off Fano, and "L.-4" destroyed near Blaavands Huk (Denmark).

February 18

German submarine blockade of Great Britain begins (see 4th).

February 19

Allied naval attack on the Dardanelles forts commences (see March 18th).

Stanislau (Galicia) captured by Austrian forces (see October 30th, 1914, and March 4th, 1915).

Norwegian S.S. "Belridge" torpedoed, but reaches port. First ship torpedoed by German submarine without warning (see October 20th, 1914, and March 13th, 1915). German Government subsequently asserted that this ship was attacked in error.

February 20

Orders issued for employment at the Dardanelles of the Australian and New Zealand troops in Egypt (see 16th, and December 1st, 1914).

Muavin ed Douleh succeeds Ala es Sultaneh as Persian Foreign Minister (see August 19th, 1914, and April 26th, 1915).

February 22

The Winter Battle in Masuria ends (see 4th).

Battle of Przasnysz begins (see 27th).

Net barrage across North Channel (between Ireland and Scotland) established.

South African Northern Force begins advance from Swakopmund on Windhuk (see January 14th).

February 23

Lemnos (Ægean) occupied by British marines (see March 7th).

February 24

The first British Territorial division (the North Midland) leaves England for France. Not to be confused with first division of the New Armies, for which see May 9th.

February 26

Liquid fire first used by the Germans on the Western front.

February 27

Battle of Przasnysz ends (see 22nd).

S.S. "Dacia" intercepted and seized by French naval forces (see 11th, and March 22nd).

March 1

British blockade of German East Africa commences.

Antivari bombarded by Austrian squadron (see January 22nd, 1916).

Joint declaration signed by Great Britain and France to prevent trade by or with Germany (see April 17th, 1916).

March 4

Stanislau (Galicia) recaptured by Russian forces (see February 19th and June 8th).

French Government decide to send Expeditionary Force to the Dardanelles (see February 16th and 20th, and April 25th).

First case of "indicator" nets aiding in the destruction of a German submarine ("U.-8," in Straits of Dover). First experimented with in January 1915.

Russian Government send circular telegram to Entente Governments laying claim to Constantinople (see 12th).

March 5

Greek Premier (M. Venizelos) proffers Greek fleet and troops to Entente for operations at the Dardanelles (see 6th, and February 15th and September 21st).

Bombardment of Smyrna by British squadron under Admiral Peirse begins (see 9th).

March 6

King of Greece refuses assent to policy of M. Venizelos (see 5th). M. Venizelos resigns office as Premier (see 9th, and August 22nd) (date of appointment October 19th, 1910).

March 7

Greek Government request explanation of British occupation of Lemnos (see 9th, and February 23rd).

March 9

British bombardment of Smyrna ends (see 5th and 15th).

M. Gounaris appointed Premier of Greece (see 6th, and August 22nd).

British Government reply to Greek Government as to occupation of Lemnos, pleading military necessity (see 7th and 20th).

March 10

Battle of Neuve Chapelle begins (see 13th).

March 11

British "Retaliatory Order in Council" relating to detention of enemy goods and Proclamation extending list of "absolute" contraband issued (see 12th, and December 23rd, 1914).

March 12

Dutch Government issue warning that foreign merchant ships using Dutch flag will be detained (see January 30th and February 11th).

British Government notify Russian Government of their acceptance of Russian claims to Constantinople (see 4th, April 12th, 1915, and December 2nd, 1916).

French Government issue decrees similar to British Order in Council and Proclamation of the 11th March.

General Sir Ian Hamilton appointed Commander-in-Chief, Mediterranean (Dardanelles) Expeditionary Force (see 17th).

March 13

Battle of Neuve Chapelle ends (see 10th).

Agreement signed by French and Belgian Governments suspending Franco-Belgian Convention of July 30th, 1891, regarding military service laws.

Swedish S.S. "Hanna" torpedoed without warning. First neutral ship actually sunk by German submarine (see 25th and 28th, and February 19th).

March 14

Light cruiser "Dresden," the last German cruiser left at sea, sunk by British warships in Chilean waters off Juan Fernandez (see December 8th, 1914, and April 26th, 1915).

Mushir ed Douleh succeeds Mustaufi ul Mamalek as Persian Prime Minister (see August 19th, 1914, and April 26th, 1915).

March 15

British Squadron blockading Smyrna withdrawn (see 5th and 9th).

First merchant ship (S.S. "Blonde") attacked by aircraft.

March 17

French Government lodge claim with British Government to Syria and Cilicia (see April 26th, 1916).

General Sir Ian Hamilton takes over command of Dardanelles Expeditionary Force (see 12th, and October 15th).

First Battle of Champagne ends (see December 20th, 1914).

March 18

Allied Naval attack on the Dardanelles forts repulsed (see February 19th). French battleship "Bouvet" and British battleships "Irresistible" and "Ocean" sunk.

Memel (East Prussia) again captured by Russian forces (see 21st, and February 17th).

General Sir John Nixon appointed Commander-in-Chief British Forces in Mesopotamia (see April 9th).

British Government conclude agreement with American cotton interests that cotton should be contraband.

March 19

Dutch Government lodge protest against blockade policy of the Entente (see 11th and 12th).

March 20

Action of Jakalswater (German South-West Africa).

British Government guarantee Greece eventual cession of Lemnos by Turkey (see 9th and July 25th).

March 21

Memel (East Prussia) reoccupied by German forces (see 18th).

First German airship raid on Paris takes place (see August 30th, 1914, and January 29th, 1916).

March 22

Przemysl capitulates to Russian forces (see November 10th, 1914, and June 3rd, 1915).

French Prize Court declare seizure of S.S. "Dacia" valid (see February 27th).

March 23

First kite-balloon ship, H.M.S. "Manica," commissioned.

Chinese and Japanese Governments conclude secret agreement as to future policy in Manchuria.

March 25

Indian Expeditionary Force "F" (in Egypt) absorbed into Indian Expeditionary Force "E" (see October 2nd, 1914, and November 2nd and 16th, 1914).

General Liman von Sanders appointed to command Turco-German Forces, Dardanelles.

Dutch S.S. "Medea" captured by German submarine and sunk. (First neutral ship sunk after visit and search) (see 13th).

March 27

Bosporus forts bombarded by Russian Black Sea Fleet (see April 25th).

March 28

The first passenger ship (British S.S. "Falaba") sunk by a German submarine (see 13th, and October 20th, 1914).

March 29

British Government conclude agreement with American rubber interests that rubber should not be exported except to Great Britain.

March 30

Aus (German South-West Africa) occupied by South African forces.

April 3

Russian Imperial ukase issued granting municipal self-government to Russian Poland (see August 14th, 1914, and November 5th, 1916).

Indecisive action in Black Sea between the "Goeben" and part of the Russian Fleet. Turkish cruiser "Medjidieh" sunk by mine off Odessa.

Dover Straits barrage completed.

April 7

First Indian units of Indian Expeditionary Force "G" (formed from Force "E") sail from Egypt for the Dardanelles (see December 31st).

April 8

Deportations and massacres of Armenians by order of the Turkish Government commence (approximate date) (see May 24th).

German armed merchant cruiser "Prinz Eitel Friedrich" interned at Newport News, Va. (see January 28th).

April 9

General Sir John Nixon relieves General Sir Arthur Barrett as Commander-in-Chief Indian Expeditionary Force "D" Mesopotamia (see November 13th, 1914, March 18th, 1915, and January 19th, 1916).

April 12

Battle of Shaiba (Mesopotamia) begins (see 14th).

First Allied advance on Yaunde (Cameroons) begins (see June 7th and 28th).

Entente Governments make offer to Greece of Smyrna and hinterland in return for immediate action against Turkey (see 14th, and January 24th).

French Government notify Russian Government of their acceptance of Russian claims to Constantinople (see March 12th).

April 14

Germans accuse French of using poison gas near Verdun (see 22nd).

Battle of Shaiba (Mesopotamia) ends (see 12th).

Greek Government reject Entente offer of Smyrna (see 12th).

British Secretary for the Colonies (Mr. Harcourt) states that Dominions will be consulted as to peace terms (see July 14th).

Japanese Government inform British Government of German overtures for separate peace.

April 16

Urmia (North Persia) occupied by Turkish regular forces (see January 2nd and May 24th).

General Tighe succeeds General Wapshare in command of British Forces in East Africa (see December 4th, 1914, and February 19th, 1916).

April 17

Capture of Hill 60 (Ypres) (17th/22nd).

April 18

Operations of Allied Force for capture of Garua (Cameroons) begin (see May 31st).

First Affair of Hafiz Kor (North-West Frontier of India).

April 20

Armenian revolt at Van: Armenian defence of Van begins (see May 19th).

April 22

Battles of Ypres, 1915, begin (see November 22nd, 1914, and May 25th, 1915). First German gas attack (see 14th).

April 23

Battle of Gravenstafel Ridge (Ypres) (22nd/23rd).

British blockade of the Cameroons commences (see February 29th 1916).

April 24

Battle of St. Julien (Ypres) begins (see May 4th).

April 25

Allied Forces effect landing at the Dardanelles (25th/26th).

Bosporus forts shelled by Russian Black Sea Fleet (see March 27th).

Action of Gibeon (25th/26th) (German South-West Africa).

April 26

Secret agreement signed in London between Italian Government and the Entente for Italian co-operation in the war and declarations by which Italy adheres to the Pact of London (see September 5th, 1914, and May 4th, November 30th, and December 1st, 1915).

The last German raider overseas (armed merchant cruiser "Kronprinz Wilhelm") interned at Newport News (United States of America) (see March 14th).

French cruiser "Leon Gambetta" sunk by Austrian submarine in Straits of Otranto.

Mushir ed Douleh, Persian Prime Minister, resigns (see March 14th and April 27th).

Muavin ed Douleh, Persian Foreign Minister, resigns (see February 20th and April 27th).

April 27

Ain ed Douleh appointed Persian Prime Minister (see 26th, and August 17th).

Mohtashem ed Douleh appointed Persian Foreign Minister (see 26th, and March 5th, 1916).

April 28

First Battle of Krithia (Dardanelles) (see May 6th).

British Government conclude a treaty with the Idrisi for co-operation against the Turks (see January 31st).

April 30

Shavli (Baltic Provinces) occupied by German forces (see May 11th).

May 1

Austro-German Spring Offensive in Galicia: Battle of Gorlice-Tarnow begins (see 5th).

Battle of Dilman (North Persia).

S.S. "Gulflight" torpedoed without warning: damaged, but reaches port. First United States ship attacked by German submarine (see February 19th and March 13th).

May 4

Italy denounces the Triple Alliance (see April 26th).

Battle of St. Julien (Ypres) ends (see April 24th).

May 5

Battle of Gorlice-Tarnow ends (see 1st).

May 6

Battle of Krithia (Dardanelles) begins (see 8th, and April 28th).

May 7

Libau (Baltic Provinces) taken by German forces (see April 30th).

S.S. "Lusitania" sunk by German submarine "U.-20" off Queenstown (see February 6th).

British Foreign Minister (Sir E. Grey) gives conditional guarantee to Serbian Minister of eventual cession of Bosnia and Herzegovina with "wide access to the Adriatic" (see August 15th and 30th).

Japan presents ultimatum to China demanding territorial concessions (see 9th).

May 8

Battle of Frezenberg Ridge (Ypres) begins (see 13th).

Battle of Krithia ends (see 6th, and June 4th).

May 9

Allied Spring Offensive begins:—

Battle of Aubers Ridge.

Second Battle of Artois begins (see June 18th).

The leading division of the British New Armies leaves England for France (see August 21st, 1914, and February 24th, 1915).

President Wilson, in a speech, defines United States policy in regard to the "Lusitania" outrage (see 7th).

Chinese Government yield to Japanese demands (see 7th and 25th).

May 10

Naval Convention signed between Great Britain, France, and Italy.

May 11

Shavli evacuated by German forces (see April 30th).

May 13

Battle of Frezenberg Ridge (Ypres) ends (see 8th).

Windhuk (German South-West Africa) occupied by South African Northern Force.

H.M.S. "Goliath" sunk by Turkish destroyer in the Dardanelles.

Signor Salandra, Italian Premier, tenders his resignation (see 16th, and October 30th, 1914).

Baron Sonnino, Italian Foreign Minister, tenders his resignation (see 16th, and November 3rd, 1914).

May 14

Jaroslaw taken by Austro-German forces (see September 21st, 1914).

Last meeting of British War Council (see August 5th, 1914, and June 7th, 1915).

General da Castro, Portuguese Premier, resigns (see 15th, and January 25th).

May 15

Battle of Festubert begins (see 25th).

Senhor J. Pinheiro Chagas appointed Portuguese Premier (see 14th, and June 19th).

Lord Fisher, First Sea Lord, Great Britain, tenders his resignation (see 28th, and October 30th, 1914).

May 16

Battle of the San (Galicia) begins (see 23rd).

Signor Salandra reappointed Italian Premier on reconstruction of Cabinet, with Baron Sonnino as Foreign Minister (see 13th, and June 11th, 1916).

May 19

Van (Armenia) taken by Russian forces. Armenian garrison relieved (see April 20th and August 3rd, 1915, and April 5th, 1918).

May 21

Russian Expeditionary Force to West Persia lands at Enzeli (see February 17th, 1918).

May 23

Battle of the San ends (see 16th).

Italian Government order Mobilisation and declare war against Austria.

General Cadorna appointed Commander-in-Chief of Italian Armies in the Field (see November 7th, 1917). Officially designated "Chief of Staff," the King being the nominal Commander-in-Chief.

May 24

Battle of Bellewaerde Ridge (Ypres) (24th/25th).

Battle of Przemysl begins (see June 3rd and 11th).

Battle of the Stryj (Galicia) begins (see June 11th).

Italian forces cross Austrian frontier (midnight 24th/25th).

Germany severs diplomatic relations with Italy (see August 28th, 1916). For the purposes of the Treaty of Versailles it was subsequently assumed that this rupture took place on the 27th, which date was accepted as that of the commencement of Italy's belligerence against Germany.

Urmia (North Persia) retaken by Russian forces (see April 16th).

Entente Governments declare that they will hold Turkish Ministers personally responsible for the Armenian massacres (see April 8th).

May 25

Battles of Ypres, 1915, end (see April 22nd, 1915, and July 31st, 1917).

Battle of Festubert ends (see 15th).

H.M.S. "Triumph" sunk by submarine off the Dardanelles.

Italian fleet commences operations in the Adriatic (see 26th).

Coalition Ministry formed in Great Britain by Mr. Asquith (see December 11th, 1916).

Treaty signed between China and Japan concerning Shantung Province (see 7th and 9th).

Treaty signed between China and Japan concerning South Manchuria and Inner Mongolia (see 7th and 9th).

May 26

Italian Government announce blockade of Austro-Hungarian coast. British battle squadron concentrates at Malta prior to joining Italian fleet in Adriatic (see 27th).

May 27

British squadron joins Italian fleet in the Adriatic (see 26th).

H.M.S. "Majestic" sunk by submarine at the Dardanelles.

Mr. Winston Churchill, First Lord of the Admiralty, Great Britain, resigns (appointed October 24th, 1911) (see 28th).

British minelayer "Princess Irene" destroyed by internal explosion in Sheerness harbour.

May 28

Mr. Arthur Balfour appointed First Lord of the Admiralty, Great Britain (see 27th, and December 11th, 1910).

Sir Henry Jackson appointed First Sea Lord, Great Britain (see 15th, and December 3rd, l916).

Dr. Joaquim T. Braga elected President of Portugal (see 29th, and October 5th).

May 29

Valona formally occupied by Italian forces (see December 26th, 1914).

Dr. Manoel Arriaga, Portuguese President, resigns (appointed August 24th, 1911) (see 28th).

May 30

Affair of Sphinxhaven (Lake Nyassa). British command of the lake secured.

May 31

Siege of Garua (Cameroons) begins (see April 18th and June 10th).

First German airship raid on London area (see January 19th 1915, October 19th, 1917, and August 5th, 1918).

Second action of Qurna (Mesopotamia).

June 2

Blockade of coast of Asia Minor announced by British Government.

June 3

Przemysl retaken by Austro-German forces (see March 22nd and May 24th).

Amara (Mesopotamia) captured by British forces.

First meeting in Paris of Allied Conference on Economic War (see February 5th, 1915, and June 14th, 1916).

Act passed in British Parliament empowering Customs to compel all exports to Holland to be consigned to the Netherlands Oversea Trust (see November 23rd, 1914, and December 7th, 1915).

San Marino declares war on Austria-Hungary.

June 4

Third Battle of Krithia (Dardanelles).

June 5

First Conference of British and French Ministers to co-ordinate war policy and strategy held at Calais.

June 7

German airship "L.Z.-37" destroyed in mid-air by Lieut. Warneford, R.N.A.S., near Ghent (first occasion of airship successfully attacked by aeroplane).

Russian and Chinese Governments conclude agreement respecting Mongolia (see May 25).

First meeting of Dardanelles Committee of the British Cabinet (see May 14th and October 30th). Under this title the War Council (see August 5th, 1914, and May 14th, 1915) exercised its functions during the critical period of the Dardanelles campaign.

Allied Commander-in-Chief in the Cameroons decides to abandon the advance on Yaunde (see 28th, and April 12th).

June 8

Stanislau recaptured by Austrian forces (see March 4th, 1915, and August 10th, 1916).

June 9

Monfalcone (Isouzo) taken by Italian forces.

June 10

Garua (Cameroons) capitulates to the Anglo-French force under General Cunliffe (see May 31st).

June 11

Battle of Przemysl ends (see 3rd, and May 24th).

Battle of the Stryj ends (see May 24th).

June 14

Turkish Attack on Perim (l4th/15th).

June 17

Third Battle of Lemberg begins (see 22nd).

June 18

Second Battle of Artois ends (see May 9th and September 25th).

June 19

South African forces begin advance on Otavifontein (see July 1st).

Dr. Jose de Castro succeeds Senhor J. P. Chagas as Portuguese Premier (see May 15th and November 29th).

June 22

Third Battle of Lemberg ends: city retaken by the Austrian forces (see 17th, and September 3rd, 1914, and November 23rd, 1918).

June 24

Mr. Lansing succeeds Mr. Bryan as United States Secretary of State.

June 26

San Giovanni de Medua (Albania) occupied by Montenegrin forces (see July 29th).

General Sukhomlinov, Russian Minister for War, removed from office (appointed in 1909) ; succeeded by General Polivanov (see March 29th, 1916).

June 27

British advance up the Euphrates begins (see July 25th).

June 28

Action of Gully Ravine (Dardanelles) begins (see July 2nd).

Operations of the first advance on Yaunde (Cameroons) end (see 7th).

Ngaundere (Cameroons) captured by the Allied Northern Force.

June 29

First Battle of the Isonzo begins (see July 7th).

July 1

Second Battle of Krasnik begins (see 19th).

Otavifontein (German South-West Africa) captured by South African forces (see June 19th).

July 2

Action of Gully Ravine ends (see June 28th).

Naval action in the Baltic between Russian and German squadrons off Gottland. German minelayer "Albatross" driven ashore.

Munitions of War Act, 1915, becomes law in Great Britain.

Ministry of Munitions formed in Great Britain.

July 4

Lahej (South Arabia) taken by Turkish forces (4th/5th).

Durazzo occupied by Serbian forces (see 17th, and October 4th, 1914).

July 7

First Battle of the Isonzo ends (see June 29th).

Italian cruiser "Amalfi" sunk by Austrian submarine in the Adriatic.

July 9

German South-West Africa capitulates to General Botha (see September 19th, 1914).

July 11

German light cruiser "Königsberg" destroyed in Rufiji River, German East Africa, by British monitors (see September 20th and October 31st, 1914).

British residency at Bushire (South Persia) attacked by Tangistani tribesmen (see August 8th).

July 13

Great Austro-German Offensive on Eastern front begins.

July 14

A Dominion Premier (Sir R. Borden, Canada) for the first time attends meeting of the British Cabinet (see April 14th).

Sherif of Mecca opens direct negotiations with British Government for co-operation against the Turks (see October 31st, 1914, and October 24th, 1915).

July 15

National Registration Act becomes law in Great Britain (see August 15th).

July 17

Durazzo evacuated by the Serbian forces at request of Italian Government (see 4th, and August 31st).

Treaty of alliance signed at Sofia between Austria-Hungary, Bulgaria, Germany, and Turkey. Albania to be ceded to Bulgaria in return for Bulgarian participation in war.

July 18

Second Battle of the Isonzo begins (see August 10th).

Italian cruiser "Giuseppe Garibaldi" sunk by Austrian submarine in the Adriatic.

July 19

Second Battle of Krasnik ends (see 1st).

July 21

Ivangorod (Poland) invested by Austro-German forces (see August 5th).

July 22

Bukoba, on Victoria Nyanza (German East Africa), captured by British forces (22nd/23rd).

July 24

Rozan and Pultusk (North Poland) stormed by German forces.

July 25

Nasiriya (Mesopotamia) taken by British forces (see June 27th).

British Government guarantee to Greece eventual cession of Mitylene by Turkey (see March 20th).

July 26

Pelagosa Island, in Adriatic, occupied by Italian forces.

July 29

Entente Governments warn Montenegro that they will not recognise her occupation of Albanian territory (see June 26th).

Establishment of the East Persia Cordon (Anglo-Russian) begins (see October 7th).

July 30

The Pope sends appeal for peace to belligerent Governments (see November 5th, 1914, and August 1st, 1917).

August 1

Constantinople harbour raided by British submarine.

August 3

Van (Armenia) evacuated by the Russian forces (see 5th, and May 19th).

August 5

Warsaw occupied by German forces (see July 13th).

Ivangorod taken by Austro-German forces (see July 21st).

Van occupied by Turkish forces (see 3rd).

August 6

Operations of the landing at Suvla (Dardanelles) begin (see 15th).

Battle of Sari Bair (Dardanelles) begins (see 9th and 10th).

Dr. Machado Guimarães elected Portuguese President (see October 5th, 1915, and December 11th, 1917).

Bulgarian Government negotiate fresh loan for 400,000,000 francs with Austro-German banks (see February 3rd).

Agreement concluded between Japan and China substituting Japanese authority for German in Tsingtau customs (see November 7th, 1914).

August 8

Bushire (South Persia) occupied by British forces (see July 12th and September 9th).

Turkish battleship "Barbarousse-Hairedine" sunk by British submarine "E.-11" in the Dardanelles.

German naval attack on Riga begins (see 21st).

August 9

Decisive day of Battle of Sari Bair (see 6th and 10th).

Viscount Kato, Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs, resigns (previously appointed April 16th, 1914) (see 10th).

August 10

Battle of Sari Bair ends (see 6th and 9th).

Second Battle of the Isonzo ends (see July 18th).

German airship "L.-12" extensively damaged by British aircraft off Ostend.

Marquis Okuma appointed Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs (ad interim) (see 9th, and September 21st).

August 12

First ship sunk by torpedo from British seaplane (Dardanelles).

August 13

H.M.T. "Royal Edward" sunk in the Ægean by German submarine. First transport so lost.

August 15

Operations of the landing at Suvla end (see 6th and 21st).

Entente Governments make conditional offer of territorial acquisitions to Serbia (see 30th, and May 7th).

National Register taken in Great Britain (see July 15th).

August 16

Lowca and Harrington, near Whitehaven (Cumberland), shelled by German submarine.

August 17

Kowno stormed by German forces (17th/18th).

Ain ed Douleh, Persian Prime Minister, resigns (see 18th, and April 27th).

August 18

Mustaufi ul Mamalek again appointed Persian Prime Minister (see 17th, and December 24th).

August 19

German battle cruiser "Moltke" torpedoed by British submarine "E.-1" in Gulf of Riga.

British submarine "E.-13" attacked by German warships while aground in Danish waters.

British S.S. "Arabic" sunk by German submarine.

H.M.S. "Baralong" (special service ship) destroys German submarine "U.-27."

August 20

Novo-Georgievsk (Poland) stormed by German forces.

August 21

Battle of Scimitar Hill (Suvla) (see 15th).

Italy declares war on Turkey.

First authenticated case of German submarine firing on a ship's crew in open boats (British S.S. "Ruel").

German naval attack on Riga discontinued (see 8th).

August 22

Osovets (North Poland) stormed by German forces.

M. Venizelos again appointed Premier of Greece in succession to M. Gounaris (see March 6th and 9th and October 5th).

August 25

Brest-Litovsk (Poland) taken by German forces (25th/26tb).

August 26

Byelostok (Poland) taken by German forces.

August 30

British Foreign Minister (Sir E. Grey) informs M. Supilo that, provided Serbia agreed, the Allies could guarantee the eventual freedom and self-determination of Bosnia, Herzegovina, South Dalmatia, Slavonia, and Croatia (see 15th, and May 7th).

August 31

Durazzo reoccupied by Serbian forces (see July 17th and December 6th).

September 1

German Government inform United States Government that United States demands for limitation of submarine activity are accepted.

Ruad Island, off Syrian coast, occupied by French forces.

September 3

Grodno captured by German forces (2nd/3rd).

September 5

The Tsar supersedes the Grand Duke Nicholas in supreme command of the Russian Armies with General Alexeiev as Chief of Staff (see 8th, August 3rd, 1914, and March 15th and June 4th, 1917). Though nominally Chief of Staff, General Alexeiev was virtually Commander-in-Chief ad performed the duties of that office till the Tsar's abdication on March 15th, 1917, and continued as Commander-in-Chief thereafter without further appointment.

Action of Hafiz Kor (North-West Frontier of India).

September 7

Russian counter-offensive in Galicia. Battle of Tarnopol begins (see 16th).

September 8

The Grand Duke Nicholas appointed Viceroy of the Caucasus (see 5th).

Second Allied Attack on Mora (Cameroons) (8th/9th).

September 9

Battle of Dvinsk begins (see November 1st).

Battle of Vilna begins (see October 2nd).

Bushire (South Persia) again attacked by tribesmen (see August 8th).

Turco-Bulgarian Frontier Convention signed at Dimotika.

United States Government request recall of Austro-Hungarian Ambassador, Dr. Dumba (appointed to United States, March 1913) (see 28th).

September 16

Pinsk taken by German forces.

Battle of Tarnopol ends (see 7th).

September 18

Yilna taken by German forces (see 9th).

September 21

Bulgarian Government order partial mobilisation (see 22nd).

Greek Premier (M. Venizelos) asks for guarantee of 150,000 British and French troops as condition for Greek intervention (see 24th, and March 5th).

Viscount Ishii succeeds Marquis Okuma as Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs (see August 10th, 1915, and October 9th, 1910).

September 22

"Dede Agatch Agreement" concluded between Turkey and Bulgaria rectifying Turkish frontier in favour of Bulgaria.

Bulgarian Government order general mobilisation for 25th.

Second Advance on Yaunde (Cameroons) begins (see January 1st, 1916).

September 23

Greek Government order precautionary mobilisation.

September 24

French and British Governments inform Greek Government that they are prepared to send troops requested (see 21st, 27th, and 28th).

September 25

Allied Autumn Offensive begins:—

Battle of Loos begins (see October 8th).

Third Battle of Artois begins (see June 18th and October 15th).

Second Battle of Champagne begins (see March 17th and November 6th).

General Sir J. Wolfe Murray, Chief of the Imperial General Staff, Great Britain, resigns (see 26th, and October 26th, 1914).

Bulgarian mobilisation begins (see 22nd).

Serbian Government give undertaking to Greek Government to cede Doiran and Gevgeli eventually to Greece, and not to claim Strumitsa.

September 26

Lieut-General Sir A. J. Murray appointed Chief of the Imperial General Staff, Great Britain (see 25th, and January 24th and December 22nd).

September 27

Greek Premier (M. Venizelos) obtains secret consent of King Constantine to proposed Entente expedition to Salonika (see 24th and 28th).

Italian battleship "Benedetto Brin" destroyed by internal explosion in harbour at Brindisi.

September 28

Battle of Kut, 1915 (Mesopotamia).

Dr. Dumba, Austro-Hungarian Ambassador, recalled from United States of America (see 9th).

Greek Government formally refuse French and British "offer" of the 24th (see 27th, and October 2nd).

British and Russian Governments agree to request of Persian Government for a monthly subvention.

September 30

Lord Derby assumes control of recruiting in Great Britain (see December 11th, 1916).

October 1

Approximate beginning of period in which the Germans obtained mastery in the air on the Western front (due to the Fokker machine) (see April 1st, 1916).

October 2

Battle of Vilna ends (see September 9th).

Greek Premier (M. Venizelos) asks British and French Governments to land troops at Salonika as soon as possible (see 3rd and 5th, and September 28th).

October 3

Allied troops arrive at Salonika: Greek Government protest against a landing (see 2nd, 5th and 6th).

First German merchant vessel (S.S. "Livonia") sunk by British submarine in the Baltic.

October 4

Entente Powers send ultimatum to Bulgaria (see 5th and 13th).

October 5

French and British forces land at Salonika (see 3rd).

King of Greece refuses to support policy of Premier (M. Venizelos) (see 2nd, and September 27th).

M. Venizelos again resigns (see 6th, and August 22nd, 1915, and June 26th, 1917).

Russia severs diplomatic relations with Bulgaria (see 4th and 19th).

Dr. Machado Guimarães succeeds Dr. J. Braga as Portuguese President (see May 28th, and August 6th, 1915, and December 11th, 1917).

October 6

Final Austro-German invasion of Serbia begins (see December 15th, 1914).

M. Zaimis appointed Greek Premier (see 5th, and November 5th).

King of Greece gives assurance to British Minister that Greece will maintain neutrality, but Greek mobilisation (see September 23rd) and Allied disembarkation at Salonika will proceed (see 3rd, 5th and 8th).

October 7

Austro-German forces effect passage of the Save and Danube (see 6th).

Birjand (East Persia) occupied by British forces (see July 29th).

October 8

Battle of Loos ends (see September 25th).

New Greek Government (see 6th) announce policy of armed neutrality.

October 9

Belgrade taken by Austrian forces (see December 15th, 1914, and November 1st, 1918).

Second Affair of Hafiz Kor (North-West Frontier of India).

October 10

Greek Government reject Serbian claim for help under Serbo-Greek Treaty of 1912.

October 11

Hostilities commence between Bulgarian and Serbian forces (see 14th).

Semendria (Serbia) taken by Austrian forces (see 6th).

October 12

Miss Edith Cavell shot in Brussels by order of a German court-martial.

October 13

Most severe airship raid on East Coast of England and London; casualties 200 (see January 19th and May 31st, 1915, October 19th, 1917, and August 5th, 1918).

Great Britain severs diplomatic relations with Bulgaria (see 4th and 15th).

Hostilities commence between French and Bulgarian forces in Macedonia.

M. Delcassé French Foreign Minister, resigns; M. Viviani succeeds temporarily (see 29th and 30th).

October 14

Bulgaria and Serbia declare war on one another (see 4th and 11th) .

October 15

Third Battle of Artois ends (see September 25th).

Great Britain declares "state of war" with Bulgaria (see 13th).

Montenegro declares "state of war" with Bulgaria.

Rumanian Government refuse to aid Serbia (see January 25th).

Vranje (Serbia) taken by Bulgarian forces (see October 5th, 1918).

General Sir Charles Monro appointed to succeed Sir Ian Hamilton as Commander-in-Chief, Mediterranean Expeditionary Force (see 17th and 28th, and March 17th).

October 16

France declares "state of war" with Bulgaria (see 4th and 15th).

British Government offer Cyprus to Greece if she will support Serbia (see 20th, and January 24th).

Entente Governments proclaim blockade of Ægean coast of Bulgaria.

October 17

General Sir William Birdwood takes over temporary command of Mediterranean Expeditionary Force from Sir Ian Hamilton (see 15th and 28th).

October 18

Third Battle of the Isonzo begins (see November 3rd).

October 19

Ishtip (Serbia) taken by Bulgarian forces (see September 25th, 1918).

Russia and Italy declare war on Bulgaria (see 4th and 5th).

Japan declares adherence to the Pact of London (see September 5th, 1914, and November 30th, 1915).

October 20

Greek Government reject British offer of Cyprus (see 16th).

October 21

Dede Agatch (Bulgaria) bombarded by Allied squadron.

Veles taken by Bulgarian forces (see Septemer 25th, 1918).

October 22

Kumanovo and Üsküb (Skoplje) taken by Bulgarian forces.

Shabatz taken by Austrian forces.

October 23

German cruiser "Prinz Adalbert" sunk by British submarine "E.-8" in the Baltic.

October 24

Negotin, on River Vardar, taken by Bulgarian forces.

First Action of Krivolak (Macedonia).

British Government in letter to Sherif of Mecca define territorial limits of proposed Arab State (see July 14th, 1915, and June 5th, 1916).

October 28

H.M.S. "Argyll" wrecked on east coast of Scotland.

Lieut.-General Sir Bryan Mahon appointed General Officer Commanding British Forces, Balkans (see May 9th, 1916).

General Sir Charles Monro assumes command of Mediterranean Expeditionary Force (see 15th, 17th, and November 4th).

October 29

M. Viviani, French Premier and Foreign Minister, resigns (date of appointment as Premier June 14th, 1914) (see 13th and 30th).

M. Millerand, French Minister for War, resigns (see 30th, and August 27th, 1914).

October 30

Third Allied attack on Mora (Cameroons) begins (see November 4th).

Second Action of Krivolak (Macedonia).

M. Briand succeeds M. Viviani as French Premier and Foreign Minister (see 29th, and March 17th, 1917).

General Galliéni appointed French Minister for War (see 29th, and March 16th, 1916).

Last meeting of Dardanelles Committee of the British Cabinet (see June 7th and November 3rd).

November 1

Kragujevatz (North Serbia) taken by Austro-German forces (30th/1st).

Battle of Dvinsk ends (see September 9th).

November 2

British Premier (Mr. Asquith) declares Serbian independence to be an essential object of the war.

Kasvin (West Persia) occupied by a Russian force.

November 3

Third Battle of the Isonzo ends (see October 18th).

Serbian Government leave Nish (see 23rd, and July 25th, 1914).

First meeting of newly-constituted War Committee of British Cabinet to replace the Dardanelles Committee (see October 30th, 1915, and December 1st, 1916).

Port and Transit Executive Committee formed in Great Britain (see 10th).

November 4

Third Allied attack on Mora abandoned (see October 30th).

Banyo (Caineroons) attacked by General Cunliffe's Allied force (see 6th).

Lord Kitchener leaves England for the Dardanelles (see 10th).

General Sir Charles Monro appointed to command Salonika Force.

Sir William Birdwood to command Mediterranean Expeditionary Force (see 25th, and October 15th, 17th, and 28th).

November 5

Nish taken by Bulgarian forces (see 3rd, and October 11th, 1918).

Battle of Kachanik (Serbia) begins (see 8th).

M. Zaimis, Greek Prime Minister, resigns (see 6th, and October 6th).

German airship "L.Z.-39" destroyed near Grodno.

November 6

Second Battle of Champagne ends (see September 25th).

Sollum (Western Egypt) attacked by German submarine (see 14th). Egyptian coastguard cruiser "Abbas" sunk and "Nur el Bahr" disabled.

Banyo captured by Allied force (see 4th).

M. Skouloudhis appointed Greek Premier (see 5th, and June 21st, 1916).

November 7

German cruiser "Undine" sunk by British submarine "E.-19."

Italian S.S. "Ancona" sunk by Austrian submarine.

November 8

Battle of Kachanik ends (see 5th).

Entente loan (£1,600,000) to Greece concluded (see July 20th, 1916).

November 10

Fourth Battle of the Isonzo begins (see December 10th).

Indian Corps begins to leave France for Mesopotamia (see October 19th, 1914).

Lord Kitchener arrives at the Dardanelles (see 4th).

Ship Licensing Committee formed in Great Britain: Order in Council prohibits voyages between foreign ports except under licence (see February 15th, 1916).

Requisitioning (Carriage of Foodstuffs) Committee formed in Great Britain: Order in Council authorises requisition of ships for carriage of foodstuffs (see November 3rd, 1917).

November 11

First British advance on Baghdad begins (see 22nd).

November 14

Senussi commence hostilities against British by attacking Egyptian post at Sollum (see 6th and 23rd).

November 15

Representatives of Central Powers leave Teheran (Persia) on approach of Russian forces.

November 16

Babuna Pass and Prilep (South Serbia) taken by Bulgarian forces (see September 23rd, 1918).

November 17

Anglo-French Conference held in Paris to discuss aid to Serbia and Dardanelles expeditions. Project approved in principle to appoint Council of War to co-ordinate Allied action (see December 29th).

British hospital ship "Anglia" sunk by mine off Dover.

November 20

Novi Bazar taken by Austrian forces (see October 14th, 1918).

November 22

Battle of Ctesiphon (Mesopotamia) begins (see 25th).

General Sir H. Smith-Dorrien appointed Commander-in-Chief of British forces in East Africa (see January 31st, 1916). Did not take over command owing to illness.

November 23

Rovereto (Trentino) taken by Italian forces.

Mitrovitza and Pristina (Serbia) taken by Austro German forces (see October 10th, 1918).

Serbian Government leave Prizren for Scutari (Shkodra) (see 3rd, and December 3rd).

British military operations against the Senussi commence (see December 13th, 1915, and February 8th, 1917): Sollum post evacuated (see 14th).

Entente Powers send Note to Greek Government demanding non-interference with Allied troops, and guaranteeing eventual restoration of occupied Greek territory (see 24th, and October 3rd).

British Government conclude preliminary agreement with the Netherlands Overseas Trust for rationing of Holland (see June 3rd, 1915, and June 30th, 1916).

November 24

Greek Government accept Entente demands of the 23rd.

Field-Marshal von der Goltz (see December 10th, 1914, and April 19th, 1916) takes command of Turkish forces in Mesopotamia.

Danish merchants and manufacturers conclude agreement with the British Government to restrict supplies to Germany.

November 25

British retreat from Ctesiphon to Kut al Amara begins (see 22nd, and December 3rd).

M. Albert Thomas announces arrangements completed for inter-Allied organisation of munitions.

General Sir Charles Monro appointed Commander-in-Chief reconstituted Mediterranean Expeditionary Force with Sir William Birdwood General Officer Commanding Dardanelles Army (see 4th, and January 9th, 1916).

November 29

Dr. A. Augusto da Costa succeeds Dr. J. de Castro as Portuguese Premier (see June 19th, 1915, and March 15th, 1916).

November 30

Serbian retreat through Albania begins (see January 15th, 1916).

Formal signature of the Pact of London by Great Britain, France, Russia, Japan, and Italy (see September 5th, 1914; April 26th, 1915; and October 19th, 1915).

December 1

Prizren (Serbia) taken by Bulgarian forces (see October 11th, 1918).

Italy announces her adherence to the Pact of London (see November 30th).

December 2

Monastir (Serbia) taken by Bulgarian forces (see November 19th, 1916).

French retreat from Serbia to Salonika begins: Krivolak evacuated.

December 3

British forces, retreating from Ctesiphon, reach Kut (see 7th, and November 25th).

General Joffre, Chief of French General Staff from July 28th, 1911, appointed Commander-in-Chief French Armies. Appointment of Chief of General Staff lapses (see April 29th, 1917).

Serbian Government and military headquarters set up at Scutari (Shkodra) (see November 23rd, 1915, and January 15th, 1916).

December 4

United States Government request recall of German attachés Captains Boy-Ed and Von Papen (see 10th).

December 5

Action of Demir Kapu (5th/6th) in French retreat from Serbia.

Kut placed in state of defence (see 3rd and 7th).

December 6

Durazzo bombarded by Austrian squadron (see 20th, and August 31st).

Ipek (Montenegro) taken by Austro-German forces (see October 14th, 1918).

British Government put economic pressure on Greece by making the "export restrictions" apply to that country (see 13th).

December 7

Siege of Kut begins (see 3rd, and January 4th and April 29th, 1916).

Actions of Kosturino (7th/8th). British retreat from Macedonia begins.

Agreement concluded between French Government and Netherlands Oversea Trust (see November 23rd, 1914, and November 23rd, 1915).

December 8

Evacuation of Suvla and Anzac ordered (see 19th and 20th).

Debra and Okhrida (Serbia) taken by Bulgarian forces.

December 9

General Castelnau appointed Chief of Staff to General Joffre (see 3rd).

General Sarrail demands withdrawal of Greek troops from Salonika (see 11th).

December 10

Fourth Battle of the Isonzo ends (see November 10th).

German Government recall from United States attachés Von Papen and Boy-Ed (see 4th, and January 15th, 1916).

December 11

Doiran and Gevgeli (South Serbia) taken by Bulgarian forces (see September 22nd, 1918).

Greek Government refuse Entente demand for withdrawal of Greek troops from Salonika (see 9th).

Yuan-Shih-Kai accepts throne of China (see March 22nd, 1916, and June 6th, 1916).

December 13

Affair of the Wadi Senab (11th/13th) (see November 23rd, 1915, and February 26th, 1916).

British Government order partial relaxation of economic pressure on Greece (see 6th).

December 14

Hamadan (Western Persia) occupied by Russian forces (see August 10th, 1916).

Bulgarian and Greek General Staffs conclude agreement establishing temporary neutral zone along Greek frontier.

December 15

The last Allied forces in Macedonia withdrawn into Greek territory (see 7th, and September 19th, 1916).

Qasr-i-Shirin (Western Persia) occupied by Turkish forces (see May 7th, 1916).

Field-Marshal Sir John French resigns as Commander-in-Chief of British armies in France (see 19th, and August 4th, 1914, and May 5th, 1918).

December 17

German light cruiser "Bremen" sunk by British submarine in the Baltic.

December 19

Evacuation of Suvla and Anzac begun (see 8th and 20th).

General Sir Douglas Haig succeeds Sir John French as Commander-in-Chief of the British Armies in France (see 15th, and January 1st, 1917).

Bulgarian and Greek General Staffs conclude agreement establishing temporary neutral zone along Greek frontier.

December 20

Evacuation of Suvla and Anzac completed (see 8th, 19th and 28th).

Durazzo occupied by Italian forces (see 6th, and February 27th, 1916).

December 22

LieutGeneral Sir W. Robertson resigns as Chief of the General Staff, British Expeditionary Force, France (see 23rd, and January 25th), and is succeeded by Lieut.-General L. E. Kiggell (see January 27th, 1918).

Lieut.-General Sir A. J. Murray, Chief of the Imperial General Staff, resigns (see 23rd, and September 26th, 1915, and March 19th, 1916).

December 23

British naval operations on Lake Tanganyika begin (see 26th).

General Sir W. Robertson appointed Chief of the Imperial General Staff (see 22nd, and February 18th, 1918).

"Trading with the Enemy (Extension of Powers) Act, 1915" (beginning of "Black List" policy), comes into force in Great Britain (see January 26th and July 28th, 1916).

December 24

Mustaufi ul Mamalek (Persian Prime Minister) resigns (see 25th, and August 18th).

December 25

Turkish Christmas Eve Attack on Kut (24th/25th).

Affair of the Wadi Majid (Western Egypt).

Kangavar (Western Persia) occupied by a Russian force. Prince Firman Firma appointed Prime Minister of Persia (see 24th, and March 5th, 1916).

December 26

German raider "Moewe" sails from Bremen on first cruise (see February 1st, 1916).

Naval action on Lake Tanganyika: German gunboat "Kingani" captured by H.M.S. "Mimi" and "Toutou" (see 23rd, and February 9th, 1916).

Treaty concluded between British Government and Ibu Sa'ud, Emir of Nejd (see July 18th, 1916).

December 28

Evacuation of remainder of Gallipoli Peninsula ordered (see 20th, and January 8th, 1916).

December 29

Durazzo raided by Austrian naval light forces: latter brought to action in Southern Adriatic.

Draft rules approved for Inter-Allied Council of War (see November 17th).

December 30

Consuls of Central Powers at Salonika arrested and deported by order of General Sarrail, Commanding French troops.

H.M.S. "Natal" destroyed by internal explosion in Cromarty harbour.

December 31

Last units of Indian Expeditionary Force "G" leave the Dardanelles to amalgamate with Indian Expeditionary Force "E" in Egypt (see April 7th).

This work derives from Principle Events 1914-1918, compiled by The Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence, and originally published by H.M. Stationery Office, in 1922; as part of the History of the Great War. It was prepared from the OCR text of the PDF copy held by the Internet Archive (urn:oclc:record:1050840522).

Only Part I of the book - the general chronological list - is reproduced in this work. Parts II and III give different presentations of entries in Part I. An ongoing effort will introduce semantic mark-up, with a view to being able to derive the presentation in Parts II and III (and more) from the chronological list.

1914, 1915, 1916, 1917, 1918

Principal Events 1914-1918

1918

January 1

Arab forces begin Actions for Et Tafile (see 28th).

M. Hyams succeeds Baron de Broqueville as Belgian Minister for Foreign Affairs (see August 4th, 1917).

January 2

Air Ministry formed in Great Britain.

January 3

The Air Council takes over functions of Air Board (see May 17th, 1916, and November 29th and December 21st, 1917).

Ukraine delegation reaches Brest-Litovsk (see November 21st, 1917, and February 1st, 1918).

January 4

British hospital ship "Rewa" sunk by submarine in Bristol Channel.

Russian Bolshevik Government and French and Swedish Governments recognise the independence of Finland (see 10th, and December 6th, 1917).

British Government in message to the King of the Hejaz declare intentions with regard to future status of Palestine (see December 17th, 1917, and February 4th, 1918).

Allied request for handing over of Dutch ships in Allied ports formulated (see March 7th).

January 5

British Premier (Mr. Lloyd George) in speech to Trade Union delegates outlines British War Aims (see 24th, and December 28th, 1917).

Negotiations again suspended on Russian front. Bolshevik demand made for meetings to be held at Stockholm (see 8th, and December 6th, 13th and 22nd, 1917).

January 8

Qasr-i-Shirin (Western Persia) occupied by British forces (see July 8th, 1917).

President Wilson delivers Message to Congress laying down the "Fourteen Points" (see February 11th).

Russian Bolshevik Government withdraw demand for transfer to Stockholm and resume negotiations at Brest-Litovsk (see 5th and 22nd).

January 10

British Government assure Russian Bolshevik Government of their support in the creation of an independent Poland (see April 5th, 1917, and February 20th, 1918).

Danish and Norwegian Governments recognise the independence of Finland (see 4th).

January 12

Latvia declares independence (see November 11th).

January 13

Estonian Government issue declaration of independence (see November 28th, 1917, and February 25th and November 11th, 1918).

January 14

German destroyers bombard Yarmouth (Norfolk).

January 18

Russian Constituent Assembly again meet in Petrograd (see 19th, and December 13th, 1917).

January 19

Russian Constituent Assembly again forcibly dissolved by Bolsheviki (see 18th, and December 13th, 1917).

Mustaufi ul Mamalek succeeds Ain ed Douleh as Persian Prime Minister (see November 24th, 1917, and May 3rd, 1918).

Mushaver ul Mamalek succeeds Ala es Sultaneh as Persian Foreign Minister (see June 6th, 1917, and August 10th, 1918).

January 20

Naval action outside the Dardanelles. German cruiser "Breslau" and British monitor "Raglan" sunk. "Goeben" strikes mine and is beached (see 27th).

January 22

Russian Bolshevik Government accuse Central Powers of falsification of reports of proceedings (see 8th and 23rd).

January 23

Negotiations between Russian Bolshevik Government and Central Powers once more suspended (see 8th, 22nd and 30th).

January 24

Count Hertling and Count Czernin (German Imperial Chancellor and Austrian Foreign Minister) make public replies to statements of President Wilson and Mr. Lloyd George on War Aims (see 5th and 8th).

Lieut.-General The Hon. Sir H. A. Lawrence appointed Chief of the General Staff, British Expeditionary Force, France (see 27th). Did not take up appointment till the 27th.

January 27

Turkish Dead Sea Flotilla seized by Arab camelry at El Mezraa'.

General Dunsterville's Mission leaves Baghdad for North-West Persia (see February 17th).

The "Goeben" refloated inside the Dardanelles (see 20th).

Lieut.-General Sir L. E. Kiggell, Chief of the General Staff, British Expeditionary Force, France, resigns (see 24th, and December 22nd, 1915).

January 28

Russian Bolshevik Government sever diplomatic relations with Rumania.

Actions for Et Tafile by the Arab forces end (see 1st).

January 30

Negotiations between Russian Bolshevik Government and Central Powers again resumed (see 23rd, and February 10th).

February 1

Central Powers recognise the Ukraine Republic (see 9th, and November 20th, 1917).

Extension of the British East Persia Cordon (see July 29th, 1915) into Khorasan begins. In relief of Russian forces withdrawn by Bolshevik Government.

February 3

British Government announce enlargement of powers of Supreme War Council at Versailles (see November 7th, 1917, and December 1st, 1917).

February 4

General Alexeiev with Don Cossacks moves towards Moscow against the Bolshevik forces (see 13th).

British Government make declaration to King of the Hejaz re-affirming their pledges as to freeing the Arab peoples (see October 24th, 1915, December 15th, 1916, December 17th, 1917, and January 4th, 1918).

February 5

British S.S. "Tuscania," carrying United States troops, sunk by submarine off Irish coast. (The only loss sustained by U.S. transports when under British naval escort.)

February 6

German Government send ultimatum to Rumania demanding peace negotiations within four days (see 25th).

M. Bratianu, Rumanian Premier, resigns (appointed January 14th, 1914) (see 9th).

February 9

Peace signed at Brest-Litovsk between Bulgaria, Central Powers and Turkey and the Ukraine Rada; also supplementary Treaty between Central Powers and The Ukraine; borders of new Ukrainian State defined (see 1st, and January 3rd).

New Rumanian Cabinet formed, with General Averescu as Premier and Foreign Minister (see 6th, and March 12th).

February 10

M. Trotski announces that state of war between Russia and Central Powers, Bulgaria and Turkey is ended, but that Russia will not sign formal peace treaty (see 18th, and January 30th).

February 11

President Wilson delivers Message to Congress laying down four additional Points (see January 8th and October 6th).

February 13

General Alexeiev defeated by the Bolsheviki (see 4th); General Kaledin commits suicide.

February 15

Third German destroyer raid in Straits of Dover (night 15th/16th) (see April 20th, 1017).

Representatives of Allied Governments arrange establishment of the "Allied Maritime Transport Council" (see December 3rd, 1917, and March 11th, 1918).

February 10

Dover shelled by German submarine.

February 17

General Dunsterville's Mission reaches Enzeli (North-West Persia) (see May 21st, 1915, January 27th and April 1st, 1918).

February 18

Armistice terminates on Russian front. Hostilities resumed by German armies (see 10th and 19th). Dvinsk taken by German forces.

General Sir W. Robertson, Chief of the British Imperial General Staff, resigns (see 19th, and December 23rd, 1915).

February 19

Russian Bolshevik Government notify willingness to sign Peace Treaty with Germany (see 18th and 28th).

General Sir H. H. Wilson appointed Chief of the British Imperial General Staff (see 18th).

February 20

British Foreign Minister (Mr. Balfour) informs Polish National Committee that Great Britain does not accept the treaty between The Ukraine and Central Powers (see 9th, January 10th, and June 3rd).

February 21

Jericho taken by British forces (19th/21st).

Ministry of Information formed in Great Britain.

February 23

Inter-Allied Labour and Socialist Conference in London pass resolution as to War Aims.

February 24

Trebizond (Asia Minor) retaken by Turkish forces (see April 17th, 1916).

Dorpat (Estonia) occupied by German forces (see December 26th).

German raider "Wolff" returns to Germany (see December 1st, 1916).

February 25

Pernau, Reval, and Pskov taken by German forces (see 18th).

Kirmanshah (Western Persia) occupied by British forces (see March 11th, 1917).

Peace negotiations begun at Bukharest (see 6th, and March 5th).

Military Convention signed at Bobruisk between Germany and Poland.

British Government inform M. Tonisson that they are prepared provisionally to recognise the independence of Estonia until the future status of Estonia is settled by the Peace Congress (see January 13th and November 11th).

February 26

British hospital ship "Glenart Castle" sunk by submarine in the Bristol Channel (see March 1st, 1917).

February 28

Negotiations again resumed between Russian Bolshevik Government and Central Powers: hostilities nominally cease (see 18th, 19th, and March 3rd).

March 1

Treaty of Peace and Amity signed between the Finnish Social Republic of Workmen and the Russian Federal Soviet Republic.

March 2

Kiev (Ukraine) captured by German forces (see December 20th).

German force landed in the Aaland Islands at request of Finnish Government (see 3rd).

March 3

Meshed (Persia) occupied by troops of British East Persia Cordon. Approximate date.

Peace signed between Bolshevik Russia and Central Powers, Bulgaria and Turkey at Brest-Litovsk, together with supplementary treaties by the signatories (see 14th and 18th, February 28th and August 27th).

German Government notify Swedish Government of occupation of the Aaland Islands (see 2nd).

March 4

Narva (Estonia) occupied by German forces (see November 28th).

March 5

Preliminary treaty of peace between Rumania and the Central Powers, Bulgaria and Turkey signed at Buftea (see December 9th, 1917, and February 25th and May 7th, 1918).

March 7

First German aeroplane raid on England undertaken on moonless night (see July 20th).

Peace signed at Berlin between Germany and Finland.

Final Allied Note presented to Netherlands Government re surrender of Dutch ships in Allied ports (see 18th, and January 4th).

March 8

M. Chichérin appointed Russian Foreign Minister and M. Trotski appointed Minister for War (see November 8th, 1917).

March 9

Hit (on the Euphrates) occupied by British forces.

Treaty of Peace signed between Rumania and Bolshevik Russia (see 5th).

March 10

British hospital ship "Guildford Castle" attacked by German submarine in Bristol Channel, but reaches port.

March 11

First meeting of the Allied Maritime Transport Council (see February 15th).

March 12

Erzerum retaken by Turkish forces (see February 16th, 1916).

General Averescu, Rumanian Premier and Foreign Minister, resigns (see 21st, and February 9th).

March 13

Odessa occupied by German forces (ses December 11th).

March 14

Congress of Soviets meet at Moscow to ratify treaty of peace with Central Powers (see 3rd).

March 15

German Government proclaim protectorate over an independent Kurland.

March 16

Hamadan (West Persia) evacuated by the Russian regular forces (see March 2nd, 1917).

March 17

Nicolaiev (South Russia) captured by German forces (see April 8th).

March 18

Entente Governments issue Note refusing to recognise Russo-German peace treaty (see 3rd and 14th).

Dutch Government accept with reservations the Allied terms for use of Dutch shipping in United States and Entente ports (see 7th and 21st).

March 20

Allied Blockade Committee formed.

March 21

First Battles of the Somme, 1918, begin with Battle of St. Quentin (21st/23rd) (see November 18th, 1910, and April 5th, 1918).

Passage of the Jordan by British forces (21st/23rd).

Destroyer action in North Sea between Allied and German flotillas (see October 17th, 1914).

Dutch ships in British ports requisitioned by British Government, and Dutch ships in United States ports requisitioned by United States Government (see 18th).

M. Marghiloman appointed Rumanian Premier (see 12th, and November 8th).

M. Constantino Arian appointed Rumanian Foreign Minister (see 12th, and November 8th).

March 23

Paris first shelled by long range gun (from Crépy-en-Valois, 75 miles distant) (see August 15th).

March 24

First Battle of Bapaume (24th/25th): Bapaume and Péronne taken

by German forces (see March 17th and 18th, 1917, and August 29th and September 1st, 1918).

First action of Es Salt (Palestine) (24th/25th).

March 25

Noyon taken by German forces (see March 18th, 1917, and August 29th, 1918).

German airship raid on Naples from the Dalmatian coast.

March 26

Albert, Chaulnes, and Roye taken by German forces (see March 17th, 1917, and August 22nd and 27th, 1918).

Action of Khan Baghdadi (Mesopotamia) (26th/27th).

"Doullens Agreement" concluded. Decision taken to appoint

General Foch to co-ordinate efforts of British and French Armies (see April 14th).

March 27

Battle of Rosières (Somme) (26th/27th).

Montdidier taken by German forces (see August 10th).

First British attack on Amman (Palestine) (27th/30th).

March 28

First Battle of Arras, 1918 (see August 26th).

Ana (Mesopotamia) occupied by British forces.

March 29

Poltava (South Russia) captured by German forces.

April 1

Enzeli (Persia) evacuated by the Russian regular forces (see February 17th).

German Expeditionary Force for Finland leaves Danzig (see 3rd).

Royal Flying Corps and Royal Naval Air Services of Great Britain amalgamated and established a separate service as the Royal Air Force.

April 3

German Expeditionary Force lands in South Finland at Hangö (see 1st, 13th, and December 16th).

Ekaterinoslav (South Russia) taken by German forces.

April 4

Battle of the Avre (France).

Sarikamish (Russian Caucasus) occupied by Turkish Eorces (see January 2nd, 1915).

British submarines at Helsingfors destroyed to avoid capture (3rd/4th) (see 3rd).

April 5

Battle of the Ancre, 1918, brings to an end the First Battles of the Somme, 1918 (see March 21st).

Japanese and British marines land at Vladivostok (see August 2nd and 3rd).

Van (Armenia) retaken by Turkish forces (see May 19th, 1915).

April 8

Kharkov (South Russia) captured by German forces.

April 9

Battles of the Lys begin (see 29th): Battle of Estaires (9th/11th); Neuve Chapelle taken by German forces.

Count Mirbach appointed German Ambassador at Moscow (see July 6th).

National Council of the Moldavian Republic (Bessarabia) pass Act of Union with Rumania, with stipulation for local autonomy (see 16th, December 23rd, 1917, and December 10th, 1918).

April 10

Battle of Messines, 1918 (10th/11th): Messines taken by German forces (see June 14th, 1917, and September 28th, 1918).

Monrovia (Liberia) bombarded by a German submarine (see August 4th, 1917).

Third Military Service Act passed in British Parliament. Military age limit raised to 50, and Conscription extended to Ireland (see 18th, and June 8th, 1916).

Settlement Treaty between Germany and Turkey ratified at Berlin (see January 11th, 1917).

Agreement reached between Italy and the Yugo-Slavs ("Pact of Rome").

April 11

Armentières and Merville taken by German forces (see October 11th and 17th, 1914, August 10th and October 3rd, 1918).

French Government publish text of Emperor of Austria's letter to Prince Sixte of Bourbon proposing peace negotiations (see 15th, and March 31st, 1917).

Battle of Estaires ends.

Battle of Messines ends.

April 12

Battle of Hazebrouck (Lys) begins (see 15th).

Last airship raid over England in which casualties were inflicted (27) (see January 19th, 1915, and August 5th, 1918).

Field Marshal Sir Douglas Haig issues Order of the Day to the British Army in France on the serious situation ("Backs to the Wall" order).

April 13

Battle of Bailleul (Lys) begins (see 15th).

Helsingfors (Finland) captured by German forces (12th/14th) (see 3rd and 4th).

Finnish Government announce that all German troops landed in Finland had been despatched at their request.

United Diets of Baltic Provinces adopt resolution to form themselves into a separate State within the German Empire.

April 14

General Foch appointed Commander-in-Chief of Allied Armies in France (see March 26th, August 6th, and November 5th). The Belgian forces were not placed under the command of General Foch.

April 15

Battle of Hazebrouck ends (see 12th).

Battle of Bailleul ends (see 13th). Bailleul taken by the German forces (see October 14th, 1914, and August 30th, 1918).

Raid by British naval light forces on the Kattegat (see November 2nd, 1917).

Batum (Georgia) occupied by Turkish forces (see December 27th).

Count Czernin, Austro-Hungarian Foreign Minister, resigns (see 17th, and December 22nd, 1916).

April 16

Passchendaele reoccupied by German forces (see November 6th, 1917, and September 29th, 1918).

The Ukraine Government issue protest against union of Bessarabia and Rumania (see 9th and 23rd).

April 17

Battle of Kemmel Ridge (Lys) begins (see 19th).

Baron Burian succeeds Count Czernin as Austro-Hungarian Foreign Minister (see 15th, and October 25th).

Dr. Wekerle, Hungarian Premier, resigns (see 27th, and August 21st, 1917).

April 18

Battle of Bethune (Lys).

Third Military Service Act comes into operation in Great Britain (see 10th).

April 19

German forces enter the Crimea.

Battle of Kemmel Ridge ends (see 17th and 26th).

April 20

Lord Derby, Secretary of State for War, Great Britain, resigns (see December 11th, 1916).

Viscount Milner appointed Secretary of State for War, Great Britain.

April 21

Viscount Motono, Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs, resigns (see 22nd, and November 21st, 1916).

April 22

The Trans-Caucasian Council decide to declare independence (night 22nd/23rd) (see September 20th, 1917, and May 6th and 26th, 1918).

Baron Goto appointed Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs (see 21st, and September 28th).

April 23

Blocking raid by British naval light forces on Ostend and Zeebrugge (see May 9th).

Russian Bolshevik Government issue protest against union of Bessarabia and Rumania (see 9th and 16th, and December 10th).

Guatemala declares war on Germany (see April 27th, 1917).

April 24

Actions of Villers-Bretonneux (Somme) (24th/25th).

April 26

Second Battle of Kemmel Ridge (25th/26th): Mount Kemmel stormed by German forces (see 19th, and August 31st).

April 27

Kars (Georgia) occupied by Turkish forces. First contingent of Italian troops arrive on the French front (approximate date).

Dr. Wekerle again appointed Hungarian Prime Minister (see 17th, and October 24).

April 29

The Battle of the Scherpenberg brings to an end the Battles of the Lys (see 9th).

German Government establish a military dictatorship in The Ukraine. General Skoropadski proclaimed Hetman (see May 9th).

April 30

Viborg (Finland) captured by German forces and Finnish White Guards (see 13th).

Second action of Es Salt (Palestine) begins (see May 4th).

May 1

Sevastopol taken by German forces (April 30th/May 1st).

Part of Russian Black Sea Fleet seized by the Germans (see June 21st, 1917, and June 18th and November 26th, 1918).

May 2

Agreement concluded regarding export of sand and gravel from The Netherlands for German use (see July 15th).

May 3

Samsam es Sultaneh succeeds Mustaufi ul Mamalek as Persian Prime Minister (see 31st, and January 19th).

May 4

Second action of Es Salt ends (see April 30th).

Armistice signed at Korenevo between Russia and The Ukraine (German-Ukrainian Command) (see June 12th).

May 5

Field-Marshal Lord French appointed Lord-Lieutenant of Ireland (see December 15th, 1915).

May 6

Turko-German delegates arrive at Batum to negotiate peace with the Georgians and Armenians (see April 22nd, May 20th, and June 8th).

May 7

Kirkuk (Mesopotamia) taken by British forces (see 24th).

Frederickshamn (South Finland) captured by Finnish White Guards: End of the Finnish Civil War. The civil war may be said to have begun about March 1st, 1918.

Final Treaty of Peace signed between Rumania and Bulgaria, Central Powers and Turkey (see March 5th), together with various supplementary treaties between the separate contracting parties (see November 10th).

May 8

Nicaragua declares war on Germany and on Austria-Hungary (see May 18th, 1917).

Rostov (South Russia) captured by German forces.

May 9

Blocking attack on Ostend. H.M.S. "Vindictive" sunk to block the harbour (see April 23rd).

M. Ustemovich proclaimed President of The Ukraine; General Skoropadski remains Hetman (see April 29th).

Joint Trade Committee of Entente Powers formed in Holland.

Dr. da Silva Paes, elected Portuguese President (see December 28th, 1917, and December 14th, 1918).

May 11

Peace signed in Berlin between Finland and Turkey.

May 12

Military Treaty ("Waffenbund") signed between Germany and Austria-Hungary.

May 14

Italian naval raid on Pola Harbour.

May 15

German submarine bombards St. Kilda (Hebrides).

Agreement between Entente Powers, Japan, and China against German penetration in Far East announced.

Dr. S. B. C. da Paes, Portuguese Premier, resigns (see 10th, and December 10th, 1017).

May 16

Agreement signed at Peking between China and Japan for military co-operation against German and Bolshevik aggression (see 19th).

Senhor J. T. de Souza Barboza, appointed Portuguese Secretary of the Interior (see l0th, and December 22nd). The appointment of Premier lapsed between May 15th and December 23rd. During this period the functions of the office were performed by the Secretary of the Interior.

May 17

Sinn Fein leaders arrested in Ireland and interned (see 25th).

May 18

First British retaliatory air raid on German towns. Cologne bombed by day.

Alexandropol (Georgia) occupied by Turkish forces.

May 19

Last German night aeroplane raid on London in which casualties were inflicted; 19 killed and 177 wounded (see May 7th, July 7th, and October 19th, 1917, and August 5th, 1918). There were altogether nineteen aeroplane raids on London during which bombs were dropped, and one air reconnaissance during which no bombs were dropped.

German air raid on British camps and hospitals at Etaples; heavy casualties.

Agreement signed between China and Japan for naval co-operation (see 16th).

May 23

Costa Rica declares war on Germany (see September 21st, 1917).

May 24

Kirkuk (Mesopotamia) evacuated by the British forces (see 7th, and October 25th).

General F. C. Poole lands at Murmansk to organise the North Russia Expeditionary Force (see June 4th, 8th and 23rd).

May 25

British Government publish account of Irish-German plots (see 17th).

May 26

Trans-Caucasian Federal Government (see September 20th, 1917, and April 22nd, 1918), dissolved. Georgia declares independence and forms a National Government. Armenian National Council assume charge of Armenian affairs (see June 8th). Tatar National Council proclaim establishment of a "Republic of Azerbaijan."

May 27

Battle of the Aisne, 1918 ("Third Battle of the Aisne"), begins (see June 6th).

Craonne again taken by German forces (see Max 4th, 1917, and October 12th, 1918).

May 29

Soissons again taken by German forces (see 27th, and August 2nd).

Peace Treaty signed at Vienna between Austria-Hungary and Finland.

May 30

Fère-en-Tardenois taken by German forces (sec 27th, and July 28th).

May 31

German forces reach the Marne. Château-Thierry and Dormans captured (see July 21st).

Battle of the Skra di Legen (Macedonia).

Samsam es Sultaneh, Persian Prime Minister, resigns (see 3rd, and June 20th).

M. G. Cooreman succeeds Baron de Broqueville as Belgian Prime Minister (Baron de Broqueville was appointed in 1911) (see November 21st). Baron de Broqueville and M. Cooreman presided over the Cabinet without the title of Prime Minister (see November 21st).

June 3

British, French, and Italian Governments make declarations supporting national aspirations of Poles, Czecho-Slovaks, and Yugo-Slavs (see February 20th, June 29th, August 13th, September 25th, and November 16th).

June 4

British Marines land at Pechenga (North Russia) (see May 24th).

The Don Cossacks declare independence.

June 5

British Independent Air Force in France constituted under tactical command of Major-General Sir H. M. Trenchard.

June 6

Battle of the Aisne, 1918, ends (see May 27th).

Dutch hospital ship "Koningen Regentes" sunk by mine or torpedo.

General Guillaumat, Allied Commander-in-Chief, Salonika, recalled to Paris (see 15th and 18th, and December 22nd, 1917).

June 7

British force lands at Kem (North Russia) (see May 24th).

Omsk (Siberia) occupied by Czecho-Slovak forces (see November 18th).

June 8

German Expeditionary Force to the Caucasus lands at Poti (Georgia).

Russian Bolshevik Government order Entente forces in North Russia to leave the country (see 30th, and May 24th).

Georgian Government and Armenian National Council sign peace treaties with Turkey (see May 6th and 26th).

Georgian Government sign peace treaty with Germany (see May 6th and 26th).

June 9

Battle of the Matz begins (see 14th).

First sitting of Anglo-German Conference at The Hague on prisoners of war.

June 10

Naval action off Premuda Island (Adriatic). Austrian battleship "Szent Istvan" sunk by Italian motor launch.

June 12

Tiflis (Georgia) occupied by a German force (see 8th, and December 27th).

Kurdamir (East Caucasus) occupied by Turkish forces.

Armistice concluded at Kiev between the whole State of The Ukraine and Russian Bolshevik Republic (see May 4th).

June 14

Battle of the Matz ends (see 9th).

Tabriz (North Persia) again occupied by Turkish forces (see January 30th, 1915).

June 15

Battle of the Piave begins (see 24th).

General Guillaumat appointed Governor of Paris (see 6th).

June 18

Russian battleship "Svobodnaya Rossiya" destroyed in Black Sea to avoid surrender to the Germans (see May 4th).

General Franchet d'Esperey appointed Commander-in-Chief Allied Forces, Salonika (see 6th).

M. Radoslavov, Bulgarian Premier, resigns (date of appointment July 20th, 1913). M. Malinov appointed Premier and Foreign Minister.

June 20

Samsam es Sultaneh reappointed Persian Prime Minister (see May 31st and August 3rd).

June 21

Dr. Ernst Ritter von Seidler, Austrian Premier, resigns (see June 23rd, 1917).

June 23

British Expeditionary Forces "Syren" and "Elope" join the North Russian Expeditionary Force at Murmansk (see 4th, May 24th and July 26th).

June 24

Battle of the Piave ends (see 15th).

June 27

British hospital ship "Llandovery Castle" sunk by submarine off Irish coast.

June 29

United States Government announce their view that all branches of the Slav races should be completely freed from German and Austrian rule (see 3rd).

June 30

First contingent of United States troops arrive in Italy (see November 3rd and 4th, 1917).

Murman Railway from Murmansk to Soroki seized by Allied forces (29th/30th) (see 23rd).

Murman Soviet (Sovdep) decide to support the Entente against the Bolshevik Government (see 8th, and July 7th and November 20th).

Treaty signed between the Czecho-Slovaks and Italy, by which Italy recognises Czecho-Slovak Council and their jurisdiction over nationals.

July 1

Affair of Nyamakura (East Africa) (lst/3rd). Near Quelimane (Portuguese East Africa). This was the most southerly point reached by Colonel von Lettow-Vorbeck's force.

July 3

Sultan Mohammed V of Turkey dies. Mohammed VI succeeds to the throne (see November 14th, 1914).

July 4

Siberian Council declare Independence (see 6th).

July 6

French and Italian forces begin offensive in Albania (see 10th and 22nd).

German Ambassador at Moscow (Count Mirbach) murdered (see April 9th).

Declaration of Siberian Independence cancelled (see 4th).

July 7

Agreement signed between France, Great Britain, United States of America, and Murman Sovdep concerning Allied expedition to Murman Coast (see June 30th).

July 9

Admiral von Hintze succeds Herr von Kuhlmann as German Foreign Minister (see August 5th, 1917, and October 4th, 1918).

July 10

Berat (Albania) taken by Italian forces (see 6th, and February 17th, 1916).

New Government formed at Vladivostok under General Horvat (see August 24th).

July 12

Haiti declares war on Germany (see June 16th, 1917).

Japanese battleship "Kawachi" destroyed by internal explosion.

July 13

Irkutsk (Siberia) occupied by Czecho-Slovak forces (see October 14th).

July 14

Kazan (East Russia) captured by Czecho-Slovak forces.

July 15

Fourth Battle of Champagne begins (see 18th, and April 17th, 1917).

British Government protest against "Sand and Gravel Agreement" between Germany and The Netherlands (see May 2nd).

July 16

Field-Marhal Conrad von Hötzendorff, Commander-in-Chief, Austro- Hungarian Armies, relieved of his command.

Ex-Tsar Nicholas II, ex-Tsaritsa, and family murdered at Ekaterinburg (see March 15th, 1917).

July 18

Fourth Battle of Champagne ends (see 15th).

Second Battle of the Marne begins (see August 7th).

Sir L. Worthington-Evans succeeds Lord Robert Cecil as British Minister for Blockade (see February 23rd, 1916).

July 19

Honduras declares war on Germany (see May 17th, 1917).

British operations in Trans-Caspia begin (see August 26th).

United States cruiser "San Diego" sunk by mine off Fire Island (Atlantic coast).

July 20

German forces retreat across the Marne (see 18th).

Last attempt to attack the British Isles with aeroplanes (unsuccessful) (see December 21st, 1914, and August 5th, 1918). There were altogether 59 aeroplane raids against the British Isles during which bombs were dropped. There were also 11 reconnaissance flights over parts of Great Britain or in the vicinity of the coast when no bombs were dropped.

British defence of Resht (North-West Persia).

July 21

Château-Thierry retaken by Allied forces (see 18th, 20th, and May 31st).

July 22

Allied offensive in Albania checked (see 6th, 10th, and August 22nd).

July 23

Battle of Soissonais and Ourcq begins (see August 2nd). British dates.

July 26

Bulk of French Expeditionary Force troops join the North Russia Expeditionary Force at Murmansk (see June 23rd).

Coup d'etat in Baku: Bolshevik Government replaced by Central Caspian Dictatorship.

British Government declare to M. Petrov that they have no intention of infringing the territorial integrity of Russia (see August 6th).

July 28

Fère-en-Tardenois retaken by Allied forces (see May 30th).

July 30

Field-Marshal von Eichhorn, commanding German Army in The Ukraine, assassinated in Kiev (see April 29th).

August 1

Allied Expeditionary Force attack and capture the defences of Archangel (see 2nd).

August 2

Battle of Soissonais and Ourcq ends (see July 23rd).

Soissons retaken by Allied forces (see May 29th).

Pro-Entente revolution in Archangel. Entente forces enter the town (see 1st).

Japanese Government decide to land troops at Vladivostok (see 11th, and April 5th).

August 3

British troops land at Vladivostok (see 2nd, and April 5th).

British ambulance transport "Warilda" sunk by submarine.

Samsam es Sultaneh, Persian Prime Minister, resigns (see 7th, and June 20th).

August 4

British force arrives at Baku (Caspian Sea) (see 26th, and July 19th).

Bolshevik Committee at Enzeli arrested by British military authorities.

August 5

Last attempt to attack England with airships (unsuccessful - "L.-70" destroyed) (see January 19th, 1015, and April 12th and July 20th, 1918). There were altogether 51 airship raids against the British Isles during which bombs were dropped. There were also 8 attempted raids which either did not reach the coast, or which, for some other reason, failed in action. There were also 59 aeroplane attacks in which bombs were dropped (see July 20th), and 11 aeroplane reconnaissances. Total number of air raids in which, bombs were dropped was 110.

August 6

British Government issue Declaration to Russian peoples, stating that they have no intention of interfering in Russian politics (see July 26th).

General Foch created Marshal of France.

August 7

Second Battle of the Marne ends (see July 18th).

French cruiser "Dupetit Thouars" sunk by submarine in the Atlantic.

Vossuq ed Douleh appointed Persian Prime Minister (see 3rd, and May 29th, 1917).

August 8

Battle of Amiens begins (see 11th).

Battle of Montdidier begins (see 15th).

British Government inform Finnish Government that they are in no way hostile to Finnish aspirations on the Murmau Coast and in Karelia.

August 10

Montdidier retaken by French forces (see 8th, and March 27th).

Mushaver ul Mamalek, Persian Foreign Minister, resigns (see 11th, and January 19th).

August 11

Battle of Amiens ends (see 8th).

German airship "L.-53" destroyed off Frisian coast. (Last German airship to be destroyed.)

First Japanese contingents arrive at Vladivostok (see 2nd and 24th, and September 5th).

Mushaver ul Mamalek reappointed Persian Foreign Minister (see 10th).

August 13

The Czecho-Slovaks declare War on Germany.

British Government recognise the Czecho-Slovaks as an Allied nation (see June 3rd and September 3rd).

Admiral von Capelle, German Minister of Marine, resigns (see 15th, and March 15th, 1916).

August 15

Battle of Montdidier ends (see 8th).

Last bombardment of Paris by German long-range gun (see March 23rd).

Action of Bairam Ali (Trans-Caspia): Trans-Caspian Government defeated by Bolshevik forces.

Vice-Admiral von Behnke appointed German Minister of Marine (see 13th).

August 17

Second Battle of Noyon begins (see 29th).

Slovene National Council meet at Ljubljana (Laibach) November 2nd).

August 18

Merv (Trans Caspia) taken by Bolshevik forces (see November 1st). Approximate date.

British advance in Flanders begins: Action of Outtersteene Ridge.

August 19

Merville retaken by British forces (see April 11th).

August 21

Battles of the Somme, 1918, begin with the Battle of Albert, 1918 (21st/23rd) (see September 3rd).

August 22

Albert recaptured by British forces (see 21st, and March 26th).

Austrian forces begin counter-offensive in Albania (see July 6th and 22nd).

August 24

Coup d'etat by General Horvat at Vladivostok (see July 10th).

Battle of Dukhovskaya (Eastern Siberia) (23rd/24th). Bolsheviki decisively defeated by Allied forces: Japanese, with one British battalion.

August 26

Battles of Arras, 1918, begin with Battle of the Scarpe, 1918 (see 30th, March 28th and September 3rd).

Berat (Albania) retaken by Austrian forces (see 22nd, and July 10th and October 1st).

Defence of Baku (Caspian Sea) against Turkish attack begins (see 4th, July 19th and September 15th).

August 27

Roye recaptured by British forces (see March 26th).

British force occupies Krasnovodsk on Caspian Sea.

German and Russian Bolshevik Governments conclude complementary treaty of peace (see March 3rd).

August 28

Affair near Kaakhka (Trans-Caspia).

August 29

Bapaume retaken by British forces (see March 24th).

Noyon retaken by French forces (see March 25th). Second Battle of Noyon ends (see 17th).

August 30

Battle of the Scarpe, 1918, ends (see 26th)

Bailleul retaken by British forces (see April 15th).

Lieut.-General Sir C. F. N. Macready, Adjutant-General, Home Forces, Great Britain, resigns (see February 22nd, 1916, and September 11th, 1918).

August 31

German forces evacuate Mount Kemmel (see April 26th).

Battle of Bapaume begins (see March 24th and September 3rd).

Captain Cromie, R.N., British Naval Attaché, murdered by Bolsheviki in British Embassy, Petrograd.

September 1

Peronne retaken by British forces (see March 24th).

September 2

Battle of the Drocourt-Quéant Line (2nd/3rd).

Italian contingent lands at Murmansk to join Allied Expeditionary Force (see July 26th).

September 3

Battles of the Somme, 1918, end (see August 21st).

Battles of Arras, 1918, end (see August 26th).

Lens occupied by British forces (see October 4th, 1914).

Battle of Bapaume ends (see August 31st).

United States Government recognises the Czecho-Slovaks as possessing a de facto Government (see August 13th and October 21st).

September 4

Obozerskaya (North Russia) occupied by Allied forces (see August 2nd).

United States contingent lands at Murmansk to join Allied Expeditionary Force (see 2nd).

Hsu-Shih-Chang elected President of China (see October 11th).

September 5

Khabarovsk (Eastern Siberia) taken by Japanese forces (see 18th, and August 11th).

September 11

Ukhtinskaya (Murman front) captured by Allied forces.

Lieut.-General Sir G. M. W. Maedonogh appointed Adjutant-General, Home Forces, Great Britain (see August 30th).

September 12

Battle of St. Mihiel (12th/13th).

Battles of the Hindenburg Line (see October 9th) begin with Battle of Havrincourt.

Actions of Chamova (Archangel front) begin (see 14th).

September 14

Actions of Chamova end (see 12th).

British evacuation of Baku begins (see 15th, and August 26th).

September 15

Battle of the Dobropolje (Macedonia) begins (see 16th). Called by the Serbs "Battle of the Moglenitza."

Baku finally evacuated by the British forces (night 14th/15th) (see August 26th and November 17th).

Austrian Government send Note to President Wilson suggesting an "unofficial" peace conference (see 16th, and January 12th, 1917).

German Government make definite peace offer to Belgium (see January 10th and 12th, 1917).

September 16

Battle of the Dobropolje ends (see 15th).

Last German aeroplane raid on Paris (see August 30th, 1914).

President Wilson replies to the Austrian Note rejecting suggestion for a peace conference (see 15th, and October 4th).

H.M.S. "Glatton" sunk by explosion in Dover harbour.

September 18

Battle of Epéhy.

Blagovyeschensk (Siberia) occupied by Japanese forces (see 5th).

Battle of Monastir-Doiran (see 24th), including Battle of Doiran, 1918, begins (see 19th).

September 19

Battles of Megiddo (Sharon and Nablus) (Palestine) begin (see 23rd and 25th).

Battle of Doiran, 1918, ends (see 18th and 22nd).

September 20

Nazareth and Beisan (Palestine) occupied by British cavalry (see 19th).

September 22

Doiran occupied by British forces (see 19th, and December 11th, 1915).

September 23

Haifa, Acre, and Es Salt (Palestine) occupied by British forces (see 19th).

Prilep (South Serbia) taken by French forces (see November 16th, 1915).

Ma'an (on Hejaz Railway) evacuated by the Turkish garrison (see 29th).

September 24

Battle of Monastir-Doiran ends (see 18th).

September 25

Ishtip (see October 19th, 1915) and Veles (see October 21st, 1915) retaken by Serbian forces.

British cavalry cut Hejaz railway at Amman.

Battles of Megiddo end (see 19th).

Yugo-Slav State recognised as independent by Italy (see June 3rd and October 5th).

September 26

Battle of Champagne and Argonne begins (see October 15th).

September 27

Battle of the Canal du Nord begins (see October 1st).

Bulgarian Government ask Entente Powers for an armistice (see 30th).

September 28

Battle of the Flanders Ridges begins (see October 10th).

Battle of Ypres, 1918, begins (see November 10th, 1917, and October 2nd, 1918).

Messines retaken by British forces (see April 10th).

Baron Goto, Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs, resigns (see 29th, and April 22nd).

September 29

Battle of the St. Quentin Canal begins (see October 2nd).

Passchendaele retaken by Allied forces (see 28th, and April 16th).

Dixmude retaken by Belgian forces (see November 10th, 1014).

Turkish garrison of Ma'an surrenders near Amman (Palestine) (see 23rd).

German force in East Africa recrosses the Rovuma and again enters German territory (see November 25th, 1917, and November 1st 1918).

September 29

Takashi Hara succeeds Count Terauchi as Japanese Prime Minister (see October 9th, 1916).

Count Yasuya Uchida appointed Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs (see 28th).

Lieut.-General Kenichi Oshima, Japanese Minister for War, resigns (see 30th, and March 30th, 1916).

September 30

Armistice between Bulgaria and Entente Powers signed (see 27th).

Hostilities between Bulgaria and Entente Powers cease at 12 noon.

Canadian contingent lands at Archangel to join Allied Expeditionary Force (see August 2nd).

Count Hertling, German Imperial Chancellor, resigns (see October 30th, 1917, and October 4th, 1918).

Lieut.-General Giichi Tanaka appointed Japanese Minister for War (see 29th).

October 1

Battle of the Canal du Nord ends (see September 27th).

St. Quentin retaken by French forces (see September 27th).

Berat (Albania) retaken by Italian forces (see August 20th).

Damascus taken by British and Arab forces.

Allies establish net and mine barrage across Straits of Otranto.

October 2

Battle of Ypres, 1918, ends (see September 28th).

Battle of the St. Quentin Canal ends (see September 29th).

Durazzo bombarded by Italian and British warships (see 14th, and February 27th, 1916).

October 3

Battle of the Beaurevoir Line begins (see 5th).

Armentières retaken by British forces (see April 11th).

Action near Pyavozero Lake (Murman front).

October 4

Prince Max of Baden appointed German Imperial Chancellor, and succeeds Admiral von Hintze as Foreign Minister (see September 30th, July 9th, and November 9th).

German and Austro-Hungarian Governments send Notes to President Wilson proposing an armistice (see 8th and 18th). The German note was received by President Wilson on October 6th and the Austrian on October 7th.

Austro-Hungarian Government send Note to President Wilson proposing an armistice (see 27th, and September 16th).

King Ferdinand of Bulgaria abdicates in favour of his son Prince Boris (see September 30th and November 1st).

General Ironside takes over command of Allied forces at Archangel.

October 5

Battle of the Beaurevoir Line ends (see 3rd).

Vranje retaken by Serbian forces (see October 15th, 1915).

Yugo-Slav delegates meet at Agram and decide on the formation of a United National Council (see 29th, and September 25th).

October 6

Sidon (Syria) occupied by British forces.

October 7

Beirut (Syria) occupied by French forces

Elbasan (Albania) taken by Italian forces (see February 2nd, 1916).

October 8

Battle of Cambrai, 1918, begins (see 9th).

President Wilson replies to Note of German Government, and demands evacuation of occupied territories as first condition of armistice (see 4th and 12th).

October 9

Cambrai City captured by British forces (see August 26th, 1914).

End of Battle of Cambrai (see 8th) brings Battles of the Hindenburg Line to a close (see September 12th).

Major-General Scheuch succeeds Major-General von Stein as German Minister for War (see October 30th, 1916, and December 17th, 1918).

October 10

Battle of the Flanders Ridges ends (see September 28th).

Irish mail boat "Leinster" sunk by submarine.

Pristina (Serbia) retaken by French forces (see November 23rd, 1915)

October 11

Prizren (Serbia) retaken by French forces (see December 1st, 1915).

Nish (Serbia) reoccupied by Allied forces (see November 5th, 1915).

Feng-Kuo-Chang, President of China, retires (see July 6th, 1917, and September 4th, 1918).

October 12

Craonne again captured by French forces (see May 27th).

Action of Dushak (Trans-Caspia).

German Government reply to President Wilson's Note and accept conditions (see 8th and 14th).

British Government recognise the Polish National Army as autonomous, allied and co-belligerent.

October 13

Laon and La Fère retaken by French forces (see August 30th, 1014).

Tripoli (Syria) occupied by Allied forces. Izzet Pasha succeeds Talaat Pasha as Turkish Grand Vizier (see February 4th, 1917).

October 14

Battle of Courtrai begins (see 19th).

Roulers recaptured by Allied forces (see October 18th, 1914).

Durazzo (see 2nd), Novi Bazar (see November 20th, 1915), and Ipek (see December 6th, 1915) retaken by Italian forces.

British troops from Vladivostok reach Irkutsk (Siberia) (see 18th, and July 13th and August 3rd).

President Wilson replies to German Government, attaching further military conditions to the terms of armistice, and warning against further breaches of laws of war, and insists on dealing only with a democratic Government (see 12th and 20th).

Turkish Government Note to President Wilson proposing an armistice delivered at Washington.

October 15

Battle of Champagne and Argonne ends (see September 20th).

Menin captured by Allied forces (see October 9th, 1914).

Homs (Syria) occupied by British cavalry.

October 16

Austrian Emperor issues manifesto proclaiming a Federal State on the principle of Nationality (excluding Hungary) (see 5th and 29th).

October 17

Ostend (see October 15th, 1914), Lille (see October 12th, 1914), and Douai (see August 20th, 1914) retaken by Allied forces.

Battle of the Selle begins (see 25th).

October 18

British troops from Vladivostok reach Omsk (see 14th).

President Wilson replies to Austro-Hungarian Note of October 4th (see 27th).

October 19

Battle of Courtrai ends (see 14th).

Zeebrugge and Bruges reoccupied by Belgian forces (see October 12th and 14th, 1914).

October 20

Belgian coast completely reoccupied by Allied forces (see October 15th, 1914).

German Government reply to President Wilson's Note accepting proposals contained therein (see 14th and 23rd).

October 21

The Ban of Croatia refuses offer of Military Governor of Agram to suppress the Yugo-Slav National Council (see 5th and 29th).

The Czecho-Slovaks declare independence (see August 13th, September 3rd, and November 14th).

October 22

Affair of Imad (Aden).

October 23

British advance on Mosul (Mesopotamia) begins (see November 4th).

President Wilson replies to German Note of the 20th, and agrees to submit the matter to the Allied and Associated Governments (see 27th, and November 3rd).

October 24

Battle of Vittorio Veneto begins (see November 4th).

Dr. Wekerle, Hungarian Premier, resigns (see April 27th and November 1st).

October 25

Battle of the Selle ends (see 17th).

Kirkuk (Mesopotamia) again taken by British forces (see May 24th).

Count Andrassy succeeds Baron Burian as Austro-Hungarian Foreign Minister (see April 17th and November 1st).

October 26

Aleppo (Syria) taken by British forces.

King of Montenegro issues manifesto in favour of a confederated Yugo-Slavia with autonomous States (see 29th, and November 7th and 23rd).

October 27

Austrian Government ask Italy for an armistice (see 4th, and November 3rd).

German Government acknowledges President Wilson's Note of October 23rd.

Austro-Hungarian Government submit further Note to President Wilson asking for immediate armistice "without awaiting the result of other negotiations") (see 4th and 18th).

General von Ludendorff resigns (see August 29th, 1916).

October 28

Muslimiya Junction, north of Aleppo (Syria), occupied by British cavalry.

Battle of Sharqat (Mesopotamia) begins (see 30th).

October 29

San Giovanni di Medua (Albania) occupied by Italian forces (see January 25th, 1916).

Yugo-Slav National Council at Agram repudiate Imperial policy and declare the independence of the Yugo-Slavs (see 5th, 21st, 26th, and November 7th and 23rd).

October 30

Armistice between Turkey and Entente Powers signed at Mudros (see 31st).

Battle of Sharqat ends (see 28th).

Turkish army on the Tigris surrenders.

Fiume surrendered to the Croats by the Hungarian authorities.

"National Council of Fiume" proclaim the independence of the city and announce desire for union with Italy (see November 5th).

Croation Congress (Sabor) unanimously adhere to Yugo-Slav declaration of independence (see 29th).

October 31

Hostilities between Entente and Turkey cease at 12 noon (see 30th).

Scutari (Albania) retaken by Italian forces (see January 23rd, 1916).

Revolutions in Vienna and Budapest (see November 1st, 12th and 16th).

Count Tisza assassinated in Vienna (see May 23rd, 1917).

Austrian Emperor makes over the Austro-Hungarian Fleet to the Yugo-Slav National Council (see 29th).

November 1

Battle of Valenciennes begins (see 2nd).

Belgrade retaken by Serbian forces (see October 9th, 1915, and December 9th, 1918).

Merv retaken by British and Russian forces (see August 18th). Approximate date.

German force in East Africa enters Rhodesia and attacks Fife (see 9th, and September 29th).

Austrian battleship "Viribus Unitis" sunk in Pola harbour.

"State of War" begins between The Ukraine and Poland (see 23rd).

King Boris of Bulgaria abdicates (see October 4th ).

Independent Hungarian Government formed. Count Karolyi appointed Premier (see October 24th and 31st).

Baron von Flotow succeeds Count Andrassy (provisionally) as Austro-Hungarian Foreign Minister (see October 25th, and entry next above).

November 2

Battle of Valenciennes ends (see 1st and 3rd).

Last British merchant vessels (S.S. "Surada" and "Murcia") sunk by submarine (in the Mediterranean).

Administration of Carniola taken over from the Austro-Hungarian authorities by Slovene leaders (see August 17th).

November 3

Valenciennes occupied by British forces (see 2nd, and August 25th, 1914).

Allied Governments agree to Germany's proposal for an armistice and peace on basis of President Wilson's proposals of January 8th (see 5th and October 23rd).

Armistice between Austria-Hungary and the Entente signed (see 4th, 15th, and October 27th).

Trieste occupied by Italian forces.

Mutiny breaks out in the German fleet at Kiel (see August 3rd, 1917).

November 4

Battle of the Sambre.

Second Battle of Guise (4th/5th).

Battle of Vittorio Veneto ends (see October 24th).

Hostilities between Austria-Hungary and the Entente cease (see 3rd and 15th).

Antivari (Montenegro) occupied by Italian naval forces (see January 22nd, 1916).

Mosul occupied by British forces (see October 23rd).

November 5

Marshal Foch placed in supreme strategical direction of all forces operating against Germany on all fronts (see April 14th).

Fiume occupied by Italian naval forces (see 18th, and October 30th).

H.M.S. "Campania" sunk by collision in the Firth of Forth.

President Wilson sends final Note to the German Government with Allies' acceptance of armistice proposals (see 3rd and 8th).

November 6

Rethel taken by French forces.

Sedan taken by United States forces (see August 29th, 1914).

King Peter of Serbia re-enters Belgrade (see 1st, and January 17th, 1916).

November 7

Bavaria proclaimed a Republic.

Yugo-Slav conference at Geneva decide to form a joint Yugo-Slav-Serbian Government to control military and foreign affairs (see 23rd, and October 29th).

November 8

German armistice delegates reach Allied General Headquarters (see 11th, and October 23rd).

Maubeuge retaken by British forces (see September 7th, 1914).

M. Marghiloman, Rumanian Premier, and M. Arian, Rumanian Foreign Minister, resign (see March 21st, and December 1st).

November 9

Alexandretta (Syria) occupied by Entente naval forces.

Kasama (Rhodesia) taken by Colonel von Lettow-Vorbeck's force (see 1st and 13th).

H.M.S. "Britannia" sunk by submarine in the Atlantic (last warship so lost).

Revolution breaks out in Berlin.

German Imperial Chancellor (Prince Max) announces that the Kaiser has decided to abdicate. Prince Max becomes Regent. Herr Ebert becomes Imperial Chancellor (see 10th, 28th, and October 4th).

Joint Declaration by British and French Governments regarding future of Syria and Mesopotamia.

Czech forces at Ekaterinenburg proclaim national independence.

November 10

Mézières retaken by French forces (see August 27th, 1914).

Ghent reoccupied by Belgian forces (see October 12th, 1914).

Allied forces cross the Danube at Ruschuk and enter Rumania.

The Kaiser crosses the frontier into Holland (see 9th and 28th).

King of Rumania announces that the Rumanian nation have taken up arms again on the side of the Allies (see December 6th, 1917).

November 11

Mons retaken by British forces (see August 24th, 1914).

Armistice concluded between the Allied and Associated Powers and Germany. Signed in Marshal Foch's special train at Rethondes Station in the Forest of Compiègne. Hostilities on the Western front cease at 11 a.m. (see 8th, and December 14th).

British Government recognise Latvian Provisional Government as independent (see January 12th).

New National Government formed in Estonia (see 16th, and January 13th).

November 12

Emperor of Austria abdicates (see October 31st).

Allied fleet passes through the Dardanelles (see 13th, and October 30th).

German-Austrian Republic proclaimed.

November 13

Allied fleet arrives at Constantinople (see 12th and 21st).

German force in East Africa reaches the Chambezi River (Rhodesia). (News of armistice received) (see 9th, 14th and 25th).

November 14

Hostilities in East Africa cease. Professor Masaryk elected First President of the Czecho-Slovak Republic (see October 21st).

H.M.S. "Cochrane" wrecked at entrance to Liverpool.

November 15

German cruiser "Königsberg" with German naval delegates, enters Firth of Forth to arrange surrender of the German fleet (see 20th and 21st).

Hungarian Government (see 1st) concludes separate armistice with General Officer Commanding Allied Army (General Henry), at Belgrade (see 3rd).

General Petlyura commences revolt against The Ukraine Government (see December 11th).

November 16

Allied Armies begin march into Germany.

Polish Government (M. Pilsudski) issue declaration proclaiming Poland an Independent and Sovereign State (see June 3rd).

New National Government in Estonia order general mobilisation (see 11th).

Hungary declares Independence (see 1st, and October 31st).

November 17

Mulhouse again occupied by French forces (see August 25th, 1914).

Baku again occupied by British forces (see September 15th).

M. Moraczewski appointed Polish Prime Minister (see 16th).

Yugo-Slav National Council at Agram protest against the Italian occupation of Fiume (see 5th and 18th).

November 18

Last German troops recross French frontier (see August 2nd, 1914).

Brussels reoccupied by Belgian forces (see 21st, and August 20th, 1914).

Italian troops reinforce naval detachment in Fiume (see 5th and 17th).

Counter-revolutionary coup d'etat at Omsk. Russian Admiral Kolchak proclaimed "Dictator of all Russia."

November 19

Metz occupied by French forces.

Antwerp reoccupied by Belgian forces (see October 10th, 1914).

General Pétain created Marshal of France (see May 15th, 1917).

November 20

Luxembourg frontier crossed by United States forces (see August 2nd, 1914).

First contingent of German submarines surrender to the British Navy at Harwich (see 15th).

General Marushevski appointed Governor-General and Commander-in-Chief of Russian forces in North Russia (Archangel) (see June 30th).

November 21

German High Seas Fleet arrives at Rosyth, en route for internment in Scapa Flow (see 15th and 20th).

Belgian Government reinstated at Brussels (see 18th, and August 17th, 1914).

Namur occupied by British forces (see August 25th, 1914).

French troops land in Constantinople (see 13th).

Greek, Serbian, and Rumanian Governments issue circular memorandum announcing their decision to strengthen the union between the three countries by all available means.

M. L. Delacroix succeeds M. Cooreman as Belgian Prime Minister (see May 31st) and M. Masson succeeds Lieut.-General de Ceuninck as Minister for War (see August 4th, 1917). M. Delacroix was the first Minister to hold the title of Prime Minister.

November 23

Lemberg captured by Polish forces (see 1st).

Yugo-Slav National Council vote for union with Serbia and formation of a common State with Serbia and Montenegro (see 7th, 29th, October 29th and December 4th).

November 24

British and United States troops reach German frontier (see December 1st).

November 25

Strasbourg occupied by French forces.

German forces in East Africa surrender to Allied forces at Abercorn (Rhodesia) (see 13th and 14th).

November 26

Last German troops recross Belgian frontier (see August 4th, 1914).

French troops cross German frontier.

Allied fleet arrives at Sevastopol and takes over remainder of the Russian Black Sea Fleet from the Germans (see 13th, and May 1st).

United States force enters Fiume (see 17th).

November 28

Kaiser Wilhelm II signs abdication (see 9th and 10th).

Narva (Estonia) captured by Bolshevik forces (see March 4th).

The General Congress of The Bukovina decide in favour of complete union with Rumania (see December 7th).

November 29

Montenegrin National Assembly (Skupshtina) meet at Podgoritsa and vote for union with Serbia (see 23rd).

November 30

Rumanian Government re-established at Bukharest (see December 1st, 1916).

December 1

British and United States troops cross the German frontier (see November 24th). Trèves occupied by United States troops.

General Coanda appointed Rumanian Premier and Foreign Minister (see 12th, and November 8th).

National Assembly of the Rumanians of Transylvania, the Banat and other districts of Hungary, assembled at Alba-Julia (Transylvania), decree their union with Rumania (see 7th, 10th, and 27th).

December 3

Last Bulgarian troops evacuate the Dobrudja (see September 2nd, 1916).

December 4

H.M.S. "Cassandra" sunk by mine in the Baltic (night 4th/5th).

Demobilisation of the British Army begins.

Yugo-Slav National Council at Agram proclaim the union of all Serbs, Croats, and Slovenes in one State (see November 23rd and 29th).

December 6

Cologne entered by British troops (see 12th, and November 24th).

December 7

Deputation from the National Council of The Bukovina arrives at Jassy to inform Rumanian Government that National Council has voted for union with Rumania (see 1st, 10th, and November 28th).

December 8

Coblenz occupied by United States troops (see 1st).

Naval action in the Caspian between British and Bolshevik vessels.

December 9

Lahej (Southern Arabia) reoccupied by British forces (see July 4th, 1915).

Serbian Government reinstated at Belgrade (see May 7th, 1916, and November 1st and 6th, 1918).

December 10

The Bessarabian National Council abrogate the stipulations for local autonomy and declare the unconditional union of Bessarabia with Rumania (see 1st, and April 9th).

December 11

Odessa occupied by Petlyura's Ukrainian revolutionary forces (see 20th, March 13th, and November 15th).

General Mannerheim elected Regent of Finland (see December 6th, 1917).

December 12

British troops cross the Rhine at Cologne (see 6th).

General Coanda, Rumanian Premier and Foreign Minister, resigns (see 1st and 14th).

December 13

Hodeida (Southern Arabia) taken by British forces.

December 14

Armistice on the Western Front prolonged to January 17th, 1919 (see November 11th).

M. Bratianu appointed Rumanian Premier and Foreign Minister (see 12th).

Dr. da Silva Paes, Portuguese President, assassinated (see 16th, and May 9th).

December 15

Poland severs diplomatic relations with Germany (see November 16th).

December 16

Field-Marshal Mackensen and his forces surrender to the Hungarians near Budapest.

Last German troops leave Finland (see April 3rd).

First meeting of "Imperial Conference" of Soldiers and Workmen in Berlin.

Senhor Antunes appointed Acting Portuguese President (see 14th).

December 17

Major-General Scheuch, German Minister for War, resigns (see October 9th).

December 20

Kiev occupied by Petlyura's Ukrainian revolutionary forces (see 11th, and March 2nd).

French troops land at Odessa (see 11th).

M. Pasich, Premier of Serbia, resigns. (Appointed in 1912) (see 29th).

December 22

Senhor J. T. de Sousa Barboza, Portuguese Secretary of the Interior, resigns (see 23rd, and May 16th).

December 23

Senhor J. T. de Sousa Barboza appointed Portuguese Premier and Minister of Interior (see 22nd).

December 24

Perm (East Russia) taken by Kolehak's forces (see November 18th).

December 26

Formation of West Ukraine Bepublic announced (see November 20th, 1917).

Dorpat (Estonia) evacuated by the German forces (see February 24th).

December 27

Batum (Georgia) occupied by British forces (see April 15th). This force subsequently occupied the whole of Georgia, with headquarters at Tiflis.

King of Rumania issues Proclamation annexing the Rumanian provinces of Austria-Hungary (see 1st).

December 29

M. Stoyan Protich appointed Prime Minister of the United Kingdom of the Serbs, Croats and Slovenes (see 4th and 20th).

December 30

Kadish (North Russia) taken by Allied forces.

Birsk (East Russia) taken by Kolchak's forces (see 24th).

December 31

Ufa and Sterlitamak (East Russia) taken by Bolshevik forces.

This work derives from:

Rowe, R P P. (2015). A Concise Chronicle of Events of the Great War. Urbana, Illinois: Project Gutenberg. Retrieved July, 2023, from www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/48525.

The introduction, appendices, footnotes and page numbers have been removed to leave a simple list of events. An ongoing effort will introduce semantic mark-up into this web page.

A CONCISE CHRONICLE OF EVENTS OF THE GREAT WAR

1914

June 28 (Sun.)

Assassination of the Archduke Franz Ferdinand, heir to the throne of Austria, at Sarajevo.

July 23 (Thur.)

The Austrian ultimatum to Serbia.

July 25 (Sat.)

Serbia replies, yielding on all points except two. The Austrian Minister leaves Belgrade.

July 26 (Sun.)

The Admiralty countermands orders for the dispersal of the British Fleet.

July 27 (Mon.)

France and Italy accept England's proposal for an international conference.

July 28 (Tues.)

Germany rejects England's proposal for an international conference.

Austria declares war on Serbia.

July 29 (Wed.)

First shots of the war: Austria bombards Belgrade.

Germany makes proposals to secure England's neutrality.

July 31 (Fri.)

German ultimatums to Russia and France.

The French Socialist leader, M. Jaurès, is assassinated in Paris.

Aug. 1 (Sat.)

Germany declares war on Russia.

Aug. 2 (Sun.)

The German army enters Luxemburg. German patrols cross the frontiers of France. Germany invades Poland.

The German ultimatum to Belgium.

A moratorium is proclaimed in England.

Aug. 3 (Mon. Bank Holiday)

Germany invades Belgium and declares war on France.

Grey's speech in the House of Commons.

Italy declares her neutrality.

The mobilisation of the British Navy is announced complete.

Aug. 4 (Tues.)

The British Government delivers an ultimatum to Germany, which is summarily rejected. Great Britain declares war on Germany as from 11P.M.on this day.

Sir John Jellicoe assumes command of the British Home Fleets.

Aug. 5 (Wed.)

Liége is bombarded by the Germans.

Austria declares war on Russia.

Montenegro declares war on Austria.

Lord Kitchener is appointed Secretary of State for War in Great Britain.

The Königin Luise, equipped as a German mine-layer, is sunk by the British Third Destroyer Flotilla (parent ship Amphion) off the Suffolk coast.

Aug. 6 (Thur.)

Fall of three of the forts of Liége.

H.M.S. Amphion (light cruiser) is sunk by a mine in the North Sea.

The Goeben and the Breslau escape at dusk from Messina and run for the Dardanelles.

Aug. 7 (Fri.)

Fall of Liége; but its northern forts hold out (see Aug. 15).

A French reconnaissance into Alsace: Altkirch is captured.

The Russians invade East Prussia.

H.M.S. Gloucester (light cruiser) attacks and pursues the Goeben and the Breslau in the Mediterranean.

Aug. 8 (Sat.)

The French occupy Mulhausen, in Alsace.

A British and French force enters Togoland (see Aug. 26).

Aug. 9 (Sun.) (Heligoland ceded to Germany in 1890).

British troops land in France (disembarkation completed on August 16th).

German submarines attack a British light cruiser squadron: the U15 is sunk by the Birmingham.

Aug. 10 (Mon.)

France declares war on Austria.

The French evacuate Mulhausen, and retire in Alsace, but gain successes in the Vosges.

Austria invades Russian Poland.

The Goeben and the Breslau reach the Dardanelles.

Aug. 11 (Tues.)

The Belgian army is defeated and falls back before the Germans.

A German reverse at Spincourt, in Lorraine.

Aug. 12 (Wed.)

Great Britain declares war on Austria.

Serbia invades Bosnia.

Aug. 13 (Thur.)

Austria invades Serbia (see Aug. 25).

Dar-es-Salaam (German East Africa) is shelled and raided by the British cruisers Astræa and Pegasus.

Aug. 14 (Fri.)

A Russian proclamation guarantees autonomy to Poland.

The Russians defeat the Austrians at Sokal.

Aug. 15 (Sat.)

Japan delivers an ultimatum to Germany, demanding the evacuation of Kiao-Chau.

The last Liége forts are reduced.

East Africa:—The Germans occupy Taveta.

Aug. 16 (Sun.)

The disembarkation in France of the original British Expeditionary Force is completed, with Sir John French in supreme command (see Dec. 15, 1915), the First Corps being commanded by Sir D. Haig, the Second Corps by Sir James Grierson (see Aug. 17).

The Austrians capture Shabatz from the Serbians.

The Austrian light cruiser Zenta is sunk during a sweep up the Adriatic by the Allied Fleets.

Aug. 17 (Mon.)

Death of Lieut.-General Sir James Grierson: he is succeeded in command of the British Second Corps by Sir H. Smith-Dorrien.

The Germans advance in Belgium: Tirlemont and Louvain are captured. The Belgian Government moves to Antwerp.

The Serbians attack on the Jardar (the Battle of the Jardar, which leads to the expulsion of the Austrians from Serbian territory).

Aug. 18 (Tues.) Gravelotte, 1870.

The French advance in Lorraine culminates in the capture of Saarburg on the Metz-Strasbourg Railway.

Aug. 19 (Wed.)

The Belgians retire on Antwerp.

Alsace:—Mulhausen is again taken by the French (see Aug. 10, 25).

The Battle of the Jardar ends in a complete victory for the Serbians (see Aug. 17).

Aug. 20 (Thur.)

The Germans enter Brussels. They bombard Namur.

The French retire before a German counter-offensive in Lorraine.

A Russian victory at Gumbinnen (East Prussia), which leads to the retirement of the Germans on Königsberg, and to the appointment of Hindenburg to High Command (see Aug. 22).

Aug. 21 (Fri.)

The forts of Namur are silenced.

The Battle of Charleroi (east of Mons) begins (see Aug. 23).

South Africa:—German patrols cross into Union territory near Nakob.

Aug. 22 (Sat.)

The French and Belgians are defeated outside Namur.

The Germans approach Nancy: the Battle of Nancy (see Sept. 11).

General von Hindenburg is appointed to command the German armies in East Prussia.

Aug. 23 (Sun.)

Japan declares war on Germany.

Namur is captured by the Germans.

The Battle of Mons.

The Battle of Charleroi ends in the defeat of the French (see Aug. 21).

East Prussia:—The Russians are victorious at Frankenau.

Galicia:—The Russians take Brody and Tarnopol (see Sept. 1 and 7, 1915).

Aug. 24 (Mon.)

The retreat of the Allies on the Western Front begins.

The Germans occupy Tournai.

Cattaro, in the Adriatic, is bombarded by the Allied fleets.

Aug. 25 (Tues.)

Louvain is sacked by the Germans.

The British fight severe actions at Landrecies and Maroilles, and reach the line Cambrai—Le Cateau in 'the Retreat.'

Mulhausen is again captured by the Germans.

In East Prussia the Russians approach Königsberg.

The Austrians defeat the Russians in the First Battle of Krasnik.

The Austrians evacuate Serbia (see Aug. 13).

Invasion of the Cameroons by the French and British (see Feb. 19, 1916).

Aug. 26 (Wed.) (Crécy, 1346).

The First Battle of Le Cateau: further retirement of the Allies in France. Maubeuge is invested by the Germans (see Sept. 7).

The beginning of the Battle of Tannenberg, which, after four days' fighting, leads to the crushing defeat of the Russians by Hindenburg.

Togoland surrenders to the Allies (see Aug. 8).

H.M.S. Highflyer (a light cruiser, used before the war as a training ship for naval cadets) sinks the German auxiliary cruiser Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse off the West African coast.

Aug. 27 (Thur.)

The Allies fall back behind the Somme. Lille and Mézières are occupied by the Germans. Ostend is occupied by British marines.

Halicz (Galicia) is captured by the Russians.

The blockade of Tsingtau (Kiao-Chau) begins (see Aug. 15, Nov. 7).

The German cruiser Magdeburg runs ashore in the Gulf of Finland, and is blown up by her captain.

Aug. 28 (Fri.)

The Battle of the Bight of Heligoland: British destroyers supported by light cruisers and battle cruisers sink three German cruisers and two destroyers; no British vessel is lost.

New Zealand troops, supported by an Allied naval force, occupy German Samoa.

Aug. 29 (Sat.)

The British Army, in touch at last with the French on both flanks, rests temporarily for the first time in 'the Retreat.' General Joffre and Sir J. French meet and confer at Compiègne. In the evening the retreat is resumed in an orderly manner.

The Battle of Tannenberg ends in a complete victory for the Germans (see Aug. 26).

Aug. 30 (Sun.)

The British reach a line a little north of Compiègne-Soissons. The Germans occupy La Fère and Laon. The British bases are established temporarily at St. Nazaire and Nantes instead of at Havre and Boulogne.

Aug. 31 (Mon.)

The Germans occupy Amiens.

In Galicia the First Battle of Lemberg begins (see Sept. 2).

Sept. 1 (Tues.)

The Germans occupy Soissons. The British fight gallant actions at Villers-Cotterets and Néry in 'the Retreat.'

East Africa:—The first portion of the Expeditionary Force arrives at Mombasa.

Sept. 2 (Wed.)

The British reach the north bank of the Marne in 'the Retreat.'

The First Battle of Lemberg ends in a heavy defeat of the Austrians by the Russians (see Aug. 31).

China:—Japanese troops are landed to attack Tsingtau (Kiao-Chau).

Sept. 3 (Thur.)

The French Government moves to Bordeaux.

The British cross the Marne in 'the Retreat,' and blow up the bridges.

Lemberg is occupied by the Russians (see June 22, 1915).

H.M.S. Speedy, torpedo gunboat, is sunk by a mine off the Humber.

Sept. 4 (Fri.)

The Germans cross the Marne in force.

The Russians advance into the Carpathian passes.

Sept. 5 (Sat.)

The Franco-British retreat ends; Joffre orders a counter-offensive. The Germans take Rheims and on their right are close to Paris. Heavy fighting on the Ourcq.

The British light cruiser Pathfinder is sunk, with serious loss of life, by a German submarine off St. Abb's Head (the first ship to be sunk by a submarine).

Sept. 6 (Sun.)

The Allied offensive in France begins with the First Battle of the Marne (see Sept. 10). A decisive day in the Battle of Nancy (see Aug. 22 and Sept. 11); German attacks are repulsed.

East Prussia:—The Battle of the Masurian Lakes begins (see Sept. 12).

In Galicia, the Battle of Grodek begins (see Sept. 13).

Sept. 7 (Mon.)

Maubeuge surrenders to the Germans (see Aug. 26). The Allies press forward in France.

The Germans advance into Russia.

Austria begins a second invasion of Serbia (see Sept. 15).

The formation of the British Royal Naval Division is announced.

Sept. 8 (Tues.)

The advance of the Allies in France continues. Von Kluck is now definitely in retreat.

H.M.S. Oceanic (armed merchant cruiser) is wrecked and lost off the Shetland Islands.

Sept. 9 (Wed.)

The decisive day of the Battle of the Marne: the British cross the river and advance north of it; the French carry the Ourcq. Foch makes a decisive move with the 9th French Army.

General Botha announces the decision of the South African Government to undertake an expedition against German South-West Africa.

Sept. 10 (Thur.)

The victory of the Marne is complete (see Sept. 6): the Allies advance rapidly.

Poland:—The Austrians are defeated in the Second Battle of Krasnik.

The Serbians occupy Semlin (Hungary).

The Emden appears in the Bay of Bengal.

Sept. 11 (Fri.)

The French reoccupy Châlons. The British cross the Ourcq. The Battle of Nancy ends in complete failure by the Germans (see Aug. 22).

Australian military and naval forces occupy the Bismarck Archipelago.

Sept. 12 (Sat.)

The Battle of the Masurian Lakes (see Sept. 6) ends in the defeat and further retreat of the Russians: East Prussia is cleared of the invader.

Sept. 13 (Sun.)

The Battle of the Aisne begins (see Sept. 28); the British force the passage of the river. Soissons and Amiens are reoccupied by the French.

Galicia:—The Battle of Grodek (see Sept. 6) ends in a complete Russian victory.

The German light cruiser Hela is sunk off Heligoland by the British submarine E9 (the first successful submarine attack by the British).

Sept. 14 (Mon.)

High ground north of the Aisne is captured by the British 1st Corps. The Germans evacuate Rheims.

In Galicia, the Russians advance across the San.

H.M.S. Carmania (auxiliary cruiser) sinks the German auxiliary cruiser Cap Trafalgar off Trinidad after a sharp action.

Sept. 15 (Tues.)

The Russians take Czernowitz, in the Bukovina (see Oct. 22).

The Serbians defeat the Austrians on the Drina: this ends the second Austrian invasion of Serbia (see Sept. 7).

The rebellion in South Africa begins, but the accidental shooting of De la Rey delays the open outbreak designed and upsets the rebel plans (see Oct. 9, 22).

Sept. 16 (Wed.)

East Africa:—Longido is occupied by the Germans.

Sept. 17 (Thur.)

The Belgians fall back on Antwerp.

Hungary:—Semlin is evacuated by the Serbians (see Sept. 10).

Sept. 19 (Sat.)

British marines are landed at Dunkirk.

South-West Africa:—Luderitz Bay is occupied by Union troops.

Sept. 20 (Sun.)

The Germans bombard Rheims Cathedral.

H.M.S. Pegasus is sunk by the Königsberg off Zanzibar (95 casualties).

Sept. 21 (Mon.)

The French retake Noyon (see Sept. 25).

The German forces advancing from East Prussia reach the Niemen.

Sept. 22 (Tues.)

The Russians invest Przemysl.

The Serbians invade Bosnia again (see Aug. 12).

South Africa:—General Botha assumes command of the Union forces.

H.M.S. Cressy, Aboukir, and Hogue (cruisers) are torpedoed by a German submarine off the Hook of Holland: 1400 lives are lost.

The Emden shells Madras.

A British naval air-raid on Düsseldorf.

Sept. 23 (Wed.)

The Germans capture St. Mihiel.

The Russians take Jaroslav (Galicia).

Sept. 24 (Thur.)

The Germans occupy Péronne.

Australian forces occupy German New Guinea.

China:—A British force is landed to aid the Japanese in their operations against Tsingtau.

Sept. 25 (Fri.)

Noyon is retaken by the Germans (see Sept. 21). The Battle of Albert (see Sept. 29) begins, the Germans attacking.

Sept. 26 (Sat.)

The Battle of the Niemen (see Sept. 28) begins, the Russians standing on the line of the river against the German attack.

Sept. 27 (Sun.)

The Germans fail to cross the Niemen and retire.

The Cameroons:—Duala surrenders to the Allies.

Sept. 28 (Mon.)

The Germans attack Antwerp.

The Battle of the Aisne (see Sept. 13) ends in trench warfare.

The Battle of the Niemen (see Sept. 26) ends in the definite retreat of the Germans.

The occupation of Galicia is completed by the Russians, who threaten Cracow and invade Hungary.

Sept. 29 (Tues.)

End of the Battle of Albert (see Sept. 25): the Germans are repulsed.

The Battle of Augustovo (see Oct. 4) begins: the Russians, having advanced from the Niemen, attack the Germans.

Sept. 30 (Wed.)

The French re-enter Arras and reoccupy Lille.

Oct. 1 (Thur.)

The transfer of the British Army from Champagne to Flanders begins (see Oct. 19).

Oct. 3 (Sat.)

The Germans attack from Varennes to Verdun.

Before Antwerp the Belgians retire to the line of the Nethe.

Oct. 4 (Sun.)

Lens and Bailleul (see Oct. 14) are occupied by the Germans in their movement towards the coast.

The end of the Battle of Augustovo (see Sept. 29): the Russians re-enter East Prussia.

Oct. 5 (Mon.)

The British Naval Division reaches Antwerp.

The first German advance on Warsaw begins.

Oct. 6 (Tues.)

The British 7th Division is disembarked at Ostend.

The British submarine E9 sinks a German destroyer off the mouth of the Ems.

Oct. 7 (Wed.)

The Belgian Government moves from Antwerp to Ostend.

Japan occupies the Marshall Islands.

Oct. 8 (Thur.)

The city of Antwerp is bombarded; the garrison retires across the Scheldt. A force of Belgians and 2000 British are driven into Dutch territory.

A British air-raid on Cologne and Düsseldorf.

Oct. 9 (Fri.)

The end of the second Russian advance into East Prussia.

South Africa:—Maritz openly rebels and joins forces with the Germans on the border of South-West Africa (see Oct. 22).

A British naval air-raid on Düsseldorf, by which a Zeppelin is destroyed in its shed.

Oct. 10 (Sat.)

Antwerp is captured by the Germans.

Oct. 11 (Sun.)

The Battle of La Bassée begins (see Oct. 31); the British (2nd Corps) attack the La Bassée position.

A heavy attack on the British 7th Division at Ghent is repulsed.

The Russian cruiser Pallada is destroyed by German submarines in the Baltic.

Oct. 13 (Tues.)

The Germans occupy Ghent and reoccupy Lille; the British (3rd Corps) drive them from Méteren.

Oct. 14 (Wed.)

The British (3rd Corps) recapture Bailleul (see Oct. 4).

Jabussi, in the Cameroons, is occupied by the Allies.

Oct. 15 (Thur.)

The Germans occupy Zeebrugge and Ostend. The British (3rd Corps) advance towards the Lys.

The First Battle for Warsaw begins (see Oct. 27). The Siege of Przemysl is raised for three weeks.

South Africa:—Union forces under Colonel Brits attack and defeat the rebel commando under Maritz at Ratedrai.

H.M.S. Hawke (cruiser) is torpedoed by a German submarine in the North Sea (500 lives lost).

Oct. 16 (Fri.)

The Battle of the Yser begins (see Oct. 30). The Belgians retire from the Forest of Houthulst.

Oct. 17 (Sat.)

The British (9th Brigade) recapture Aubers.

H.M.S. Undaunted (cruiser) and four British destroyers sink four German destroyers off the Dutch coast.

Oct. 18 (Sun.)

British monitors bombard the right flank of the German army in Belgium.

The British submarine E3 is sunk in the North Sea (the first British submarine to be lost through enemy action).

Oct. 19 (Mon.)

The transfer of the British to Flanders is completed (see Oct. 1). The First Battle of Ypres begins (see Nov. 21). The first division of Indians reaches the Western Front.

Oct. 20 (Tues.)

The German attack on Arras begins.

Oct. 22 (Thur.)

Bukovina:—Czernowitz is reoccupied by the Austrians (see Sept. 15, Oct. 27).

South Africa:—Beyers, Kemp and De Wet openly rebel (see Sept. 15, Oct. 9).

Oct. 23 (Fri.)

French troops support the British at Zonnebeke.

South-West Africa:—Angola (Portuguese colony) is entered by the Germans.

Oct. 24 (Sat.)

The French advance near Zonnebeke. The Germans cross the Yser.

South Africa:—De Wet seizes Heilbron.

H.M.S. Badger rams a German submarine off the Dutch coast.

Oct. 26 (Mon.)

South Africa:—Union troops under Colonel Brits defeat and break up rebel forces under Maritz at Kakamas.

The Cameroons:—Edea is occupied by the Allies.

The French liner Amiral Ganteaume is sunk by a submarine off Cape Grisnez.

Oct. 27 (Tues.)

The British line is drawn back at Ypres.

The end of the First Battle for Warsaw (see Oct. 15): the Germans retreat.

Bukovina:—Czernowitz is reoccupied by the Russians (see Oct. 22, 1914; Feb. 17, 1915).

The Serbians are driven out of Bosnia by the Austrians.

South Africa:—General Botha defeats and disperses Beyers' commando at Commissie Drift, near Rustenburg; Beyers escapes.

H.M.S. Audacious (dreadnought) is sunk by a mine off Lough Swilly on the north coast of Ireland.

Oct. 28 (Wed.)

The Belgians flood the land round the Yser.

The Emden sinks the Russian cruiser Jemchug and the French destroyer Mousquet off Penang.

Oct. 29 (Thurs.)

Lord Fisher succeeds Prince Louis of Battenberg as British First Sea Lord (see May 28, 1915).

Fierce fighting round Kruseik and Gheluvelt.

Oct. 30 (Fri.)

The Germans are forced back by the floods in the Yser district: the end of the Battle of the Yser (see Oct. 16). The British are driven from Zandvoorde but hold at Klein Zillebeke.

South Africa:—Colonel Brits clears the north-west of Cape Province by defeating the remnant of the rebels left in this locality at Schuit Drift.

The German cruiser Königsberg is discovered in the Rufiji River (German East Africa) and shelled by H.M.S. Chatham and other British warships (see July 11, 1915).

Oct. 31 (Sat.)

The end of the Battle of La Bassée (see Oct. 11).

A critical day in the First Battle of Ypres; the British line is broken and restored.

Tsingtau is bombarded by the Japanese and British (see Nov. 7).

H.M.S. Hermes (aircraft-carrier) is sunk by a submarine in the Straits of Dover.

Nov. 1 (Sun.)

The Germans take Messines.

The third Austrian invasion of Serbia begins (see Dec. 15).

The forts of Tsingtau are silenced (see Nov. 7).

A British squadron is defeated off Coronel (Chile) by a German squadron of superior strength under Admiral von Spee: the Good Hope and Monmouth are sunk.

Nov. 2 (Mon.)

The Germans capture Neuve Chapelle from the British.

Nov. 3 (Tues.)

The Dardanelles Forts are bombarded by the British and French Mediterranean fleets.

East Africa:—Tanga is attacked by the British (see Nov. 5).

A German cruiser squadron bombards Yarmouth and escapes.

Nov. 4 (Wed.)

The Austrians are heavily defeated at Jaroslav (Galicia).

East Africa:—A British attack on Longido is repulsed.

The German armoured cruiser Yorck is sunk by a mine at the entrance to Jahde Bay (west of the mouth of the Weser).

Nov. 5 (Thur.)

Great Britain declares war on Turkey and annexes Cyprus.

The British line at Ypres is readjusted.

East Africa:—The British attack on Tanga is repulsed (see Nov. 3).

Nov. 6 (Fri.)

Carl Lody is shot for espionage in the Tower of London.

The Germans attack at Klein Zillebeke.

Mesopotamia:—Fao, at the mouth of the Shatt-el-Arab, is captured by the British.

Nov. 7 (Sat.)

Tsingtau is taken by the Japanese and British (see Aug. 27, Oct. 31).

Nov. 9 (Mon.)

H.M.S. Sydney of the Australian navy destroys the Emden off Cocos Island.

Nov. 10 (Tues.)

The Germans capture Dixmude.

Goldap (East Prussia) is occupied by the Russians.

H.M.S. Chatham and other British warships again shell the Königsberg in the Rufiji River (German East Africa) (see Oct. 30 and July 11, 1915).

Nov. 11 (Wed.)

A critical day in the First Battle of Ypres: a great attack by the Prussian Guard is repulsed.

The Russians begin the Second Siege of Przemysl (see March 22, 1915).

The British torpedo-gunboat Niger is sunk by a German submarine off Deal.

Nov. 12 (Thur.)

A fresh German assault on the Klein Zillebeke position is partially successful.

South Africa:—Botha completely routs the rebel forces under De Wet at Mushroom Valley in the Orange Free State.

Nov. 14 (Sat.)

Death of Lord Roberts at British G.H.Q. in France (St. Omer).

Nov. 15 (Sun.)

The Russians advance rapidly in East Prussia.

Nov. 17 (Tues.)

South-West Africa:—The Germans again invade Angola (see Oct. 23).

East Africa:—Longido is occupied by the British.

Libau is shelled by a German squadron.

Nov. 18 (Wed.)

The Second Battle for Warsaw begins (see Dec. 28).

The Goeben and the Breslau are attacked by a Russian squadron in the Black Sea, the Goeben being damaged.

Nov. 20 (Fri.)

The Germans invade Uganda.

Nov. 21 (Sat.)

The end of the First Battle of Ypres (see Oct. 19).

Basra, at the head of the Persian Gulf, is occupied by British forces from India.

A British air-raid on the Zeppelin sheds at Friedrichshafen.

Nov. 23 (Mon.)

The Germans attack the Indians at Festubert; trenches are lost and recovered.

The Russian front is broken near Lodz.

Zeebrugge is bombarded by two British battleships.

The German submarine U18 is rammed and sunk off the north coast of Scotland.

Nov. 24 (Tues.)

The Russian line near Lodz is restored.

Nov. 25 (Wed.)

Mesopotamia:—A naval reconnaissance up the Tigris to Gurneh.

Nov. 26 (Thur.)

H.M.S. Bulwark (battleship) is destroyed by an accidental explosion off Sheerness with heavy loss of life.

Nov. 27 (Fri.)

The Russians begin to evacuate Lodz.

Dec. 1 (Tues.)

South Africa:—De Wet is captured by Union troops at Waterburg (100 miles west of Mafeking) (see Oct. 22).

Dec. 2 (Wed.)

A French success at Vermelles.

Belgrade is occupied by the Austrians.

Dec. 3 (Thur.)

The Battle of the Ridges, between the Serbians and the Austrians, begins (see Dec. 6).

Dec. 4 (Fri.)

South Africa:—Part of the rebel forces surrenders near Reitz.

Dec. 6 (Sun.)

The Battle at Lodz (see Nov. 23, 24 and 27) ends in the capture of the town by the Germans.

The Battle of the Ridges (see Dec. 3) ends in the rout of the Austrians.

Dec. 7 (Mon.)

The Russians attack the forts of Cracow.

Mesopotamia:—A British success at Mezera.

Dec. 8 (Tues.)

The Battle of the Falkland Islands: a German squadron under Admiral von Spee is destroyed by a British cruiser force under Admiral Sir F. Doveton Sturdee; only the Dresden escapes.

South Africa:—General Beyers, after a crushing defeat south of Bothaville, is drowned in attempting to escape across the Vaal River. The main rebel force surrenders to General Botha (see Oct. 22).

Dec. 10 (Thur.)

The Cameroons:—Bare is occupied by the British.

Dec. 11 (Fri.)

The Goeben is driven from Batum.

Dec. 12 (Sat.)

The Austrians take the Dukla Pass. The Russians are forced to retreat from Cracow.

Dec. 13 (Sun.)

The British submarine B11 passes under the Dardanelles mine-fields and sinks the Turkish battleship Messudiyeh.

Dec. 15 (Tues.)

The end of the third Austrian invasion of Serbia: the Serbians retake Belgrade and again drive the Austrians out of the country (see Nov. 1).

Dec. 16 (Wed.)

German cruisers bombard Scarborough, Hartlepool, and Whitby.

Dec. 18 (Fri.)

The Khedive of Egypt, Abbas II., is deposed, and Prince Hussein Kamel Pasha, a son of the ex-Khedive Ismail, is appointed Sultan of Egypt by Great Britain (see Oct. 9, 1917).

Dec. 19 (Sat.)

An attack by the Indian Corps at Givenchy: ground is gained and lost.

Dec. 20 (Sun.)

The Germans capture Indian positions near Givenchy.

The Russians recapture the Dukla Pass and advance in the Carpathians.

A British air-raid on Brussels airship sheds.

Dec. 22 (Tues.)

The situation near Givenchy is restored by a British counter-attack.

Dec. 24 (Thurs.)

A British air-raid on the German airship sheds near Brussels.

Dec. 25 (Fri.)

German warships are bombed by British seaplanes off Cuxhaven.

South-West Africa:—Walfish Bay is occupied by Union troops.

Dec. 26 (Sat.)

Valona (Albania) is temporarily occupied by the Italians (see May 29, 1915).

Dec. 28 (Mon.)

The Second Battle for Warsaw (see Nov. 18) ends in failure for the Germans.

Dec. 29 (Tues.)

The Caucasus:—The Battle of Sarykamish begins, between the Russians and the Turks (see Jan. 2, 1915).

Dec. 30 (Wed.)

A raid by German aeroplanes on Dunkirk.

1915

Jan. 1 (Fri.)

A new British decoration, the 'Military Cross,' is instituted.

The Caucasus:—Ardahan is occupied by the Turks.

H.M.S. Formidable (battleship) is torpedoed in the English Channel (600 lives lost).

Jan. 2 (Sat.)

The Caucasus:—The end of the Battle of Sarykamish (see Dec. 29, 1914): the Turks are routed.

East Africa:—Jassin is occupied by the British (see Jan. 19).

H.M.S. Fox and H.M.S. Goliath bombard Dar-es-Salaam (German East Africa).

Jan. 3 (Sun.)

The Caucasus:—Ardahan is reoccupied by the Russians.

Jan. 4 (Mon.)

A Russian advance in the Bukovina begins.

Jan. 7 (Thurs.)

The Cameroons:—A German attack on Edea is repulsed.

Jan. 8 (Fri.)

The Battle of Soissons begins (see Jan. 14): the French advance.

The Caucasus:—The Battle of Kara Urgan begins (see Jan. 13).

Jan. 9 (Sat.)

Northern Persia:—The Turks capture Tabriz from the Russians (see Jan. 30).

Jan. 11 (Mon.)

A German counter-attack at Soissons is repulsed.

Jan. 12 (Tues.)

East Africa:—The Island of Mafia surrenders to the British.

Jan. 13 (Wed.)

Caucasus:—The Battle of Kara Urgan ends in a Turkish defeat (see Jan. 8).

Jan. 14 (Thur.)

The French fall back on Soissons: the end of the Battle of Soissons (see Jan. 8).

South-West Africa:—Swakopmund is occupied by Union forces.

Jan. 19 (Tues.)

The Austrian army enters Galicia.

East Africa:—Jassin is captured by the Germans (see Jan. 2).

A Zeppelin raid on Yarmouth, Cromer and King's Lynn.

Jan. 21 (Thur.)

The Germans capture the Hartmannsweilerkopf (Alsace).

Jan. 22 (Fri.)

A British air-raid on Zeebrugge.

Jan. 24 (Sun.)

South Africa:—The rebels under Maritz and Kemp are repulsed with heavy loss at Upington.

The Battle of the Dogger Bank: Beatty's squadron destroys the Blücher and damages other German warships.

Jan. 25 (Mon.)

German attacks are repulsed at Cuinchy and near Givenchy.

The German light cruiser Gazelle is torpedoed in the Baltic.

The Russians destroy a German airship over Libau.

Jan. 26 (Tues.)

The Turks advance on Egypt from Palestine.

Jan. 29 (Fri.)

The Turks occupy Katiyeh, near the Suez Canal.

Jan. 30 (Sat.)

Northern Persia:—The Russians reoccupy Tabriz (see Jan. 9).

Jan. 31 (Sun.)

Farsan Island (Red Sea) is occupied by Arab forces.

Feb. 1 (Mon.)

The British hospital ship Asturias is attacked near Havre by a German submarine.

Feb. 2 (Tues.)

The first Turkish attack on the Suez Canal.

Feb. 3 (Wed.)

The Turks are repulsed on the Suez Canal.

South Africa:—Kemp, the last rebel leader, surrenders unconditionally; this ends the rebellion (see Oct. 22, 1914).

Feb. 4 (Thur.)

The British cross the Suez Canal and pursue the Turks.

Feb. 6 (Sat.)

The Russians again advance in East Prussia.

Feb. 7 (Sun.)

The Russians retire before a German advance in East Prussia, and are driven back by the Austrians in the Bukovina.

Feb. 8 (Mon.)

South-West Africa:—General Botha sails for Walfish Bay (see July 9, 1915).

French airmen bombard Ostend.

Feb. 11 (Thur.)

A British air-raid on Zeebrugge.

Feb. 12 (Fri.)

The Germans invade Russia and take Miriampol.

The Austrians advance in the Carpathians.

Aden Protectorate is invaded by the Turks.

Feb. 14 (Sun.)

The Germans capture Lyck and again clear East Prussia.

Feb. 15 (Mon.)

Mutiny of the 5th Light Infantry at Singapore.

Feb. 16 (Tues.)

The Austrians capture Kolomea (Bukovina).

A British naval air-raid on Zeebrugge.

Feb. 17 (Wed.)

Czernowitz is recaptured by the Austrians (see Oct. 27, 1914).

Feb. 18 (Thur.)

The declaration by Germany of a submarine blockade round the British Isles comes into force.

The end of the German advance into Russia.

Feb. 19 (Fri.)

The Austrians drive the Russians out of Stanislau (see March 4).

A naval attack on the Dardanelles begins: the outer forts are bombarded until the 23rd.

Feb. 21 (Sun.)

A Zeppelin raid on Calais.

Feb. 22 (Mon.)

The Germans advance on Przasnysz (the Battle of Przasnysz).

The Turks are driven from Akaba (Red Sea).

South-West Africa:—Garub is occupied by Union troops.

Feb. 24 (Wed.)

The Germans capture Przasnysz (see Feb. 27).

Feb. 25 (Thur.)

The bombardment of the Dardanelles forts is resumed; the Queen Elizabeth comes into action.

Feb. 26 (Fri.)

The entrance to the Dardanelles is swept clear of mines.

Feb. 27 (Sat.)

Przasnysz is reoccupied by the Russians (see Feb. 24 and July 14).

Feb. 28 (Sun.)

A German retreat from North Poland begins.

A German submarine is rammed by the Thordis off Beachy Head (the first case of a submarine being rammed by a merchant ship).

Mar. 3 (Wed.)

South-West Africa:—Makob is occupied by Union forces.

Mar. 4 (Thur.)

Stanislau is recaptured by the Russians (see Feb. 19).

The Dardanelles forts are bombarded from inside the Straits.

The German submarine U8 is sunk by British destroyers near Dover.

Mar. 5 (Fri.)

The Allies bombard Smyrna.

Mar. 6 (Sat.)

Another great attack on the Dardanelles forts.

Mar. 7 (Sun.)

Lemnos, in the Ægean Sea, is occupied by the British.

Mar. 8 (Mon.)

The British Government announces that a separate treatment will be meted out to prisoners captured in German submarines (see April 12 and June 12).

Heavy fighting near Augustovo: the Russians drive the Germans back to the frontier.

A British air-raid on Ostend.

Mar. 9 (Tues.)

East Africa:—The British defeat the Germans on the Mora River.

The German submarine U12 is rammed and sunk by the British destroyer Ariel off the Firth of Forth.

Mar. 10 (Wed.)

The Battle of Neuve Chapelle begins: the British advance (see March 13).

Mar. 11 (Thur.)

South-West Africa:—Nabas is occupied by Union forces.

H.M.S. Bayano (armed merchant cruiser) is sunk by a submarine off the Clyde.

Mar. 13 (Sat.)

The Battle of Neuve Chapelle ends: the British gains are consolidated (see March 10).

The Russians breach the defences of Przemysl.

Mar. 14 (Sun.)

The Germans attack at St. Eloi and take the village.

H.M.S. Kent and H.M.S. Glasgow sink the Dresden off Juan Fernandez Island.

Mar. 15 (Mon.)

The British retake St. Eloi.

H.M.S. Amethyst makes a raid up the Dardanelles.

Mar. 17 (Wed.)

A further enemy attack at St. Eloi is repulsed.

Sir Ian Hamilton arrives at Tenedos (Ægean Sea).

Mar. 18 (Thur.)

The Battle of the Narrows: an Allied naval attack on the Dardanelles is repulsed; the French battleship Bouvet and the British battleships Irresistible and Ocean are sunk.

The Russians again invade East Prussia and temporarily occupy Memel (see March 21).

A Zeppelin raid on Calais.

Mar. 20 (Sat.)

South-West Africa:—General Botha defeats the Germans at Riet on the Swakop.

Mar. 21 (Sun.)

The Germans retake Memel (see March 18).

Mar. 22 (Mon.)

Przemysl surrenders to the Russians, who claim 126,000 prisoners (see Nov. 11, 1914, and June 3, 1915).

A second Turkish attack on the Suez Canal.

Mar. 23 (Tues.)

The Turks are again driven back from the Suez Canal.

Mar. 24 (Wed.)

A British air-raid on German submarine works at Hoboken, near Antwerp.

Mar. 25 (Thur.)

The French attack the Hartmannsweilerkopf (Alsace).

The Dutch steamship Medea is sunk by a German submarine off Beachy Head.

The German fleet bombards the coast of Courland.

A French air-raid on Metz.

Mar. 27 (Sat.)

The French capture the Hartmannsweilerkopf (Alsace).

Mar. 28 (Sun.)

The British liner Falaba is sunk by the U28 south of St. George's Channel.

Libau is bombarded by German warships.

A German air-raid on Calais.

April 1 (Thur.)

South-West Africa:—Union forces seize Hasuur.

A British air-raid on Hoboken and Zeebrugge.

April 4 (Easter Sunday)

South-West Africa:—Warmbad is occupied by Union forces.

April 5 (Mon.)

The French attack at Les Eparges.

Caucasus:—Artvin is occupied by the Russians.

April 6 (Tues.)

A German counter-attack at Les Eparges.

April 8 (Thur.)

The French win the summit of Les Eparges.

April 9 (Fri.)

A final German counter-attack at Les Eparges is repulsed.

April 12 (Mon.)

Germany places 39 British officers in detention barracks as a reprisal against the treatment of submarine prisoners by Great Britain (see March 8 and June 12).

Mesopotamia:—The British are attacked at Shaiba.

April 14 (Wed.)

Mesopotamia:—The Battle at Shaiba ends in the defeat of the Turks.

A Zeppelin raid on the Tyneside.

April 15 (Thur.)

A Zeppelin raid on East Anglia.

April 16 (Fri.)

Northern Persia:—Urmia is occupied by the Turks.

April 17 (Sat.)

The British capture 'Hill 60,' near Ypres.

South West Africa:—Seeheim is occupied by Union forces.

April 18 (Sun.)

The Germans counter-attack on 'Hill 60' and regain part of it.

On the North-West Frontier of India Mohmand Inshkar is defeated by the British.

April 20 (Tues.)

Fierce fighting on 'Hill 60.' The Germans bombard Ypres.

April 21 (Wed.)

The Germans are driven from 'Hill 60' (see May 5).

April 22 (Thur.)

The Second Battle of Ypres (see May 24) begins; poison gas is used by the Germans for the first time; the Canadians suffer heavily.

April 24 (Sat.)

A second German gas attack; the Germans storm St. Julien.

April 25 (Sun.)

Alsace:—The French lose ground on the Hartmannsweilerkopf.

April 25-26 (Sun.-Mon.)

The Allies land in Gallipoli (the Battle of Cape Helles).

April 27 (Tues.)

The Baltic Provinces are invaded by the Germans.

The British positions in Gallipoli are consolidated.

The French armoured cruiser Leon Gambetta is torpedoed and sunk at the entrance of the Straits of Otranto (night of 26-27).

The British submarine E14 enters the Sea of Marmora.

April 28 (Wed.)

The German offensive is held at Ypres.

Alsace:—The French retake the Hartmannsweilerkopf, the summit of which had been lost on the 25th.

Gallipoli:—The First Battle for Krithia: the Allies are repulsed.

An unsuccessful Turkish attack on the Suez Canal (the third).

South-West Africa:—The Germans are defeated at Gibeon.

French airmen raid Friedrichshafen.

April 29 (Thur.)

A Turkish transport is sunk by the E14 in the Sea of Marmora.

April 30 (Fri.)

A Zeppelin raid on East Anglia.

May 1 (Sat.)

The great Austro-German offensive in Western Galicia begins. In the Baltic Provinces the Germans occupy Shavli and approach Libau.

The Turks attack in Gallipoli.

The British destroyer Recruit is sunk by a submarine off the Galloper lightship. Two German torpedo boats are sunk by British destroyers in the North Sea.

May 2 (Sun.)

A German gas attack at Ypres is repulsed.

The Austro-Germans cross the Biala; Ciezkowice is taken.

The British counter-attack in Gallipoli.

May 3 (Mon.)

The British line at Ypres is shortened.

The Germans advance on the Eastern Front.

May 4 (Tues.)

Gallipoli:—The British fail in an attack at Gaba Tepe.

May 5 (Wed.)

The Germans recapture 'Hill 60' (see Apr. 21).

South-West Africa:—Union forces occupy Karibib.

May 6 (Thur.)

Gallipoli:—The Second Battle for Krithia begins (see May 8).

May 7 (Fri.)

The Lusitania is torpedoed by a German submarine off the Old Head of Kinsale; 1198 lives are lost (including 124 Americans).

The British destroyer Maori is sunk by a mine in the North Sea.

May 8 (Sat.)

A fierce German attack at Ypres.

The Russians are defeated in Galicia and in the Baltic Provinces. Libau is captured by the Germans.

Gallipoli:—The Second Battle for Krithia (see May 6) ends in a slight Allied advance.

May 9 (Sun.)

The British line is pushed back at Ypres. The British attack and gain ground (which is subsequently relinquished) near Fromelles.

The Battle of Souchez begins (see July 13).

Gallipoli:—Turkish trenches at Sari Bair are stormed by the Australians.

May 10 (Mon.)

The Germans retreat in the Baltic Provinces but continue to advance in Galicia.

May 11 (Tues.)

The Germans evacuate Shavli (Baltic Provinces) (see May 1).

The Cameroons:—Eseka is captured by the Allies.

May 12 (Wed.)

South-West Africa:—Union forces capture Windhoek, the capital of the Colony.

May 13 (Thur.)

A fierce German attack at Ypres: the British line is restored after hard fighting.

H.M.S. Goliath (battleship) is torpedoed off Gallipoli, while inside the Straits protecting the French flank.

May 14 (Fri.)

The Battle of the San: Jaroslav is taken by the Austro-Germans.

May 15 (Sat.)

The Caucasus:—The Russians capture Van.

May 16 (Sun.)

The Battle of Festubert begins: the British advance (see May 25).

The Austrians are defeated in South Poland.

A Zeppelin raid on Calais.

May 17 (Mon.)

The San is crossed by the Austro-Germans.

A Zeppelin raid on Ramsgate.

May 18 (Tues.)

Gallipoli:—The Turks attack the Australians and are repulsed.

May 19 (Wed.)

The Austro-Germans capture Lutkow (Galicia).

May 20 (Thur.)

Admiral von Essen, Commander-in-Chief of the Russian Baltic fleet, dies of pneumonia.

May 23 (Whit Sunday)

Italy declares war on Austria.

May 24 (Mon.)

The end of the Second Battle of Ypres (see April 22).

The Italians cross the frontier into Austria (midnight, 24th-25th).

May 25 (Tues.)

The formation of a new Coalition Ministry is announced in the House of Commons.

The end of the Battle of Festubert (see May 16); the British gains are consolidated.

H.M.S. Triumph (battleship) is sunk by a submarine off Gaba Tepe, Gallipoli.

May 26 (Wed.)

The constitution of the new British Government is announced: Prime Minister, Mr. Asquith; Foreign Secretary, Sir E. Grey; Secretary for India, Mr. Chamberlain; Secretary for War, Lord Kitchener; First Lord of the Admiralty, Mr. Balfour; Minister of Munitions, Mr. Lloyd George (see Aug. 4, 1914, and Dec. 10, 1916).

The British submarine E11 torpedoes a Turkish transport in Constantinople harbour.

A Zeppelin raid on Southend.

May 27 (Thur.)

The Italians capture Ala and Grado.

H.M.S. Majestic (battleship) is torpedoed off Cape Helles, Gallipoli.

A French air-raid on Ludwigshaven.

May 28 (Fri.)

The appointment of Admiral Sir Henry Jackson as First Sea Lord in succession to Lord Fisher is announced (see Oct. 29, 1914, and Nov. 29, 1916).

May 29 (Sat.)

The French capture Ablain (near Souchez).

The Italians occupy Valona (Albania).

May 30 (Sun.)

The Austro-Germans attack Przemysl.

May 31 (Mon.)

The French capture the sugar factory at Souchez.

A Zeppelin raid on London.

June 1 (Tues.)

The Austro-Germans capture Stryj.

June 2 (Wed.)

A German attack at Hooge is repulsed by the British.

June 3 (Thur.)

The Austro-Germans recapture Przemysl (see March 22).

Mesopotamia:—The British capture Amara.

June 4 (Fri.)

Gallipoli:—A third Allied attack on Krithia and Achi Baba results in a slight gain of ground at certain points.

A Zeppelin raid on the east coast of England.

June 6 (Sun.)

A Zeppelin raid on the east coast of England.

June 7 (Mon.)

The Italians begin a general advance on the Isonzo Front.

Sub-Lieut. R. A. J. Warneford destroys a Zeppelin over Belgium. A Zeppelin in its shed near Brussels is destroyed by British airmen.

June 8 (Tues.)

Stanislau is recaptured by the Austrians (see March 4).

June 9 (Wed.)

The Isonzo front:—Monfalcone is captured by the Italians.

June 10 (Thur.)

The Austro-Germans are defeated near Zurawno, where they had crossed the Dniester.

The Cameroons:—Garua surrenders to the Allies.

June 12 (Sat.)

The British Government rescinds the order concerning the treatment of German submarine prisoners (see March 8 and April 12).

June 14 (Mon.)

The Russian retirement on Grodek begins.

June 15 (Tues.)

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians attack the Podgora position.

A Zeppelin raid on the north-east coast of England.

A French air-raid on Karlsruhe.

June 16 (Wed.)

The British attack and gain ground on the Bellewarde Ridge, east of Ypres.

June 17 (Thur.)

The Isonzo Front:-The Italians attack at Plava.

June 18 (Fri.)

The Austrians are defeated at Plava, and the town is captured by the Italians.

Gallipoli:—The Turks attack and are repulsed.

An Austrian squadron raids Fano on the Italian coast.

June 20 (Sun.)

The Germans attack in the Argonne.

The Russians are defeated at Rava Russka; the Grodek position is turned.

June 21 (Mon.)

Gallipoli:—The Allies attack and gain ground.

June 22 (Tues.)

The Austrians recapture Lemberg (see Sept. 3, 1914).

June 23 (Wed.)

East Africa:—Bukoba on Lake Victoria Nyanza is captured by the British.

June 25 (Fri.)

The Cameroons:—The Allies capture Lome.

June 27 (Sun.)

The Austro-Germans occupy Halicz.

Gallipoli:—The British attack and gain ground.

June 29 (Tues.)

Gallipoli:—The Turks attack in strength (see July 1).

Cameroons:—The Allies occupy Ngaundere.

June 30 (Wed.)

The Russians retreat before a powerful German offensive between the Bug and the Vistula.

The British destroyer Lightning is sunk in the North Sea.

July 1 (Thur.)

Gallipoli:—The Turkish offensive fails completely after fierce fighting (see June 29).

July 2 (Fri.)

An offensive is launched by the Italians on the Isonzo: they advance on Gorizia (see July 29).

South-West Africa:—Union forces capture Otavifontein.

The German cruiser Pommern is torpedoed by a British submarine in the Baltic.

July 4 (Sun.)

Gallipoli:—A strong Turkish attack is repulsed.

South-West Africa:—The Germans are defeated at Gaub.

July 5 (Mon.)

The German advance on Warsaw is checked.

In the Aden Protectorate Lahej is taken by the Turks.

July 6 (Tues.)

The British capture trenches near Pilkem.

A German success at St. Mihiel.

The Russians defeat the Austrians near Krasnik.

July 7 (Wed.)

An Italian attack at Gorizia is repulsed.

July 8 (Thur.)

The Italian cruiser Amalfi is sunk by an Austrian submarine in the Adriatic.

July 9 (Fri.)

The German forces in South-West Africa surrender unconditionally to General Botha.

July 11 (Sun.)

The Königsberg is finally destroyed in the Rufiji River (East Africa) by British river monitors (see Oct. 30 and Nov. 10, 1914).

July 13 (Tues.)

The end of the Battle of Souchez (see May 9).

July 14 (Wed.)

The Austro-Germans launch an offensive which covers the whole Eastern Front; they capture Przasnysz (see Feb. 27).

July 15 (Thur.)

The Germans advance towards Riga.

July 16 (Fri.)

Heavy fighting on the Eastern Front; the Battle of Krasnostav begins.

July 18 (Sun.)

The Russians are defeated at Krasnostav.

Windau (on the coast of Courland) is captured by the Germans.

The Italian cruiser Giuseppe Garibaldi is sunk by an Austrian submarine.

July 19 (Mon.)

The Third Battle for Warsaw begins (see Aug. 5). The Germans force a crossing of the Upper Bug.

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians capture Monte San Michele.

July 20 (Tues.)

The Germans advance on Kovno (see Aug. 17).

The Isonzo Front:—An Italian success at Podgora.

July 21 (Wed.)

A British success at Hooge.

The Germans gain a crossing of the Vistula at Nova Alexandria.

July 22 (Thur.)

The Germans invest Ivangorod.

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians continue to gain ground.

July 23 (Fri.)

The Germans force a crossing of the Narev.

An Austrian squadron bombards Ortona (on the eastern coast of Italy).

July 25 (Sun.)

The Italians occupy the island of Pelagosa (Adriatic).

Mesopotamia:—Nasiriyeh is captured by the British.

July 26 (Mon.)

There is heavy fighting before Warsaw.

A British submarine sinks a German destroyer near the German coast.

July 27 (Tues.)

The Germans close in on three sides of Warsaw.

July 28 (Wed.)

The Germans cross the Vistula in force.

July 29 (Thur.)

The Russian line is broken on the Lublin-Cholm railway.

The end of the Italian offensive on the Isonzo (see July 2); it results in a valuable advance and the capture of many prisoners by the Italians.

July 30 (Fri.)

A successful German attack with liquid fire (first use of this) at Hooge; a British counter-attack fails (see Aug. 9).

The Austro-Germans occupy Lublin. The Russians retire rapidly.

A British submarine sinks a German transport in the Baltic.

July 31 (Sat.)

The Austro-Germans occupy Cholm.

Aug. 1 (Sun.)

Mitau is occupied by the Germans (see Aug. 16).

Rhodesia:—The Germans are driven back from Abercorn.

Aug. 3 (Tues.)

The Germans force the line of the Narev.

Aug. 4 (Wed.)

The Russians evacuate the Blonie lines, 15 miles west of Warsaw.

Aug. 5 (Thur.)

Warsaw, Ivangorod, and Vladimir Volynski are captured by the Austro-Germans (see July 19 and 22). The Russians prepare to evacuate Riga.

Aug. 6 (Fri.)

Gallipoli:—The Battles of Sari Bair (see Aug. 11) and Suvla (see Aug. 15) begin: the British effect a surprise landing in Suvla Bay and launch an offensive against the Turks at other points.

Aug. 7 (Sat.)

The Germans are repulsed near Riga.

Gallipoli:—Slight successes are gained against the Turkish positions above Suvla Bay.

Aug. 8 (Sun.)

Gallipoli:—The New Zealanders capture Chunuk Bair. This is the critical day at Suvla (see Aug. 10).

Persian Gulf:—Bushire is occupied by the British.

H.M.S. India (armed merchant cruiser) is sunk by a submarine off the Norwegian coast.

Aug. 9 (Mon.)

A successful British counter-attack at Hooge: the trenches lost on July 30 are recaptured.

A British submarine sinks a Turkish battleship, the Kheyr-ed-Din Barbarossa.

The British destroyer Lynx is mined off the Moray Firth.

A Zeppelin raid on the east coast of England.

A Zeppelin is destroyed near Ostend.

Aug. 10 (Tues.)

The German advance beyond the Vistula begins.

Gallipoli:—The Turks regain Chunuk Bair.

A German squadron fails to force its way into the Gulf of Riga (see Aug. 17, 18, and 21).

The German mine-layer and raider Meteor is blown up, to avoid capture by British cruisers near the German coast.

Aug. 11 (Wed.)

Gallipoli:—The end of the Battle of Sari Bair (see Aug. 6).

Aug. 12 (Thur.)

Syedlets (Poland) is taken by the Germans.

A Zeppelin raid on the east coast of England.

Aug. 14 (Sat.)

A German submarine sinks a British transport, the Royal Edward, in the Ægean (the first British transport to be lost).

Aug. 15 (Sun.)

The Germans take Vlodava (Poland).

Gallipoli:—The end of the Battle of Suvla (see Aug. 6).

Aug. 16 (Mon.)

The Russians retake Mitau (see Aug. 1).

Aug. 17 (Tues.)

The Germans capture Kovno (see July 20).

A German squadron enters the Gulf of Riga (see Aug. 10, 18, and 21).

Aug. 18 (Wed.)

The Germans cut the Brest-Bialystok railway.

A Russian naval success in the Gulf of Riga: the German squadron which has entered the Gulf suffers severe losses.

A British submarine torpedoes the German battle-cruiser Moltke in the Baltic.

The British submarine E13 is shelled by German warships when aground in Danish waters. She is wrecked and interned.

Aug. 19 (Thur.)

A German submarine sinks the White Star liner Arabic south of Ireland.

Aug. 20 (Fri.)

Italy declares war on Turkey.

Novo-Georgievsk is captured by the Germans; a further Russian retreat follows.

Aug. 21 (Sat.)

The British and French Governments declare cotton an absolute contraband of war.

Gallipoli:—A fresh British attack on the Turkish positions at Suvla fails.

The German naval forces retire from the Gulf of Riga (see Aug. 17 and 18).

Aug. 23 (Mon.)

The Germans take Ossowietz. The Austro-Germans occupy Kovel.

A Franco-British squadron bombards Zeebrugge.

Aug. 25 (Wed.)

Brest-Litovsk is taken by the Germans.

Aug. 26 (Thur.)

The Russians evacuate the fort of Olita on the Niemen.

A British aeroplane bombs and sinks a German submarine near Ostend.

Aug. 27 (Fri.)

Germany notifies the U.S.A. that her submarine commanders are henceforward forbidden to sink merchantmen without warning.

Aug. 28 (Sat.)

A great German attack on the Dvina line begins.

Aug. 30 (Mon.)

A Russian victory on the Strypa in Southern Galicia.

Sept. 1 (Wed.)

The Germans capture Lutsk (see Sept. 23 and 28) and storm part of the defences of Grodno. The Austro-Germans capture Brody (Galicia) (see Aug. 23, 1914).

Sept. 2 (Thur.) Sedan capitulated 1870.

The Germans capture Grodno. The Austro-Germans cross the Styr, the Sereth, and the Strypa.

The British transport Sutherland is torpedoed in the Ægean (loss of life small).

Sept. 3 (Fri.)

The Russians re-enter Grodno temporarily, but are forced across the Dvina at Friedrichstadt.

Sept. 4 (Sat.)

The Germans complete the occupation of Grodno.

A German submarine torpedoes the Allan liner Hesperian off Ireland.

Sept. 5 (Sun.)

The Tzar formally assumes command of the Russian armies; the Grand Duke Nicholas is appointed Viceroy in the Caucasus.

A British success at Hafiz Kor on the North-West Frontier of India.

Sept. 6 (Mon.)

A French air-raid on Saarbrücken.

Sept. 7 (Tues.)

The Battle of Tarnopol begins (see Aug. 23, 1914).

British and French warships bombard the Belgian coast.

A Zeppelin raid on the east coast of England (17 killed).

Sept. 8 (Wed.)

The Battle of Tarnopol on the Sereth ends in a Russian victory.

A Zeppelin raid on the east coast of England and on London (20 killed).

Sept. 9 (Thur.)

Further Russian successes on the Sereth.

Sept. 12 (Sun.)

The Germans storm Meiszagola and cut the Vilna-Dvinsk railway.

Sept. 16 (Thur.)

The Germans occupy Pinsk.

Sept. 18 (Sat.)

Vilna capitulates to the Germans.

British and French warships bombard the Belgian coast.

Sept. 19 (Sun.)

The British transport Ramazan is torpedoed and sunk in the Ægean with heavy loss of life in Indian troops.

Sept. 20 (Mon.)

The Russians retake Vidzy.

Sept. 22 (Wed.)

A French air-raid on Stuttgart.

Sept. 23 (Thur.)

The Russians retake Lutsk and Dubno (see Sept. 1 and 28).

Bulgaria mobilises (see Oct. 11).

Sept. 24 (Fri.)

A German attack on Dvinsk fails.

Sept. 25 (Sat.)

The Battle of Loos begins: the British capture Loos and make a considerable advance in its neighbourhood (see Oct. 15).

The French attack at the Vimy Ridge and in Champagne (the Battle of Champagne).

Mesopotamia:—General Townshend reaches Kut-el-Amara.

Sept. 26 (Sun.)

Fierce fighting round Loos and Hulluch; the British lose ground.

The French capture Souchez.

Sept. 28 (Tues.)

The Russians abandon Lutsk (see Sept. 1 and 23).

Mesopotamia:—The First Battle of Kut-el-Amara begins.

The Italian battleship Benedetto Brin is destroyed by an accidental explosion.

Sept. 29 (Wed.)

Heavy fighting for the Hohenzollern Redoubt (near Loos).

Heavy fighting on the French front in Champagne and on the Vimy Ridge.

Mesopotamia:—The British capture Kut-el-Amara and 2000 prisoners.

Oct. 3 (Sun.)

The Germans counter-attack near Loos and retake most of the Hohenzollern Redoubt.

A great battle for Dvinsk begins (see Oct. 10).

Oct. 4 (Mon.)

Russian ultimatum to Bulgaria.

The Caucasus:—The Turks are defeated by the Russians near Van.

Oct. 5 (Tues.)

Lord Derby is appointed Director of Recruiting in Great Britain.

M. Venizelos resigns and M. Zaimis becomes Greek Premier (see Nov. 4).

Allied troops land at Salonika.

Oct. 6 (Wed.)

Crossings of the Save and the Danube are forced by the Austro-Germans; Serbia is thus invaded for the fourth time.

Oct. 8 (Fri.)

German counter-attacks in Champagne and near Loos are repulsed with heavy loss.

The Austro-Germans capture Belgrade.

Oct. 9 (Sat.)

Austria invades Montenegro.

The Cameroons:—Wum Biagas is captured by the British.

Oct. 10 (Sun.)

The German attack on Dvinsk fails (see Oct. 3).

Semendria is taken by the Austrians.

Oct. 11 (Mon.)

Bulgaria invades Serbia (see Oct. 14). Serbia appeals to Greece for aid.

Oct. 12 (Tues.)

Edith Cavell is executed at Brussels.

Greece refuses Serbia's appeal.

The Russians attack near Dvinsk.

A Zeppelin raid on London (many casualties).

Oct. 13 (Wed.)

M. Delcassé, the French Minister for Foreign Affairs, resigns.

The British attack near Loos with partial success.

A Zeppelin raid on London (59 killed).

Oct. 14 (Thur.)

Bulgaria declares war on Serbia (see Oct. 11).

A Russian success near Dvinsk.

Oct. 15 (Fri.)

Great Britain declares war on Bulgaria.

The end of the Battle of Loos (see Sept. 25).

The Bulgarians take Vranja.

Oct. 16 (Sat.)

France declares war on Bulgaria.

Alsace:—The French recover the Hartmannsweilerkopf (lost after much previous fighting).

Sir Ian Hamilton is recalled from Gallipoli, Sir Charles Monro being appointed to succeed him.

Oct. 17 (Sun.)

The Italians capture Pregasina.

A French air-raid on Trèves.

Oct. 18 (Mon.)

Sir Edward Carson resigns his seat in the British Cabinet.

The Germans advance on Riga.

Oct. 19 (Tues.)

Italy declares war on Bulgaria.

A French force drives the Bulgarians from Strumnitza.

Oct. 21 (Thur.) Trafalgar, 1805.

The Bulgarians capture Veles (see Oct. 25 and 29).

An Allied squadron bombards the harbour of Dedeagatch and other points of military importance on the Bulgarian coast.

Oct. 22 (Fri.)

The 'Group' system of enlistment comes into operation in Great Britain.

The Bulgarians capture Uskub and Rumanovo.

The Italians advance on the Isonzo front.

Oct. 23 (Sat.)

The Austro-Germans force the passage of the Danube at Orsova.

Mesopotamia:—The British reach Azizie in their advance on Baghdad.

A British submarine sinks the German cruiser Prinz Adalbert in the Baltic.

Oct. 24 (Sun.)

The Germans are within ten miles of Riga.

The Danube route to Constantinople is opened to the Germans by their victories in Serbia.

Oct. 25 (Mon.)

The Austro-German and Bulgarian forces effect a junction in the Kraina district. The Serbians recapture Veles (see Oct. 21 and 29).

The Cameroons:—Sende is occupied by the French.

The British destroyer Velox is mined off the Nab lightship.

Oct. 26 (Tues.)

The British transport Marquette is torpedoed in the Ægean.

Oct. 27 (Wed.)

French troops effect a junction with the Serbians at Veles. The French and British are in position across the Vardar.

The Russian Black Sea Fleet bombards Varna.

Oct. 28 (Thur.)

The French Ministry resigns: M. Briand becomes Premier (see March 17, 1917).

King George is thrown from his horse and injured in France.

Sir Charles Monro assumes command in Gallipoli.

H.M.S. Argyll (cruiser) is wrecked off the east coast of Scotland (no lives lost).

Oct. 29 (Fri.)

Veles is retaken by the Bulgarians (see Oct. 21 and 25).

The British mine-sweeper Hythe is sunk off Gallipoli.

Oct. 30 (Sat.)

The Germans capture the Butte of Tahure.

The Serbian arsenal at Kragujevatz is captured by the Austrians.

The Cameroons:—Eseka is captured by the Allies.

Oct. 31 (Sun.)

A Russian counter-offensive near Dvinsk begins.

Nov. 2 (Tues.)

A Russian success on the Strypa: 5000 prisoners are taken.

An Italian success on the Isonzo front.

Nov. 3 (Wed.)

The Russians advance south-east of Dvinsk.

The British transport Woodfield is sunk by a submarine off Morocco (loss of life small).

The Cameroons:—Tibati is occupied by the Allies.

Nov. 4 (Thur.)

The resignation of M. Zaimis, the Greek Premier, is announced (see Oct. 5).

Turkish attacks at Anzac are repulsed.

Nov. 5 (Fri.)

The Russians force back the Germans in the Riga district.

Serbia:—Nish is captured by the Bulgarians after three days' fierce fighting. The main German and Bulgarian forces effect a junction at Krivivir, north of Nish.

Nov. 6 (Sat.)

M. Skouloudis becomes Greek Premier (see June 22, 1916).

A British success at Bango Mountain in the Cameroons.

The British submarine E20 is lost in the Dardanelles.

Nov. 7 (Sun.)

A Note is received from the U.S.A. protesting against the maritime policy of Great Britain and France.

The Russians capture Olai (west of Riga).

A German submarine sinks the Italian liner Ancona off Sardinia; many are drowned, including 25 Americans.

A British submarine sinks the German light cruiser Undine in the Baltic.

Nov. 9 (Tues.)

A Russian victory near Kolki, on the Styr: 3500 prisoners are taken.

Nov. 10 (Wed.)

Heavy fighting between the Russians and the Germans near Riga.

Nov. 11 (Thur.)

The War Committee of the British Cabinet is appointed. Mr. Churchill leaves the Government.

A Russian victory at Kemmern near Riga: the Germans are forced to retreat.

Nov. 12 (Fri.)

The Germans henceforward control the railway from Belgrade to Constantinople.

Mesopotamia:—The British under General Townshend advance on Ctesiphon.

Nov. 14 (Sun.)

Fierce fighting for the 'Labyrinth' in Artois.

An Austrian air-raid on Verona.

Nov. 15 (Mon.)

An Austrian success on the Styr.

Gallipoli:—A successful attack is made on Turkish trenches by the 52nd Division.

Nov. 16 (Tues.)

The Bulgarians capture Prilep. The French repulse Bulgarian attacks between Krivolak and Strumnitza.

Nov. 17 (Wed.)

The British hospital ship Anglia is sunk by a mine in the Channel (85 lives lost).

Nov. 21 (Sun.)

Serbia:—Fall of Novi Bazar to the Germans.

Nov. 22 (Mon.)

A German success on the Dvina.

Mesopotamia:—The Battle of Ctesiphon begins: the chief Turkish positions are captured (see Nov. 24).

A revolt, instigated by Germany, breaks out in Persia.

Nov. 23 (Tues.)

The Serbians retreat towards Albania. The Serbian Government leaves Mitrovitza for Prisrend.

Rovereto is taken by the Italians.

Nov. 24 (Wed.)

Mesopotamia:—The Battle of Ctesiphon ends in the defeat of the Turks, but at the price of very heavy British losses (see Nov. 22).

Nov. 25 (Thur.)

Serbia:—The Austrians capture Mitrovitza and Prishtina. The Serbian seat of Government is moved to Scutari in Albania.

Mesopotamia:—The British retreat from Ctesiphon towards Azizie.

Nov. 28 (Sun.)

The Serbian army retreats into Albania.

A German submarine is sunk off the Belgian coast by a bomb from a British aeroplane.

Nov. 29 (Mon.)

The Bulgarians occupy Prisrend.

Nov. 30 (Tues.)

Mesopotamia:—The British retreat from Azizie on Kut-el-Amara.

Dec. 3 (Fri.)

Mesopotamia:—The British reach Kut-el-Amara.

Dec. 4 (Sat.)

British reinforcements are landed at Salonika.

Dec. 5 (Sun.)

Serbia:—Monastir is taken by the Bulgarians.

Dec. 6 (Mon.)

The Allied Council meets in Paris (its first meeting).

The Bulgarians attack the British near Lake Doiran.

Dec. 7 (Tues.)

Ipek (Montenegro) is taken by the Austrians; the British are forced back from Lake Doiran; the Allies begin to retire from Serbia into Greece.

Mesopotamia:—The siege of Kut-el-Amara begins (see April 29, 1916).

Dec. 8 (Wed.)

Gallipoli:—The evacuation of Suvla and Anzac begins (see Dec. 20, 1915, and Jan. 8, 1916).

Dec. 9 (Thur.)

The Bulgarians occupy Diakhova, Dibra, and Okrida.

Dec. 11 (Sat.)

Macedonia:—The French and British repel Bulgarian attacks with heavy loss.

Persia:—The Russians occupy Hamadan after defeating the Persian rebels.

Dec. 12 (Sun.)

Recruiting for the 'Derby' groups is closed in Great Britain.

The Franco-British forces are in position before Salonika.

The Bulgarians capture Doiran and Ghevgeli.

Mesopotamia:—A Turkish attack on Kut-el-Amara is repulsed.

Dec. 13 (Mon.)

Western Egypt:—In an action near Mersa Matruh an attack by Senussi Arabs is repulsed.

Dec. 14 (Tues.)

It is announced that Sir H. Smith-Dorrien is appointed to Supreme Command in East Africa (see Feb. 10, 1916).

Dec. 15 (Wed.)

Resignation of Sir John French; Sir Douglas Haig succeeds him as British Commander-in-Chief in France.

Dec. 17 (Fri.)

The German light cruiser Bremen and a German torpedo boat are sunk in the Baltic by Allied submarines.

Albania:—Elbasan is taken by the Bulgarians.

Dec. 20 (Mon.)

The first 'Derby' groups are called up for service.

Gallipoli:—The evacuation of Anzac and Suvla is completed (see Dec. 8).

Albania:—Durazzo is occupied by the Italians.

Persia:—The Russians occupy Kum; this marks the end of the Persian revolt.

Dec. 21 (Tues.)

Sir William Robertson is appointed Chief of the British Imperial General Staff (see Feb. 16, 1918).

The Cameroons:—Mangeles is occupied by the French.

Dec. 24 (Fri.)

The French liner Ville de Ciotat is torpedoed in the Mediterranean.

Dec. 25 (Sat.)

Western Egypt:—The main Senussi force is attacked and routed near Mersa Matruh.

Mesopotamia:—Turkish attacks on Kut-el-Amara are repulsed.

Dec. 27 (Mon.)

Heavy fighting between the Russians and the Austrians on the Bessarabia-Bukovina frontier.

Dec. 28 (Tues.)

The decision of the British Cabinet in favour of Compulsory Service is announced.

The Indian Corps leaves France.

Dec. 29 (Wed.)

In a sea fight off Cattaro a French submarine and two Austrian destroyers are sunk.

Dec. 30 (Thur.)

The P. & O. liner Persia is torpedoed in the Mediterranean.

Dec. 31 (Fri.)

H.M.S. Natal (cruiser) is blown up in Cromarty Firth by an internal explosion.

1916

Jan. 1 (Sat.)

The Russians gain successes on the Styr and the Strypa.

The Cameroons:—The British capture Jaunde (the capital of the German colony).

Jan. 2 (Sun.)

The Russians approach Czernowitz.

The British passenger steamer Glengyle is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean.

Jan. 4 (Tues.)

Lord Derby's report on the recruiting campaign in Great Britain is issued.

Mesopotamia:—The Kut relieving force advances from Ali-el-Gharb.

Jan. 5 (Wed.)

The Military Service Bill that inaugurates conscription is introduced in the British House of Commons.

The Russians advance in the Bukovina.

Jan. 6 (Thur.)

Recruiting for the 'Derby' groups reopens in Great Britain.

Mesopotamia:—The British relieving force defeats the Turks before Kut, but its further progress is checked by floods.

H.M.S. King Edward VII. (battleship) is sunk by a mine off the north coast of Scotland.

Jan. 8 (Sat.)

The evacuation of Gallipoli is completed (see Dec. 8, 1915).

The Russians capture Chartorysk (50 miles east of Kovel).

Jan. 10 (Mon.)

Montenegro:—The Austrians capture Mount Lovtchen.

Jan. 11 (Tues.)

A French force lands at Corfu to prepare for the transfer thither of Serbian troops from Albania.

The Caucasus:—The Russians advance on Erzerum.

Jan. 13 (Thur.)

Cettinje, the capital of Montenegro, is occupied by the Austrians.

Mesopotamia:—The Turks are again defeated before Kut.

Jan. 14 (Fri.)

An Austrian cruiser is sunk off Cattaro by a French submarine.

Jan. 15 (Sat.)

The first Serbian troops land at Corfu.

The steamship Ariadne is sunk by the Möwe.

Jan. 16 (Sun.)

A Russian success near Pinsk.

General Sarrail assumes command of the Allied forces at Salonika.

A battle begins in the Caucasus (near Erzerum) between the Russians and the Turks.

The liner Appam is captured by the Möwe off the Canaries (see Feb. 1 and March 4).

Jan. 17 (Mon.)

A Russian victory in the Caucasus: the Turks retire on Erzerum.

The Clan MacTavish is sunk by the Möwe.

Jan. 18 (Tues.)

Allied warships bombard Dedeagatch and Porto Lagos on the Bulgarian coast.

Jan. 21 (Fri.)

Mesopotamia:—Action of Um-el-Hannah: the Kut relieving force is repulsed.

Jan. 22 (Sat.)

Montenegro:—Antivari is taken by the Austrians.

Jan. 23 (Sun.)

The Austrians complete their possession of Montenegro by the occupation of Scutari.

Western Egypt:—A British column disperses the Senussi Arabs and burns their camp.

A German air-raid on Kent.

A French air-raid on Metz.

Jan. 24 (Mon.)

German attacks near Neuville meet with some success.

A French air-raid on Monastir.

Jan. 27 (Thur.)

The U.S.A. Government publishes a Note of protest against the British search of mails.

A German attack on the British near Loos is repulsed.

Jan. 29 (Sat.)

A Zeppelin raid on Paris.

Jan. 31 (Mon.)

A Zeppelin raid on the Midlands (67 killed); a Zeppelin, the L19, is wrecked in the North Sea while returning from the raid.

Feb. 1 (Tues.)

The British liner Appam arrives at Norfolk, Virginia, manned by a German prize crew.

A German air-raid on Salonika.

Feb. 2 (Wed.)

The Dutch steamer Artemis is torpedoed by a German submarine.

Feb. 3 (Thur.)

Mesopotamia:—Heavy fighting before Kut.

Feb. 4 (Fri.)

Heavy fighting round Dvinsk.

Feb. 8 (Tues.)

The Russians cross the Dniester.

The French cruiser Amiral Charnier is sunk by a mine or submarine off the Syrian coast.

Feb. 9 (Wed.)

A German air-raid on Ramsgate and Broadstairs. A British air-raid on Terhand.

Feb. 10 (Thur.)

The Military Service Act (instituting compulsory service for single men aged 19 to 30) comes into operation in Great Britain.

It is announced that Sir H. Smith-Dorrien resigns command in East Africa owing to ill-health (see Dec. 14, 1915), and that Lieut.-General J. Smuts is appointed to succeed him (see Jan. 28, 1917).

The Caucasus:—The Russian attack on Erzerum begins (see Feb. 16).

The reorganised Serbian army (75,000 troops) is successfully concentrated at Corfu.

British mine-sweepers are attacked off the Dogger Bank; the Arabis is sunk.

Feb. 11 (Fri.)

H.M.S. Arethusa (light cruiser) is sunk by a mine off the East Coast.

Feb. 12 (Sat.)

The Germans make several attempts to cross the Yser Canal.

German attacks near Vimy are repulsed.

Feb. 13 (Sun.)

The Caucasus:—A Russian success at Erzerum.

Feb. 14 (Mon.)

A German success at 'the Bluff,' near Ypres: the British lose trenches (see March 2).

An Austrian air-raid on Milan.

Feb. 16 (Wed.)

Verdun is cleared of its civilian population.

The Caucasus:—Erzerum is captured by the Russians (see Feb. 10).

Feb. 19 (Sat.)

German attacks are repulsed south of Arras and north of Ypres.

The Caucasus:—The Russians capture Akhlat and Mush, north-west of Lake Van (see Aug. 2).

The Cameroons:—The last German post in the Mora Mountains surrenders; this completes the occupation of the Cameroons by the Allies (see Aug. 25, 1914).

Feb. 20 (Sun.)

A German air-raid on Walmer and Lowestoft.

A British air-raid on Don, in Flanders.

Feb. 21 (Mon.)

The Battle of Verdun begins (see July 1).

A Zeppelin is destroyed near Revigny.

Feb. 22 (Tues.)

The Germans gain ground before Verdun, capturing Haumont Wood and the French salient north of Beaumont.

Feb. 23 (Wed.)

Portugal seizes interned German ships (see March 10).

Further German progress and French withdrawals before Verdun.

Feb. 24 (Thur.)

The French resist strongly before Verdun, but the German advance continues.

Feb. 25 (Fri.)

A critical day in the Battle of Verdun: Fort Douaumont is stormed by the Germans.

Feb. 26 (Sat.)

German attacks beyond Fort Douaumont are repulsed by the French; this ends the first stage of the Battle of Verdun.

Western Egypt:—The Senussi Arabs are defeated at Agagia.

The French transport Provence II. is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean with heavy loss of life.

Feb. 27 (Sun.)

Verdun:—A heavy bombardment by the Germans and some infantry fighting.

Durazzo is captured by the Austrians.

Persia:—Kermanshah is captured by the Russians (see July 2, 1916).

The P. & O. liner Maloja is sunk by a mine off Dover.

Feb. 29 (Tues.)

An action is fought in the North Sea between H.M.S. Alcantara (armed merchant cruiser) and the German raider Greif, in which both are sunk.

Mar. 1 (Wed.)

H.M.S. Primula (sloop) is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean.

Mar. 2 (Thur.)

A British success near Ypres: 'the Bluff' is recaptured (see Feb. 14).

Verdun:—The Germans capture the village of Douaumont.

The Caucasus:—Bitlis (south-west of Lake Van) is captured by the Russians (see Aug. 2).

Mar. 3 (Fri.)

Verdun:—The French reoccupy Douaumont village; the Germans attack the village of Vaux.

Mar. 4 (Sat.)

There is fierce fighting for the Hohenzollern Redoubt (near Loos).

Verdun:—The Germans again capture the village of Douaumont.

The German Admiralty announces the safe return of the raider Möwe.

Mar. 5 (Sun.)

Persia:—Sinneh is taken by the Russians.

A Zeppelin raid on the north-east coast of England.

Mar. 6 (Mon.)

Verdun:—The Germans advance up the northern slopes of the Côte de l'Oie.

Mar. 7 (Tues.)

A further German success at Verdun: Hill 265 is carried.

East Africa:—The British advance in the Kilimanjaro district.

The Caucasus:—Rizeh is captured by the Russians.

H.M.S. Coquette (destroyer) and the British torpedo boat No. 11 are sunk by mines off the east coast of England.

Mar. 8 (Wed.)

Heavy fighting at Verdun: the French regain ground.

Mesopotamia:—The second attempt to relieve Kut fails, the British being repulsed at Es Sinn.

The Caucasus:—The Russians advance towards Trebizond.

A French air-raid on Metz.

Mar. 9 (Thurs.)

Mesopotamia:—The British relieving force falls back from Es Sinn.

H.M.S. Fauvette (armed boarding-steamer) is sunk by a mine off the east coast of England.

Mar. 10 (Fri.)

Germany declares war on Portugal (see Feb. 23).

Mar. 11 (Sat)

East Africa:—Further British successes west of Taveta and near Kilimanjaro: the Germans retreat.

Mar. 12 (Sun.)

Persia:—Kerind is occupied by the Russians.

East Africa:—Moshi is occupied by the British.

Mar. 14 (Tues.)

The Caucasus:—The Russians occupy Mamakhatun (see May 31).

Egypt:—The British occupy Sollum.

Mar. 16 (Thurs.)

The resignation of Grand Admiral von Tirpitz as Head of the German Navy is announced. He is succeeded by Admiral von Capelle.

Verdun:—Heavy German attacks are repulsed.

The Dutch liner Tubantia is sunk by a German submarine.

Mar. 17 (Fri.)

A fresh German offensive is launched against Russia.

Egypt:—A motor force under the Duke of Westminster rescues British prisoners from the Senussi by a successful raid.

Mar. 18 (Sat.)

A German success at the Hohenzollern Redoubt.

The First Battle of Lake Narotch (east of Vilna) begins (see April 14).

The Dutch liner Palembang is sunk by a German submarine.

The French destroyer Renaudin is sunk by an enemy submarine in the Adriatic.

Allied air-raids on Metz and Zeebrugge.

Mar. 19 (Sun.)

Persia:—Ispahan is captured by the Russians.

An air-raid on Kent by German seaplanes (one destroyed).

Mar. 20 (Mon.)

Verdun:—Renewed German attacks fail.

Heavy fighting near Dvinsk and Riga.

An action is fought between British and German destroyers off the Belgian coast: the Germans run for Zeebrugge.

A big raid by Allied aeroplanes on Zeebrugge.

Mar. 22 (Wed.)

Verdun:—The Germans carry Avocourt Wood.

A Russian success near Dvinsk.

Mar. 24 (Fri.)

The Sussex (passenger steamer) is torpedoed in the Channel by a German submarine.

Mar. 25 (Sat.)

The Russians attack the Germans near Vilna.

A raid by British seaplanes, convoyed by light cruisers and destroyers, on German airship sheds in Schleswig-Holstein: the British destroyer Medusa is lost by collision, and two German patrol boats are sunk in the naval action which develops.

Mar. 27 (Mon.)

A Conference of the Allies is held in Paris.

A British success at St. Eloi: German trenches are captured (see April 7).

The Russians again attack near Vilna.

A German air-raid on Salonika.

Mar. 28 (Tues.)

Verdun:—The German attacks are renewed.

Mar. 30 (Thur.)

Verdun:—There is heavy fighting for Fort Douaumont; the Germans capture Malancourt.

The Russian hospital ship Portugal is sunk by an enemy submarine in the Black Sea.

Mar. 31 (Fri.)

The British G.H.Q. are moved from St. Omer to Montreuil.

A Zeppelin raid on England (which is followed by four more within a week). The Zeppelin L15 is brought down at the mouth of the Thames.

April 1 (Sat.)

Verdun:—The Germans gain ground at Fort Vaux.

A Zeppelin raid on the north-east coast of England.

April 2 (Sun.)

An explosion occurs in a munitions factory at Faversham, Kent (106 killed).

A Zeppelin raid on England and Scotland.

April 3 (Mon.)

A British success at St. Eloi.

A French success at Verdun.

The Caucasus:—A Russian attack on Trebizond begins (see April 18).

April 4 (Tues.)

Verdun:—The Germans attack at Douaumont and are repulsed.

General Brussiloff succeeds General Ivanoff in command of the Russian armies of the South.

A Zeppelin raid on the Eastern Counties.

April 5 (Wed.)

A Zeppelin raid on the north-east of England.

April 6 (Thur.)

Mesopotamia:—A third attempt is made to relieve Kut: the Um-el-Hannah and Falahiyah positions are captured.

April 7 (Fri.)

The Germans regain the trenches captured by the British at St. Eloi on March 27.

The Russians again attack the German lines near Vilna.

Macedonia:—The Allied positions on the Vardar are bombarded.

April 8 (Sat.)

Fierce fighting at Verdun: the French evacuate Bethincourt.

April 9 (Sun.)

The British regain ground at St. Eloi.

Verdun:—A fierce German attack on the Mort Homme.

Mesopotamia:—The first British attack on the Sanna-i-Yat position is repulsed.

April 10 (Mon.)

A British success at St. Eloi.

A critical day at Verdun: German attacks on the Mort Homme are repulsed.

April 11 (Tues.)

The Germans attack near Albert and continue their attacks at Verdun.

Italy:—The Alpini gain a success on the Adamello glacier.

April 12 (Wed.)

Mesopotamia:—The British make a second attack on the Sanna-i-Yat position: some ground is gained.

April 13 (Thur.)

Egypt:—Australian troops destroy a Turkish camp at Jifjaffa on the Egyptian frontier.

April 14 (Fri.)

The end of the First Battle of Lake Narotch (see March 18); it leads to little change of position.

British naval aeroplanes bomb Constantinople and Adrianople.

April 15 (Sat.)

A Russian success in the Caucasus.

April 16 (Sun.)

Verdun:—The French attack at Douaumont and regain ground.

April 17 (Mon.)

Fresh German attacks at Verdun, which gain ground.

The Italians capture the Col di Lana (Trentino).

Mesopotamia:—A Turkish counter-attack on the Tigris is partially successful.

April 18 (Tues.)

The Caucasus:—Trebizond is captured by the Russians (see April 8).

April 19 (Wed.)

Verdun:—German attacks at Les Eparges are repulsed.

A Note from the U.S.A. is presented to Germany demanding modification of her submarine policy (see May 4).

The Caucasus:—The Russians carry a strong enemy position west of Erzerum.

April 20 (Thur.)

The rebellion breaks out in Ireland (see May 1).

Verdun:—The French gain ground near Fort Vaux.

Russian troops reach Marseilles.

April 21 (Good Friday)

Sir Roger Casement is captured on the coast of Kerry, near Tralee (see June 26, Aug. 3).

April 22 (Sat.)

Mesopotamia:—A third British attack on the Sanna-i-Yat position is repulsed.

A British success in German East Africa, by which the occupation of the northern half of the colony is made secure.

April 23 (Easter Sunday)

An engagement at Katia on the Egyptian frontier.

April 24 (Mon.)

Riots in Dublin: the Sinn Feiners occupy the Post Office and St. Stephen's Green.

Mesopotamia (night of the 24th-25th):—An unsuccessful attempt is made to run a supply ship into Kut.

April 25 (Tues.)

German battle-cruisers bombard Lowestoft and Great Yarmouth; they are pursued home but escape in safety.

A Zeppelin raid on the eastern counties of England.

April 26 (Wed.)

Fighting in Dublin.

A Zeppelin raid on Kent.

April 27 (Thur.)

Martial law is proclaimed throughout Ireland.

H.M.S. Russell (battleship) is sunk by a mine off Malta.

H.M.S. Nasturtium (sloop) is sunk by a mine in the Mediterranean.

The German submarine UC5 is captured in the North Sea.

April 28 (Fri.)

The Second Battle of Lake Narotch: a Russian reverse.

April 29 (Sat.)

Italy:—The Austrians are driven from the Adamello glacier by Alpini.

Mesopotamia:—Kut-el-Amara capitulates, after a siege of 144 days, owing to failure of supplies (see Dec. 7, 1915).

May 1 (Mon.)

The Irish rebellion is crushed (see April 20).

A Zeppelin raid on Scotland and the northeast of England.

May 2 (Tues.)

Resignation of Mr. Birrell, Secretary of State for Ireland.

Verdun:—A French success at the Mort Homme.

A Zeppelin raid on Scotland and England: the Zeppelin L20, returning from this raid, is wrecked off Norway.

May 3 (Wed.)

Verdun:—Fresh German attacks on the Mort Homme begin.

May 4 (Thur.)

Germany, in a Note to the U.S.A., agrees to sink no ships without warning (see April 19).

The Zeppelin L 7 is destroyed off Schleswig by the gunfire of British warships.

May 5 (Fri.)

Verdun:—Fierce fighting for Hill 304.

A Zeppelin is destroyed near Salonika.

May 7 (Sun.)

Verdun:—A great German attack on Hill 304 results in a slight gain of ground.

May 8 (Mon.)

Verdun:—The Germans lose ground at the Mort Homme and Fort Douaumont.

The White Star liner Cymric is torpedoed without warning by a German submarine near the Irish coast.

May 10 (Wed.)

Persia:—Kasr-i-Shirin is occupied by the Russians.

May 11 (Thur.)

A German success near Vermelles: 500 yards of British front-line trenches are captured.

May 12 (Fri.)

A British counter-attack near Vermelles is partially successful.

May 13 (Sat.)

The Germans attack the British at Ploegsteert Wood and are repulsed.

The Caucasus:—The Russians retire on Erzerum.

The British monitor M30 is sunk in action in the Gulf of Smyrna.

May 14 (Sun.)

Italy:—The Battle of the Trentino begins (see June 4).

May 15 (Mon.)

The British capture a German trench on the Vimy Ridge.

The Austrians advance in the Trentino.

May 16 (Tues.)

A Turkish force is defeated by an Australian detachment in the Sinai Peninsula.

May 17 (Wed.)

Verdun:—Fresh German attacks on Hill 304 are unsuccessful.

British monitors engage German destroyers off the Belgian coast and put them to flight.

May 18 (Thur.)

An Air Board is constituted in Great Britain.

The Italians retire in the Trentino.

Sinai Peninsula:—A British raid on El Arish.

Mesopotamia:—Russian cavalry, after a ride of 200 miles from the Persian frontier, join the British on the Tigris.

May 19 (Fri.)

A British success at Vimy Ridge.

Mesopotamia:—The Turks evacuate the Es Sinn position and withdraw to Kut.

A German air-raid on Kent.

May 20 (Sat.)

Verdun:—Fierce fighting for the Mort Homme.

A further Italian withdrawal in the Trentino.

May 21 (Sun.)

The Germans win trenches from the British on the Vimy Ridge.

Verdun:—Part of the Mort Homme is captured by the Germans, but the French advance on the Douaumont Plateau and carry the Haudromont quarries.

Mesopotamia:—The British advance on the south bank of the Tigris.

May 22 (Mon.)

The Sudan:—The action of Beringia: the Sultan of Darfur is defeated.

May 23 (Tues.) Ramillies, 1706.

The Sudan:—El Fasher, the capital of Darfur, is captured by the British.

May 24 (Wed.)

Verdun:—Cumières is stormed by the Germans.

May 25 (Thur.)

Compulsory service for married as well as single men between 18 and 41 becomes law in Great Britain, to take effect from June 24.

The Germans win successes at Verdun and Vimy.

Italy:—Bettale is taken by the Austrians.

May 26 (Fri.)

The Bulgarians and Germans advance into Greek Macedonia and capture Fort Rupel.

May 29 (Mon.)

A great German attack at Verdun: the French line holds.

A renewed British advance in German East Africa: Neu Langenburg is occupied.

May 30 (Tues.)

Verdun:—The French abandon the Bethincourt-Cumières road.

Italy:—The battle for the Pass of Buola.

East Africa:—A Belgian force invades Ruanda.

May 31 (Wed.) Union Day, South Africa, 1910.

The Battle of Jutland is fought between the main British and German fleets: the German fleet, with considerable loss, escapes aided by mist.

Italy:—Asiago and Arsiero are captured by the Austrians (see June 25 and 27).

The Caucasus:—Mamakhatun is retaken by the Turks (see March 14 and July 12).

June 1 (Thur.)

Verdun:—The Germans begin a fresh attack on Fort Vaux.

June 2 (Fri.)

The Germans capture trenches from the Canadians at Ypres (see June 13), and from the French at Verdun.

June 4 (Sun.)

Verdun:—Fort Vaux is isolated.

A great Russian offensive is launched in the Bukovina and the Ukraine (with the 8th and 9th Armies): rapid progress is made, and many thousands of prisoners are captured.

The end of the Battle of the Trentino: the Austrian advance is checked (see May 14).

June 5 (Mon.)

H.M.S. Hampshire is sunk off the Orkneys and Lord Kitchener drowned.

June 6 (Tues.)

The Germans gain ground from the British at Hooge.

Verdun:—Fierce German attacks on Fort Vaux.

The Russians capture Lutsk from the Austrians.

June 7 (Wed.)

Verdun:—Fort Vaux is captured by the Germans.

June 8 (Thur.)

The Russian 7th Army launches an offensive in Eastern Galicia: Buczacz is captured.

June 9 (Fri.)

The War Council of the Allies meets in London.

Arabia:—The Emir Hussein, Grand Sherif of Mecca, revolts against the Turks and gains possession of Mecca.

The Italian transport Principe Umberto is sunk by a submarine in the Adriatic (many lives lost).

June 10 (Sat.)

A great Russian victory near Czernowitz: 35,000 prisoners are captured.

East Africa:—Momba is occupied by the British.

June 11 (Whit Sunday)

Verdun:—A German advance near Thiaumont.

Venice is bombed by Austrian seaplanes.

June 12 (Mon.)

The Germans are within four miles of Verdun.

A further Russian advance in the Bukovina.

Southern Persia:—Kerman is occupied by a British force.

June 13 (Tues.)

The Canadians win back the trenches they had lost at Ypres (from south of Sanctuary Wood to north of Hill 60: see June 2).

The Russian 4th Army advances on Baranovitchi.

In the Baltic, Russian destroyers attack a convoy of German steamers escorted by warships: they sink the German auxiliary cruiser Herrmann and two German torpedo boats.

June 14 (Wed.)

The Allied Economic Conference meets in Paris.

The British occupy Wilhelmsthal, the capital of German East Africa.

June 15 (Thur.)

Fresh German attacks at Verdun.

Russian victories on the Strypa and on the frontiers of Galicia.

Mesopotamia:—A British success on the Tigris.

June 16 (Fri.)

Arabia:—The Grand Sherif of Mecca captures Jeddah from the Turks.

H.M.S. Eden (destroyer) is sunk by a collision in the Channel.

June 17 (Sat.)

Czernowitz is again captured by the Russians.

June 18 (Sun.)

Death of von Moltke.

Immelman, the famous German airman, is shot down by a British airman.

Russian progress continues in the Bukovina.

June 19 (Mon.)

Fierce fighting between the Russians and Austrians before Kovel.

June 21 (Wed.)

A Note is presented to the Greek Government by Great Britain, France, and Russia, demanding complete demobilisation of the Greek army.

June 22 (Thur.)

M. Skouloudis, the Greek Premier, resigns and is succeeded by M. Zaimis (see Nov. 4, 1915, and Sept. 11, 1916). Greece accepts the Allies' demands.

The Germans are within three miles of Verdun.

Further Russian progress in the Bukovina.

June 23 (Fri.)

Fierce German attacks at Verdun: Fort Thiaumont is stormed.

Kimpolung (Southern Bukovina) is captured by the Russians.

The Great Eastern Railway Company's steamer Brussels (master, Captain Charles Fryatt) is captured by a German torpedo flotilla and taken to Zeebrugge (see July 27).

June 24 (Sat.)

Verdun:—Fleury is stormed by the Germans; this is the extreme point of their advance.

The Russians are in possession of almost all the Bukovina.

June 25 (Sun.)

Verdun:—A French success at Fleury.

Asiago is recaptured by the Italians (see May 31); the Austrians are pressed back along the entire Trentino Front.

June 26 (Mon.)

The trial of Sir Roger Casement for high treason begins (see June 29).

June 27 (Tues.)

Western Front:—Heavy bombardments and many trench raids by the British.

A Russian reverse near Kovel.

The Italians recapture Arsiero (see May 31) and Posina.

June 28 (Wed.)

It is announced in the House of Commons that the British and French Governments have abandoned the Declaration of London.

June 29 (Thur.)

Sir Roger Casement is sentenced to death (see April 21, Aug. 3).

June 30 (Fri.)

Verdun:—The French recapture Fort Thiaumont.

Heavy bombardments of the German lines along the Western Front.

The Russians capture Kolomea (Galicia).

July 1 (Sat.) (The Battle of the Boyne, 1690).

The Battle of the Somme begins (see Nov. 17): Montaubon, Mametz, and other villages are captured by the British; the French capture Dompierre, Becquincourt, and other villages.

The German offensive at Verdun is virtually at an end (see Feb. 21).

July 2 (Sun.)

The Somme Front:—The British capture Fricourt; the French capture Curlu and Frise.

The Battle of Baranovitchi (an important junction on the railway running south from Vilna) begins (see July 14): the Russians advance.

Persia:—Kermanshah is retaken by the Turks (see Feb. 27, 1916, and March 13, 1917).

July 3 (Mon.)

The Somme Front:—Fighting is in progress for Ovillers, Contalmaison, and La Boiselle; the British capture Serre; the French take a number of villages beyond the German second position.

July 4 (Tues.)

The Somme Front:—La Boiselle is captured by the British; the French advance towards Péronne.

July 5 (Wed.)

The Russians advance towards the Stokhod.

July 6 (Thur.)

Mr. Lloyd George is appointed British Secretary of State for War.

July 7 (Fri.)

The Somme Front:—The British line is advanced: Leipsig Redoubt is carried; Contalmaison is taken and lost.

East Africa:—The British occupy Tanga.

July 8 (Sat.)

The Russians cross the Stokhod.

July 9 (Sun.)

The Somme Front:—Heavy fighting on the British Front for Ovillers and in Trônes Wood; the French approach Péronne and capture Hardecourt.

The German cargo-carrying submarine Deutschland reaches Norfolk in Virginia (see Aug. 23).

July 10 (Mon.)

The Somme Front:—The British capture Contalmaison.

Mesopotamia:—A Turkish attack on the British position near Sanna-i-Yat.

July 11 (Tues.) Oudenarde, 1708.

A German submarine bombards Seaham harbour.

July 12 (Wed.)

The Somme Front:—The British complete the capture of Mametz Wood.

The Caucasus:—Mamakhatun is retaken by the Russians (see May 31).

East Africa:—The British capture Mwanza.

July 14 (Fri.)

British attacks on the Somme are renewed: Bazentin-le-Petit and the greater part of Longueval are captured (see July 29); the British complete the capture of Trônes Wood.

The Battle of Baranovitchi (see July 2) ends in the repulse of strong German attacks with slight change of position.

July 15 (Sat.)

The Somme Front:—The British abandon High Wood (entered the previous day), but advance towards Pozières; fierce fighting in Delville Wood.

The Russian 11th Army launches an offensive towards Brody (Galicia).

The Caucasus:—The Russians capture Baiburt (between Erzerum and Trebizond).

July 16 (Sun.)

The Somme Front:—The British complete the capture of Ovillers; fierce fighting on the French front near Péronne.

Umlej surrenders to the Sherif of Mecca.

July 18 (Tues.)

The Somme Front:—German counter-attacks in Delville Wood and Longueval are partially successful.

The Caucasus:—The Russians capture Kighi.

July 19 (Wed.)

The Somme Front:—A British attack on Guillemont fails, but an advance is made near Thiepval.

July 20 (Thur.)

The Somme Front:—A British success at High Wood; a French success near Hardecourt.

The Russians advance across the Styr: 12,000 prisoners are captured.

July 21 (Fri.)

The Somme Front:—The Germans attack the French near Chaulnes and are repulsed.

July 22 (Sat.)

The Russians occupy Berestetchko, south of the Lipa.

An action is fought between British and German light craft off the Belgian coast.

July 23 (Sun.)

The Somme Front:—The British attack towards Pozières and make progress.

Taif surrenders to the Grand Sherif of Mecca.

July 24 (Mon.)

East Africa:—The action of Malangali.

July 25 (Tues.)

The Somme Front:—The British complete the capture of Pozières.

The Russians advance on Brody (Galicia).

The Caucasus:—The Russians complete the conquest of Armenia by the capture of Erzingan.

July 27 (Thur.)

Captain Fryatt is executed in the Jardin de l'Aurore at Bruges by order of a German court-martial (see June 23).

The Somme Front:—The British complete the capture of Delville Wood.

July 28 (Fri.)

Brody (Galicia) is captured by the Russians, with 20,000 prisoners and many guns.

July 29 (Sat.)

The Somme Front:—The British complete the capture of Longueval.

A Zeppelin raid on Lincolnshire and Norfolk.

July 30 (Sun.)

The Somme Front:—A French success near Hardecourt.

Russian troops land at Salonika.

East Africa:—The British occupy Dodoma.

July 31 (Mon.)

The Somme Front:—The French advance near Maurepas.

A Zeppelin raid on the east and south-east of England.

Aug. 1 (Tues.)

The Russians attack before Kovel.

The Italians bombard the Austrian positions on the Isonzo.

Aug. 2 (Wed.)

The Caucasus:—Mush and Bitlis are recaptured by the Turks (see Feb. 19, Mar. 2, and Aug. 23 and 24).

The Italian dreadnought Leonardo da Vinci is sunk by an internal explosion in Taranto harbour.

A Zeppelin raid on the eastern counties of England.

Aug. 3 (Thur.)

Sir Roger Casement is hanged in Pentonville Prison (see June 29).

Fierce fighting on the Stokhod; the Russian advance is checked.

East Africa:—Ujiji is captured by the Belgians.

Aug. 4 (Fri.)

The Somme Front:—The British advance near Pozières.

The Russians attack on the Sereth.

The Turks attack on the Suez Canal (the Battle of Romani).

Aug. 5 (Sat.)

The Somme Front:—A further British advance near Pozières.

The Italians attack on the Isonzo (the Battle of Gorizia: see Aug. 8 and 14).

Egypt:—The Turks are routed in the Battle of Romani.

Aug. 6 (Sun.)

The Somme Front:—A German counter-attack at Pozières is repulsed.

A Russian success on the Sereth.

Aug. 7 (Mon.)

The Russians attack south of the Dniester: Tysmienica (near Stanislau) is captured and many prisoners are taken.

Aug. 8 (Tues.)

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians capture Gorizia and take 12,000 prisoners (see Oct. 28, 1917).

Aug. 9 (Wed.)

The French advance on a four-mile front north of the Somme.

A Zeppelin raid on England. A British air-raid on the Zeppelin sheds near Brussels.

Aug. 10 (Thur.)

The Somme Front:—The British and French advance at a number of points.

Stanislau is captured by the Russians, with a large sector of the remaining Austrian defences in Eastern Galicia; over 80,000 prisoners and many guns are taken.

Aug. 11 (Fri.)

Macedonia:—Italian troops land at Salonika; a French success near Doiran.

East Africa:—Mpwapwa is occupied by the British.

British airmen bombard the Zeppelin sheds near Brussels and Namur.

Aug. 12 (Sat.)

The Somme Front:—The French advance near Hardecourt.

The Italians advance on the Carso.

A German seaplane bombs Dover.

Aug. 13 (Sun.)

The Somme Front:—The British advance near Pozières; the French advance near Maurepas.

The British destroyer Lassoo is sunk by a mine off the Dutch coast.

Aug. 14 (Mon.)

The end of the Battle of Gorizia (see Aug. 5), which results in an important advance and the capture of Gorizia and many prisoners by the Italians.

Aug. 15 (Tues.)

The Russians occupy Jablonica (Carpathians).

Aug. 16 (Wed.)

The Somme Front:—The French and British reach the Guillemont-Maurepas road.

Aug. 17 (Thurs.)

The Bulgarians attack near Salonika.

Aug. 18 (Fri.) Gravelotte, 1870.

The Somme Front:—The British attack along a front of 11 miles between Thiepval and Guillemont and capture important positions; the French gain ground near Maurepas.

Macedonia:—The Bulgarians advance towards Kavalla.

Aug. 19 (Sat.)

The Somme Front:—The British capture important positions on the Thiepval Ridge.

H.M.S. Nottingham and H.M.S. Falmouth (light cruisers) are torpedoed in the North Sea. The British submarine E23 torpedoes a German battleship, the Westfalen, in the North Sea.

Aug. 20 (Sun.)

The Somme Front:—The Germans counterattack unsuccessfully near Thiepval.

Macedonia:—The Bulgarians capture Florina; a general offensive is launched by the Allies.

Aug. 22 (Tues.)

The Somme Front:—The British gain ground before Thiepval and near Pozières.

Verdun:—The French advance between Fleury and Thiaumont Wood.

The heights of the Jablonica Pass (Carpathians) are carried by the Russians.

Macedonia:—The Bulgarians are driven back by the British and Serbians on the Doiran Front.

East Africa:—Kilossa is captured by the British.

Aug. 23 (Wed.)

The Caucasus:—Bitlis is recaptured by the Russians (see Aug 2).

The mercantile submarine Deutschland arrives back in Germany (see July 9).

A Zeppelin raid on the eastern counties of England.

Aug. 24 (Thur.)

The Caucasus:—Mush is recaptured by the Russians (see Aug. 2, 1916, and May 3, 1917).

A Zeppelin raid on London and the eastern counties of England.

Aug. 25 (Fri.)

Macedonia:—The forts of Kavala are occupied by the Bulgarians.

A raid by British naval aeroplanes on the Zeppelin sheds near Namur.

H.M.S. Duke of Albany (armed boarding-steamer) is sunk by a submarine in the North Sea.

Aug. 26 (Sat.)

The Somme Front:—A strong attack by the Prussian Guard near Thiepval is repulsed by the British.

East Africa:—Mrogoro, the seat of German Government in the colony, is captured by the British.

Aug. 27 (Sun.)

Roumania declares war on Austria.

Aug. 28 (Mon.)

Germany declares war on Roumania.

Italy declares war on Germany.

The Roumanians invade Transylvania.

Sir Stanley Maude assumes command of the British forces in Mesopotamia (see Nov. 18, 1917).

British warships bombard the forts of Kavala.

Aug. 29 (Tues.)

Hindenburg succeeds Falkenhayn as Chief of the German General Staff.

Brasso (Kronstadt) is occupied by the Roumanians (see Oct. 7).

East Africa:—Neu Iringa is occupied by the British.

Aug. 30 (Wed.)

Turkey declares war on Roumania.

The Russians advance in the Carpathians.

Aug. 31 (Thur.)

The Somme Front:—A German attack at High Wood is repulsed by the British.

The Russians continue to advance in the Carpathians and take many prisoners.

Sept. 1 (Fri.)

An Allied naval demonstration at Athens.

Bulgaria declares war on Roumania.

Hermanstadt is occupied by the Roumanians.

Sept. 2 (Sat.)

The Russians capture the Ploska Height near the Jablonica Pass (Carpathians).

Sept. 3 (Sun.)

The Somme Front:—Guillemont and part of Ginchy are captured by the British; the French take Cléry.

German and Bulgarian forces enter the Dobrudja.

A Zeppelin raid on London and the Eastern Counties; a Zeppelin is brought down in flames at Cuffley by Lieut. W. L. Robinson.

Sept. 4 (Mon.)

The Somme Front:—The advance of the French and British continues.

East Africa:—Dar-es-Salaam surrenders to British naval forces.

Sept. 5 (Tues.)

The Somme Front:—Leuze Wood is captured by the British; south of the Somme the French make a notable advance.

A Russian victory near Halicz (4500 prisoners).

Sept. 6 (Wed.)

The French advance at Verdun and make further progress south of the Somme.

The Russians advance rapidly on Halicz.

The Bulgarians capture Tutrakan (Dobrudja).

Sept. 7 (Thur.)

The Roumanians occupy Orsova (in Hungarian territory on the Danube: see Nov. 23).

Sept. 9 (Sat.)

The Somme Front:—The British complete the capture of Ginchy.

Silistria, the Roumanian fortress on the Danube, is captured by the Bulgarians.

Sept. 10 (Sun.)

Macedonia:—The British advance across the Struma.

Sept. 11 (Mon.)

Resignation of M. Zaimis, the Greek Premier (see June 22).

Sept. 12 (Tues.)

The French advance north of the Somme and reach the Bapaume-Péronne road.

The 4th Greek Army Corps at Kavala surrenders to the Germans.

Sept. 13 (Wed.)

The Somme Front:—The French advance across the Bapaume-Péronne road.

Sept. 14 (Thur.)

The Somme Front:—The British storm 'the Wonderwork' near Thiepval.

A new Italian offensive is launched on the Isonzo front.

The Roumanians advance in Transylvania, but are forced to retire in the Dobrudja.

Sept. 15 (Fri.)

The Somme Front:—The British attack on a wide front; tanks are used for the first time; Martinpuich, Flers, and Courcelette are taken and the capture of High Wood is completed.

The Italians capture San Grado (on the Carso).

Macedonia:—The Allies capture high ground overlooking Florina.

Sept. 16 (Sat.)

A new Greek cabinet is formed under M. Kalogeropoulos.

The Russians and Roumanians are definitely in retreat in the Dobrudja.

Sept. 17 (Sun.)

The French attack south of the Somme and capture Vermandovillers and Berny.

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians capture important positions and a number of prisoners.

Sept. 18 (Mon.)

The Somme Front:—'The Quadrilateral' near Morval is stormed by the British. Deniécourt is captured by the French.

Macedonia:—The Allies capture Florina.

The Russo-Roumanian army in the Dobrudja is forced to retire from strong positions.

Sept. 20 (Wed.)

Transylvania:—The Austro-Germans gain the summit of the Vulcan Pass.

Sept. 21 (Thur.)

The Great Eastern Railway Company's steamer Colchester is captured by German small craft and taken to Zeebrugge.

Sept. 23 (Sat.)

A Zeppelin raid on England: two Zeppelins are brought down in Essex, the L 32 and L 33.

Sept. 25 (Mon.)

Greece:—M. Venizelos leaves the Piræus for Crete, where he proclaims a Provisional Government four days later.

The Somme Front:—Morval and Les Bœufs are captured by the British; Rancourt and Fregicourt are taken by the French.

A Zeppelin raid on England.

Sept. 26 (Tues.)

The Somme Front:—Gueudecourt is captured by the British and Combles by the British and French; the British attack Thiepval; the French advance east of Combles to St. Pierre Vaast Wood.

The Roumanians regain ground in the Vulcan Pass.

Sept. 27 (Wed.)

The Somme Front:—The British complete the capture of Thiepval.

Sept. 28 (Thur.)

The Somme Front:—The greater part of Schwaben Redoubt, on the Thiepval Plateau, is captured by the British.

Sept. 29 (Fri.)

A Greek Provisional Government is formed in Crete by M. Venizelos (see Sept. 25).

Oct. 1 (Sun.)

The Somme Front:—Eaucourt l'Abbaye is captured by the British.

The Bulgarians and Germans are checked in the Dobrudja.

A Zeppelin raid on London: a Zeppelin is brought down near Potter's Bar by 2nd Lieut. W. J. Tempest.

Oct. 3 (Tues.)

The Greek Cabinet resigns owing to the attitude of the Allies.

The Roumanians counter-attack successfully both in Transylvania and the Dobrudja and capture many prisoners.

Macedonia:—The Serbians reach Kenali in their advance on Monastir.

Oct. 4 (Wed.)

The Somme Front:—The French advance east of Morval.

Macedonia:—The British advance east of the Struma and capture a number of villages.

The Cunard liner Franconia and the French transport Gallia are sunk by submarines in the Mediterranean.

Oct. 5 (Thur.)

The Roumanians fall back in Transylvania.

Oct. 7 (Sat.)

The Somme Front:—The British capture Le Sars.

Transylvania:—Brasso (Kronstadt) is recaptured by the Austro-Germans (see Aug. 29).

The British advance in Macedonia.

The German submarine U53 reaches Newport, Rhode Island, after a voyage of seventeen days.

Oct. 8 (Sun.)

The Somme Front:—The French advance to the outskirts of Sailly-Saillisel.

The Germans advance in Transylvania.

Eight ships are torpedoed off the American coast by the U53.

Oct. 9 (Mon.)

A new Greek Cabinet is formed by Professor Lambros.

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians capture important positions and many prisoners.

Oct. 10 (Tues.)

An Allied ultimatum is presented to Greece demanding the surrender of the Greek fleet; the Greek Government protests but yields.

Oct. 11 (Wed.)

The Allies take possession of the Greek fleet.

The Isonzo Front:—The Italian advance continues.

Oct. 12 (Thur.)

A Franco-British raid by 40 aeroplanes on the mauser factories at Oberndorf.

Oct. 13 (Fri.)

The Germans enter Roumania.

Norway prohibits the use of her territorial waters by belligerent submarines.

Oct. 14 (Sat.)

The Somme Front:—The British advance at Schwaben Redoubt; the French advance near Bouchavesnes and Ablaincourt.

Oct. 16 (Mon.)

The Germans capture the Gyimes Pass leading into Northern Roumania.

Oct. 17 (Tues.)

The Allies land troops at Athens.

Oct. 18 (Wed.)

The Somme Front:—The French capture Sailly-Saillisel.

Oct. 19 (Thur.)

A new offensive is launched by the Germans and Bulgarians in the Dobrudja.

The German cruiser München is sunk by a British submarine in the North Sea.

Oct. 20 (Fri.)

The Russian dreadnought Imperatritsa Maria is sunk by an internal explosion.

Oct. 21 (Sat.)

Murder of the Austrian Premier, Count Sturgkh.

The Somme Front:—The British capture strong positions near Thiepval.

The Germans and Bulgarians advance in the Dobrudja and capture Tuzla.

Oct. 22 (Sun.)

The Germans and Bulgarians capture Constanza, the port of the Dobrudja. The Germans continue to advance through the Transylvanian passes.

A German seaplane which raids Sheerness is destroyed.

Oct. 23 (Mon.)

The British mine-sweeping sloop Genista is sunk by a submarine in the Atlantic (many lives lost).

Oct. 24 (Tues.)

The French attack at Verdun: the village and fort of Douaumont and other important positions are captured with 4500 prisoners (see Nov. 4).

The Dobrudja:—Chernavoda is captured by the Germans and Bulgarians.

Oct. 25 (Wed.)

A further French advance at Verdun.

Oct. 27 (Fri.)

German destroyers make a raid into the Straits of Dover: the empty British transport Queen and the British destroyer Flirt are sunk; the British destroyers Zulu and Nubian are severely damaged (subsequently these last two are made into one ship named the Zubian).

Oct. 28 (Sat.)

The Donaldson liner Marina is sunk by a submarine without warning off Queenstown.

Oct. 29 (Sun.)

The Somme Front:—The French capture trenches north of Sailly-Saillisel.

Captain Boelcke, the famous German airman, is shot down.

Oct. 30 (Mon.)

East Africa:—The Germans are defeated at Lupembe.

Oct. 31 (Tues.)

Macedonia:—The British advance in the Struma Valley.

Nov. 1 (Wed.)

The Somme Front:—The Allies advance near Les Bœufs and Sailly.

The Italians advance on the Isonzo Front in the sector between Gorizia and the sea: 4700 prisoners are captured.

An action between destroyers in the North Sea.

A raid on Pola by Italian torpedo-boats.

Nov. 2 (Thur.)

Verdun:—The French recapture Fort Vaux.

The Italians continue to advance on the Carso.

Russian warships bombard Constanza.

Nov. 3 (Fri.)

Verdun:—The French make further progress.

Isonzo Front:—The Italians make further progress on the Carso.

Nov. 4 (Sat.)

The recapture by the French of all the main defences of Verdun is completed by the occupation of the Damloup work (see Oct. 24).

Nov. 5 (Sun.)

Germany and Austria proclaim an 'independent State of Poland' with an 'hereditary Monarchy and Constitution.'

Nov. 6 (Mon.)

The Somme Front:—The French advance in St. Pierre Vaast Wood.

The Germans advance in Roumania.

The P. & O. liner Arabia is sunk by a submarine without warning in the Mediterranean.

Nov. 7 (Tues.)

Mr. Wilson is re-elected President of the United States.

The French advance south of the Somme.

The Russians and Roumanians advance in the Dobrudja.

Nov. 8 (Wed.)

A further German advance into Roumania.

Nov. 10 (Fri.)

The Somme Front:—The British make progress north of Thiepval.

The Serbians make progress towards Monastir: Chuke heights and the village of Polag are captured.

German destroyers shell the Russian coast near Reval.

British naval aeroplanes bombard the harbours and submarine shelters at Zeebrugge and Ostend.

Nov. 11 (Sat.)

The armed French transport Magellan is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean.

Nov. 12 (Sun.)

The Somme Front:—The French capture Saillisel.

A further German advance into Roumania.

The Serbians gain ground towards Monastir: 16 guns and 1000 prisoners are captured.

Nov. 13 (Mon.)

The British attack astride the Ancre and capture St. Pierre Divion, Beaumont Hamel, and 3300 prisoners.

The Germans continue to advance in Roumania.

Nov. 14 (Tues.)

The British capture Beaucourt (on the Ancre Front).

The Allies advance in Macedonia: the Bulgarians fall back on the Bystritza, five miles south of Monastir.

Nov. 15 (Wed.)

The Germans advance rapidly in Roumania.

British naval aeroplanes bombard the harbours and submarine shelters at Zeebrugge and Ostend.

Nov. 17 (Fri.)

The end of the Battle of the Somme (see July 1).

British airmen raid Zeebrugge and Ostend.

Nov. 18 (Sat.)

A further British advance astride the Ancre.

An important German victory in Roumania which breaks the Roumanian resistance.

Macedonian Front:—Monastir is recaptured by the Allies (see Dec. 5, 1915).

Nov. 21 (Tues.)

Death of the Austrian Emperor, Francis Joseph.

Roumania:—Craiova is captured by the Germans.

The British hospital ship Britannic is sunk by a mine or submarine in the Ægean Sea.

Nov. 23 (Thur.)

Orsova is recaptured by the Austro-Germans (see Sept. 7).

Nov. 24 (Fri.)

The Germans and Bulgarians under Mackensen cross the Danube at several points from the Dobrudja.

The British hospital ship Braemar Castle is torpedoed in the Mediterranean; the vessel is subsequently salved and repaired.

Nov. 25 (Sat.)

Roumania:—The armies of Falkenhayn and Mackensen effect a junction north of the Danube.

The French battleship Suffren is sunk by a submarine in the Atlantic.

Nov. 26 (Sun.)

The Allies demand of the Greek Government the surrender of ten mountain batteries.

The Roumanians are in full retreat.

A Serbian success north of Monastir: Hill 105 is captured.

A German naval raid on Lowestoft.

Nov. 27 (Mon.)

The Roumanian retreat continues: the line of the Aluta is abandoned; Giurgevo, on the Danube, is captured by the enemy.

A Zeppelin raid on England: two Zeppelins are destroyed.

Nov. 28 (Tues.)

A daylight raid on London by one German aeroplane.

A British air-raid on the harbour at Zeebrugge.

Nov. 29 (Wed.)

The appointments of Sir John Jellicoe to the office of First Sea Lord (see May 28, 1915, and Dec. 26, 1917) and of Sir David Beatty to the command of the Grand Fleet are announced in Parliament.

Dec. 1 (Fri.)

Mr. Lloyd George makes proposals to Mr. Asquith for the reform of war administration in Great Britain.

The Allies' demands are rejected by the Greek Government; an Allied force which is landed at the Piræus is attacked by Greek troops.

Dec. 3 (Sun.)

Roumania:—A German victory in the Arges Valley; the Roumanian armies are driven back all along the line. The Serbians advance and carry high ground north-east of Monastir.

A German submarine bombards Funchal (Madeira).

Dec. 4 (Mon.)

The Serbians continue to advance north-east of Monastir; they capture Stravina.

The British liner Caledonia is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean.

Dec. 5 (Tues.)

Resignation of Mr. Asquith, British Prime Minister.

Dec. 6 (Wed.)

Roumania:—Bucharest and Ploesti are captured by the Germans.

Greece:—The Royalist party in Athens regains control of the posts and telegraphs.

Dec. 7 (Thur.)

Mr. Lloyd George becomes British Prime Minister.

Roumania:—The German successes continue; many prisoners are captured.

Dec. 8 (Fri.)

A blockade of Greece is proclaimed by the Allies, as from this date, until adequate reparation shall be made for recent outrages.

Dec. 10 (Sun.)

The formation of the new British Cabinet is announced. Mr. Balfour becomes Foreign Secretary, Lord Derby Secretary for War, Sir E. Carson First Lord of the Admiralty, Mr. Chamberlain Secretary for India, Lord Devonport Food Controller; Minister of Munitions, Dr. Addison; Minister of Blockade, Lord R. Cecil (see May 26, 1915, and July 17, 1917).

Dec. 11 (Mon.)

An Allied Note is presented to Greece demanding the demobilisation of the Greek troops.

The Roumanian retreat continues: enemy forces are 20 miles east of Ploesti.

The Italian battleship Regina Margherita is sunk by a mine in the Adriatic.

A British air-raid on Zeebrugge.

Dec. 12 (Tues.)

The German Chancellor announces that Germany has made proposals for peace.

General Nivelle succeeds General Joffre in command of the armies in the field on the Western Front.

Vice-Admiral Gauchet succeeds Admiral du Fournet in command of the Allied Fleets in the Mediterranean.

Dec. 13 (Wed.)

Mesopotamia:—A new offensive against Kut-el-Amara is launched by the British forces under General Sir Stanley Maude.

Dec. 14 (Thur.)

The Allies present an ultimatum to Greece demanding the withdrawal of all Greek forces from Thessaly.

The Roumanians evacuate Buzeu.

The empty British transport Russia is sunk by a submarine.

Dec. 15 (Fri.)

The Greek Government accepts the ultimatum of the Allies.

A brilliant French advance at Verdun: important positions and 7500 prisoners are taken.

East Africa:—A British victory near Kibata.

Dec. 16 (Sat.)

The French advance at Verdun continues.

Dec. 18 (Mon.)

Germany's peace proposals are received by the British Foreign Office (see Dec. 12 and 30).

The end of the French offensive at Verdun (see Dec. 15), over 11,000 prisoners and 115 guns having been captured and much ground gained.

Roumania:—The Germans advancing on Braila, the grain port on the Danube, are checked by the Russians at Botogu.

Dec. 19 (Tues.)

Mr. Lloyd George announces the attitude of the British Government and of the Allies towards the German peace proposals: 'restitution, reparation, and a guarantee against repetition' are declared essential.

Dec. 20 (Wed.)

A Peace Note from President Wilson is communicated to the belligerents (see Dec. 25).

Dec. 21 (Thur.)

Sinai Peninsula:—The British occupy El Arish.

The British destroyer Negro is sunk by collision in the North Sea.

Dec. 23 (Sat.)

Sinai Peninsula:—The British capture the strong Turkish position of Magdhaba, near the Syrian border: 1300 prisoners and 7 guns are taken.

Dec. 25 (Mon.)

Germany replies to President Wilson's Peace Note, ignoring his request for the statement of terms but proposing that Peace Delegates should be summoned immediately.

Dec. 26 (Tues.)

General Joffre is created a Marshal of France.

The British take over more trench-line on the Western Front.

Roumania:—The Germans capture Rimnic-Sarat.

Dec. 27 (Wed.)

The French battleship Gaulois is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean.

Dec. 28 (Thur.)

Roumania:—Further German successes at Rimnic-Sarat: 10,000 prisoners are taken.

Dec. 29 (Fri.)

Rasputin, the notorious Russian monk, is assassinated.

Dec. 30 (Sat.)

The Allies reply to the German peace proposals, which they describe as empty and insincere, with a direct negative (see Dec. 12 and 18).

1917

Jan. 1 (Mon.)

Sir Douglas Haig is gazetted a Field Marshal.

East Africa:—The British storm a strong enemy position in the Mageta Valley and approach Kilambawe.

The British transport Ivernia is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean.

Jan. 2 (Tues.)

The Roumanian Cabinet is reconstituted with M. Bratiano as Premier.

Jan. 3 (Wed.)

A Russian success in the Southern Bukovina (600 prisoners).

Jan. 4 (Thur.)

East Africa:—The British occupy the German camp on the Tshogowali River.

Jan. 5 (Fri.)

Roumania:—The Austro-Germans capture Braila.

Mesopotamia:—The Second Battle of Kut-el-Amara begins (see Feb. 24).

East Africa:—The British reach Kilambawe, on the north bank of the Rufiji River.

Jan. 7 (Sun.)

The Russians make a successful advance near Riga.

Jan. 8 (Mon.)

The Allies present an ultimatum to Greece repeating former demands (see Jan. 16).

Roumania:—The Austro-Germans capture Focsani and 5500 prisoners; the Sereth line is thus turned. The Dobrudja is finally evacuated by the Russians and Roumanians.

Jan. 9 (Tues.)

The Allies reply to President Wilson's Note, stating their terms of peace.

Resignation of M. Trepoff, the Russian Premier; he is succeeded by M. Golitzine.

The Russians continue to advance in the Riga district.

Syria:—Australian mounted troops and the Imperial Camel Corps capture a strong enemy position at Rafa (the Battle of Rafa).

Jan. 11 (Thur.)

The Ancre Front:—The British capture the Beaumont Hamel spur.

Roumania:—Galatz is evacuated by the Russians: the conquest of Wallachia by the Germans is complete.

H.M.S. Cornwallis (battleship) is sunk by a submarine off Malta. H.M.S. Ben-my-Chree (aircraft carrier) is sunk in action off Asia Minor.

Jan. 12 (Fri.)

Germany and Austria-Hungary reply through Neutrals to the Allied Note which refused to consider the German peace proposals.

Jan. 16 (Tues.)

The Greek Government accepts in their entirety the demands of the Allies (see Jan. 8).

Jan. 17 (Wed.)

Roumania:—The enemy's advance is checked in the Moldavian Hills.

Jan. 19 (Fri.)

An explosion at a munitions factory at Silvertown, in the East End of London (69 killed).

Jan. 20 (Sat.)

Roumania:—Fundeni, on the Sereth, is captured by the Germans.

Jan. 23 (Tues.)

The Germans attack in the Riga district and compel the Russians to withdraw slightly.

Two actions are fought in the North Sea between British and German light forces: a German destroyer and the British destroyer Simoon are sunk.

The British armed merchant cruiser Laurentic is sunk by a mine off the Irish coast.

Jan. 24 (Wed.)

East Africa:—A small German force is isolated and compelled to surrender.

Jan. 25 (Thur.)

The Greek Government offers a formal apology to the Allies for the events of December 1.

Mesopotamia:—A British attack on Turkish trenches south-west of Kut is partially successful.

A German vessel shells Southwold at night: there are no casualties.

The French transport Amiral Magon is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean.

Jan. 26 (Fri.)

To regulate exchange, the British Government by Order in Council enforces the sale or loan of foreign securities to the Treasury.

Mesopotamia:—The British complete the capture of the Turkish position attacked on the previous day.

Jan. 27 (Sat.)

A Russian success in the Southern Bukovina: 1200 prisoners are captured.

Jan. 28 (Sun.)

Lieut.-General Smuts is succeeded by Major-General Hoskins as British Commander-in-Chief in East Africa (see Feb. 10, 1916, and May 16, 1917).

Jan. 30 (Tues.)

German attacks between Soissons and Rheims are repulsed.

Riga Front:—The Germans attack in strength: the Russians fall back slightly.

Jan. 31 (Wed.)

Germany announces 'unrestricted naval warfare' as from February 1.

The German intention to sink hospital ships is announced in a statement by the British Foreign Office.

Feb. 1 (Thur.)

The Government of the U.S.A. is officially informed that Germany 'must abandon the limitations she has hitherto imposed upon herself in the employment of her fighting weapons at sea.'

Mesopotamia:—The British capture the last line but one of the Turkish trenches before Kut east of the Hai-Tigris junction.

Feb. 2 (Fri.)

The Food Controller, Lord Devonport, appeals to the British nation to economise in food as the only way to avoid compulsory rationing.

A British naval air-raid on Bruges harbour.

Feb. 3 (Sat.)

The Government of the U.S.A. breaks off diplomatic relations with Germany; Count Bernstorff is handed his passports; Mr. Gerrard is recalled from Berlin; interned German cruisers and Hamburg-Amerika liners are seized.

The United States S.S. Housatonic is sunk in daylight off the Scillies by a German submarine.

Mesopotamia:—The British capture three lines of Turkish trenches west of the Hai-Tigris junction.

Feb. 4 (Sun.)

The Ancre Front:—The British carry important enemy positions.

President Wilson invites other Neutral Powers to follow the example of the U.S.A. in the interests of peace and civilisation (i.e. to break off diplomatic relations with Germany).

Feb. 5 (Mon.)

The Swiss Government declines to follow President Wilson's advice to break off relations with Germany.

Resignation of Said Kalim; a new Turkish Cabinet is formed with Talaat Bey as Grand Vizier.

Western Egypt:—The action of Siwa: the Senussi are defeated near the Siwa oasis.

Feb. 6 (Tues.)

The Ancre Front:—The British line is advanced near Grandcourt: 1000 yards of German trenches are taken.

Feb. 7 (Wed.)

The Ancre Front:—The British occupy Grandcourt.

The California, of the Anchor Line, is sunk by a German submarine with serious loss of life.

Feb. 8 (Thur.)

The British advance from Grandcourt on both banks of the Ancre.

The British destroyer Ghurka is sunk by a mine in the English Channel.

A British naval air-raid on Bruges harbour.

Feb. 9 (Fri.)

The Isonzo Front:—The Austrians attack and gain some ground east of Gorizia.

Feb. 10 (Sat.)

The Ancre Front:—The British capture a strong German position south of Serre Hill.

Mesopotamia:—The British storm Turkish trenches west of Kut and capture the 'Liquorice Factory.'

Feb. 11 (Sun.)

Germany attempts through the Swiss Government to reopen negotiations with the U.S.A.

The Italian line is re-established east of Gorizia.

Feb. 12 (Mon.)

President Wilson refuses to negotiate with Germany until her proclamation of unrestricted sea-warfare is withdrawn.

Roumanian Front:—The Germans attack the Russians near Jacobeny with partial success.

Feb. 13 (Tues.)

Roumanian Front:—The Russians regain ground near Jacobeny, but the Germans renew their attack, and make further progress.

Feb. 14 (Wed.)

Mesopotamia:—General Maude clears the Turks from the Dahra bend of the Tigris.

A British naval air-raid on Bruges harbour.

Feb. 15 (Thur.)

The Germans attack the French between Tahure and Massiges: they gain ground and capture 800 prisoners.

The Italian transport Minas is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean.

Feb. 16 (Fri.)

A British naval air-raid on Bruges harbour.

Feb. 17 (Sat.)

The British advance up the valley of the Ancre and capture important enemy positions.

Mesopotamia:—A British attack on the Sanna-i-Yat position fails.

The French transport Athos is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean.

Feb. 18 (Sun.)

Italian and French forces effect a junction in Southern Albania, thereby cutting the communication between Greece and the Central Powers.

Feb. 20 (Tues.)

Sinai Peninsula:—The British capture two Turkish advanced posts.

Feb. 22 (Thur.)

Mesopotamia:—General Maude again attacks the Sanna-i-Yat position: two lines of Turkish trenches are captured.

Seven Dutch ships are attacked by a German submarine outside Falmouth and six of them are sunk.

Feb. 23 (Fri.)

Minimum prices for wheat and oats are guaranteed for five years in Great Britain.

Mesopotamia:—General Maude's forces cross the Tigris at the Shamrun bend, threatening the Turkish line of retreat; the third and fourth Turkish lines are captured at Sanna-i-Yat.

Feb. 24 (Sat.)

On the Ancre the Germans begin to retire from their front-line positions.

Mesopotamia:—General Maude captures Kut-el-Amara; the Turks evacuate the Sanna-i-Yat position and retreat towards Baghdad; over 1700 prisoners are taken and much booty; this ends the Second Battle of Kut-el-Amara (see Jan. 5).

Feb. 25 (Sun.)

On the Ancre, the Germans withdraw before the British: Serre, Miraumont, Warlencourt, and Pys are captured.

Mesopotamia:—The British advance-guard, in pursuit of the Turks, is 15 miles west of Kut.

The Cunard liner Laconia is sunk without warning in the Atlantic.

German destroyers shell Margate and Broadstairs.

Feb. 26 (Mon.)

The Ancre Front:—The Germans retire before the British on an eleven-mile front: Le Barque is captured.

Feb. 27 (Tues.)

The British occupy Gommecourt (on the left of the advance).

Mesopotamia:—The Turkish retreat becomes a rout; the British pursue with cavalry, infantry, and gunboats; the British gunboat Firefly, lost on the fall of Kut, is recaptured.

Feb. 28 (Wed.) (Relief of Ladysmith, 1900).

The British capture Thilloy and advance east of Gommecourt.

The Germans gain ground in the Southern Bukovina near the Dorna Watra Pass.

The French destroyer Cassini is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean (many lives lost).

Mar. 1 (Thur.)

Mesopotamia:—The Turks continue their disorderly retreat on Baghdad.

The British destroyer Pheasant is sunk by a floating mine off the Orkneys.

Mar. 2 (Fri.)

The Somme and Ancre Fronts:—The British continue to advance against the yielding enemy.

Persia:—Hamadan is captured by the Russians.

Mar. 3 (Sat.)

The Germans retreat to a depth of five miles east of Gommecourt.

Mar. 4 (Sun.)

The British capture German trenches at Bouchavesnes.

Verdun:—The Germans attack and gain ground north of Caurières Wood.

Mar. 5 (Mon.)

The British approach the German main positions on the Bapaume Ridge.

Mesopotamia:—British cavalry reach Lajj, twenty-seven miles from Baghdad.

Persia:—The Turks retreating from Hamadan are attacked by the Russians in the Asadabad Pass.

Mar. 6 (Tues.)

Mesopotamia:—General Maude's rapid advance on Baghdad continues.

Persia:—The Russians capture the Asadabad Pass.

Mar. 7 (Wed.)

Mesopotamia:—The Turks stand on the line of the Dialah River.

The Turks continue to retreat before the Russians in Western Persia.

Mar. 8 (Thur.)

Death of Count Zeppelin.

A French advance in Champagne.

Roumania:—The Austro-Germans attack in the Trotus Valley (the centre of the Moldavian Front) and gain high ground.

Mar. 9 (Fri.)

Serious food riots are reported in Petrograd.

Verdun:—A French success near Caurières Wood.

Mesopotamia:—General Maude forces a crossing of the Dialah River.

Mar. 10 (Sat.) Neuve Chapelle, 1915.

The Ancre Front:—The British capture Irles.

Mesopotamia:—The Turkish resistance before Baghdad is broken; the British advance upon the city.

Mar. 11 (Sun.)

Mesopotamia:—The British capture Baghdad, and continue to pursue the Turks.

Mar. 12 (Mon.)

Revolution in Russia: the Duma, which demands representative Government, is prorogued; a number of regiments join the cause of the Duma; troops refuse to fire on the rioters; the Cabinet resigns; the Duma elects a Provisional Government.

Macedonia:—The British advance near Lake Doiran.

Mar. 13 (Tues.)

China breaks off diplomatic relations with Germany.

The Germans abandon the forward slopes of the Bapaume Ridge; the British capture Loupart Wood and Grévillers.

Mesopotamia:—The British are thirty miles beyond Baghdad.

Persia:—The Russians again capture Kermanshah (see July 2, 1916).

Mar. 14 (Wed.)

The constitution of the Russian Provisional Government is announced: Prince Lvoff is Premier.

Mar. 15 (Thur.)

The Russian Provisional Government demands the abdication of the Tsar. The Tsar abdicates for himself and the Tsarevitch, and names his brother, the Grand Duke Michael, as Regent.

The British destroyer Foyle is sunk by a mine in the Straits of Dover.

Mar. 16 (Fri.)

The British occupy St. Pierre Vaast Wood.

A Zeppelin raid on Kent: one Zeppelin, returning from the raid, is brought down in France.

Mar. 17 (Sat.)

Resignation of M. Briand, the French Premier, and his Cabinet (see Oct. 28, 1915).

The Germans retreat in France on a front of nearly a hundred miles; Bapaume, Chaulnes, and fourteen villages north and south of the Somme are occupied by the British; further south the French occupy Lassigny, Roye, and many villages.

Persia:—The Russians occupy Kerind.

H.M.S. Mignonette (sloop) is sunk by a mine off the south-west coast of Ireland.

Mar. 18 (Sun.)

The British advance on a front of forty-five miles and occupy Péronne and Nesle; the French advance on a front of thirty-seven miles and occupy Noyon and many villages.

The Caucasus:—Van is occupied by the Russians for the third time.

German destroyers shell Ramsgate. Two British destroyers are torpedoed (one of them, the Paragon, is sunk) in the Straits of Dover.

H.M.S. Alyssum (sloop) is sunk by a mine off the south-west coast of Ireland.

Mar. 19 (Mon.)

A new French Cabinet is formed with M. Ribot as Premier (see Sept. 7).

The German retreat continues; Ham and Chauny are occupied by the French.

Mesopotamia:—Feluja, on the Euphrates, is captured by the British.

The French battleship Danton is torpedoed and sunk in the Mediterranean (many lives lost).

Mar. 20 (Tues.)

The French and British advance on an eighty-mile front, the British towards Cambrai and St. Quentin, the French towards La Fère and Laon.

Mar. 21 (Wed.)

The British advance towards St. Quentin and occupy forty villages; the French capture Jussy and force the passage of the Crozat Canal.

The British hospital ship Asturias is sunk without warning by a German submarine (midnight, 20-21).

Mar. 22 (Thur.)

The French cross the Crozat Canal and the Ailette.

Mar. 23 (Fri.)

The French gain ground against fierce resistance between St. Quentin and La Fère; the Germans flood the region round La Fère.

The raider Möwe is reported to have returned to Germany for the second time (see March 4, 1916).

The British destroyer Laforey is sunk by a mine in the English Channel.

Mar. 24 (Sat.)

The new Russian Government is officially recognised by Great Britain, France, and the United States.

The British occupy Roisel, seven miles east of Péronne. The French reach the western bank of the Oise between St. Quentin and La Fère.

Mar. 25 (Sun.)

The French Government addresses to Neutrals a protest against the devastation and barbarities committed by the Germans in the evacuated territories.

German torpedo-boats bombard Dunkirk.

Mar. 26 (Mon.)

The British capture Lagnicourt (north-east of Bapaume), the French Coucy-le-Château and Folembray.

Macedonia:—The French advance west of Monastir: 2000 prisoners are taken.

The British destroyer Myrmidon is sunk by a mine in the English Channel.

Mar. 27 (Tues.)

The British occupy Longavines, Lièrmont, Villiers, Equancourt, and Saulcourt; the French capture the forest of Lower Coucy.

Palestine:—The British forces under Sir A. Murray defeat the Turks near Gaza (the First Battle of Gaza): 900 prisoners are captured, including the General of a Division and his Staff.

Mar. 28 (Wed.)

Verdun:—The French recapture Hill 304.

Mar. 29 (Thur.)

The British make progress south-east of Bapaume.

Mar. 30 (Fri.)

The British advance towards Cambrai and capture Sorel, Heudicourt, Soyécourt, and other places; the French advance north-east of Soissons.

The British hospital ship Gloucester Castle is torpedoed and sunk in mid-Channel, but without loss of life.

Mar. 31 (Sat.)

The British advance north-west of St. Quentin and capture Jeancourt, Hervilly, Herbecourt, and Vendelles.

Mesopotamia:—The British occupy Deli Abbas.

April 1 (Sun.)

The British capture Savy Wood and Savy, near St. Quentin, and Epéhy and Peizières, on the Bapaume Railway; the French advance towards Laon on the Margival-Vrégny Front.

The Russians occupy Khanikin (north-east of Baghdad).

April 2 (Mon.)

President Wilson asks Congress for a declaration that 'a state of war exists.'

The British take Holnon Wood (two miles from St. Quentin) and Francilly-Selency and Selency; they also advance on a ten-mile front between Bapaume and Arras and capture Croissilles and Doignies.

The American armed liner Aztec is torpedoed off the French coast.

April 3 (Tues.)

The British gain ground south-east of Arras; the French advance between St. Quentin and La Fère.

The Germans defeat the Russians on the Stokhod; they win a bridge-head and take many prisoners.

April 4 (Wed.)

The U.S.A. Senate resolves that a state of war with Germany exists by a majority of 82 votes to 6.

April 5 (Thur.)

The U.S.A. House of Representatives resolves that a state of war with Germany exists by a majority of 373 votes to 50. The sanction of Congress having thus been obtained, President Wilson subsequently declares the United States of America to be at war with Germany.

April 7 (Sat.)

Cuba declares war against Germany.

Two German destroyers are torpedoed off Zeebrugge, one of them being sunk.

The British torpedo gunboat Jason is sunk by a mine off the west coast of Scotland.

April 8 (Easter Sunday)

Austria breaks off diplomatic relations with the United States.

Mesopotamia:—The British capture Belad Station, and occupy the left bank of the Shatt-el-Adhaim.

April 9 (Mon.)

Brazil breaks off diplomatic relations with Germany.

The First Battle of Arras begins: the British advance on a fifteen-mile front between Lens and Arras, and capture the Vimy Ridge with 6000 prisoners (see May 16). On the Bapaume-Cambrai road they take Deniécourt and Havrincourt Wood, and, north of St. Quentin, Fresnoy-le-Petit, Pontru, and Le Vergnier.

April 10 (Tues.)

The British continue to advance: they reach the outskirts of Monchy-le-Preux, and capture Louveval.

The British hospital ship Salta is sunk by a mine in the English Channel.

April 11 (Wed.)

The British capture Monchy-le-Preux and La Bergère.

The French advance east and north-east of Soissons.

Mesopotamia:—General Maude defeats the Turks with heavy loss near Deltawa.

April 12 (Thur.)

The British advance on Lens; south of the Scarpe, Wancourt and Heninel are carried with the aid of tanks; Gouzeaucourt is captured.

April 13 (Fri.)

Bolivia breaks off diplomatic relations with Germany.

On the fifty-mile front between Loos and west of Cambrai the British take a number of important villages, including Vimy and Givenchy-en-Gohelle; south of the Scarpe they capture a portion of the Hindenburg line. The French attack and gain ground south of St. Quentin.

April 14 (Sat.)

The British capture Liévin (the western suburb of Lens), Cité St. Pierre (north-west of Lens), and Gricourt (near St. Quentin).

An Allied air-raid on Freiburg, as a reprisal for the sinking of hospital ships.

April 15 (Sun.)

German counter-attacks are repulsed by the British.

The British transports Cameronia (140 lives lost) and Arcadian (279 lives lost) are sunk by submarine in the Mediterranean.

April 16 (Mon.)

The Second Battle of the Aisne begins (see May 20): the French attack on the front Soissons to Rheims; the German first positions are carried from Soissons to Craonne, the German first and second positions from Craonne to Juvincourt; 17,000 prisoners and 130 guns are taken.

April 17 (Tues.)

The French capture Auberive and carry the heights south of Moronvilliers.

Palestine:—The British attack and carry Turkish first-line positions on a six-mile front (the Second Battle of Gaza).

Mesopotamia:—General Maude forces the passage of the Shatt-el-Adhaim below Samarra.

The British hospital ships Donegal and Lanfranc are sunk in the English Channel without warning; 75 persons (mostly wounded), including 15 wounded Germans, are drowned.

April 18 (Wed.)

The British capture Villers-Guislan, 12 miles south of Cambrai.

The French continue to advance on the Aisne: Chavonne, Chivy, and Ostell are captured.

Mesopotamia:—The Turkish 18th Army Corps is annihilated by General Maude at Istabulat, 12 miles south-east of Samarra.

April 19 (Thur.)

The French capture positions east and west of the Vrégny salient, and advance east of Rheims.

April 20 (Fri.)

The British capture Gonnelieu, 8 miles south-west of Cambrai.

The Aisne Front:—The French continue to advance on the Chemin-des-Dames.

Five German destroyers raid Dover; they are engaged by the British destroyers Broke and Swift, and two of them are sunk (the loss being subsequently admitted by the German Admiralty).

A German destroyer shells Calais.

April 21 (Sat.)

Mesopotamia:—The Turks evacuate Istabulat; the British attack their new positions between Istabulat and Samarra.

April 22 (Sun.)

The British gain ground east of Havrincourt Wood.

April 23 (Mon.)

The British advance north and south of the Scarpe on a front of 12,000 yards; Gavrelle, Guémappe, and the German positions for 2½ miles further south are captured.

German counter-attacks fail to drive the French from the heights south of Moronvilliers.

Mesopotamia:—Samarra station is occupied by the British.

Three British aeroplanes attack five German destroyers off the Belgian coast: a German destroyer is sunk.

April 24 (Tues.)

Mesopotamia:—General Maude attacks on the west bank of the Shatt-el-Adhaim; the Turks retreat to the Jebel Hamrin range.

April 25 (Wed.)

Macedonia:—The British advance on the Doiran Front.

A German flotilla bombards Dunkirk.

April 26 (Thur.)

A German counter-attack at Gavrelle is repulsed by the British; German counter-attacks on the Chemin-des-Dames are repulsed by the French.

April 27 (Fri.)

Guatemala breaks off diplomatic relations with Germany.

The British transport Ballarat, carrying Australian troops, is torpedoed and sunk, but all hands are saved.

Ramsgate is shelled by German destroyers (5 casualties).

April 28 (Sat.)

The United States Congress passes by large majorities a Bill for raising an American army by compulsory service.

The British advance east of the Vimy Ridge and astride the Scarpe: Arleux is captured.

The French offensive on the Aisne is checked.

April 29 (Sun.)

The British approach the Oppy line; they capture a mile of German trenches and 976 prisoners; fierce German counter-attacks are repulsed.

General Pétain is appointed Chief of the French Staff.

April 30 (Mon.)

Mesopotamia:—General Maude defeats the 13th Turkish Army Corps at the gorge of the Shatt-el-Adhaim (where the river cuts the Jebel Hamrin range).

H.M.S. Tulip (sloop—employed as Special Service ship) is sunk by a submarine in the Atlantic.

May 1 (Tues.)

The French advance east of Rheims.

May 2 (Wed.)

In Great Britain a Royal Proclamation is issued, exhorting the nation to food economy.

The British destroyer Derwent is sunk by a mine in the English Channel (52 lives lost).

May 3 (Thur.)

A new Greek Cabinet is formed: Premier, M. Zaimis (see Sept 11, 1916, and June 23, 1917).

The British attack on a sixteen-mile front east of Arras; the Canadians take Fresnoy, east of Vimy (see May 8); the Hindenburg 'switch' line is broken near Queant, and the Hindenburg line as far as Oppy is carried; counter-attacks by two divisions of the Prussian Guard are repulsed; 928 prisoners are captured.

The Caucasus:—Mush is abandoned by the Russians (see Aug. 24, 1916).

May 4 (Fri.)

The British gain ground near St. Quentin and Hargicourt; the French take Craonne, carry German trenches on a front of 2½ miles, and capture 1000 prisoners.

The British transport Transylvania is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean (over 400 lives lost).

May 5 (Sat.)

Russia:—The Council of Workmen's and Soldiers' Delegates passes a vote of confidence in the Provisional Government by a narrow majority.

The French advance on a front of 20 miles north of the Aisne and capture important ground towards Laon; they carry the Chemin-des-Dames and the crest of the Craonne Ridge; over 6000 prisoners are taken.

H.M.S. Lavender (sloop) is sunk by a submarine in the English Channel.

May 6 (Sun.)

German counter-attacks on the Aisne Front are repulsed, and the French capture 2000 more prisoners.

May 7 (Mon.)

A German attack on the British near Lens is repulsed.

A German aeroplane raid on north-east London in the early morning (1 killed).

May 8 (Tues.)

Liberia breaks off diplomatic relations with Germany.

The Germans attack in strength and recapture Fresnoy from the British (see May 3).

The French carry an enemy position beyond Chevreux (north-east of Craonne).

May 9 (Wed.)

A resolution is passed by the Russian Committee of Workmen's and Soldiers' Delegates in favour of an International Socialist Peace Conference to be held at Stockholm (see May 28).

Macedonia:—The British advance near Lake Doiran.

May 10 (Thur.)

A scouting force of light cruisers and destroyers under Commodore Tyrwhitt engage 11 enemy destroyers off Harwich, and chase them back to Zeebrugge.

May 12 (Sat.)

Arras Front:—The British capture important enemy positions and the greater part of Bullecourt (see May 17).

Zeebrugge is bombarded by British naval forces.

May 14 (Mon.)

Great Britain:—Sir Eric Geddes is appointed Controller at the Admiralty.

The British gain ground north of Gavrelle, and capture Rœux.

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians assume the offensive from Gorizia to Plava.

May 15 (Tues.)

General Pétain succeeds General Nivelle as Commander-in-Chief of the French army; he is succeeded by General Foch as Chief of Staff.

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians advance on the slopes of Monte Santo.

British naval forces destroy the Zeppelin L 22 in the North Sea.

An Austrian naval force sinks 14 British drifters in the Adriatic and escapes to harbour.

May 16 (Wed.)

It is announced that Major-General J. L. van Deventer is appointed to supreme command in East Africa, in succession to Major-General Hoskins (see Jan. 28).

Russia:—M. Miliukoff resigns: a Coalition Government is formed, with Prince Lvoff as Premier and M. Kerenski as War Minister.

The end of the First Battle of Arras (see April 9).

May 17 (Thur.)

Honduras breaks off diplomatic relations with Germany.

The British complete the capture of Bullecourt on the Siegfried line (see May 12).

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians win the western slopes of Monte Santo.

U.S.A. destroyers reach British waters.

May 18 (Fri.)

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians win the highest peak of Monte Vodice.

May 19 (Sat.)

Nicaragua breaks off diplomatic relations with Germany.

The Russian Coalition Government issues a declaration repudiating a separate peace.

May 20 (Sun.)

The French advance near Moronvilliers and take 1000 prisoners: the end of the Second Battle of the Aisne (see April 16).

May 22 (Tues.)

The Hungarian Premier, Count Tisza, resigns.

May 23 (Wed.)

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians advance on a wide front on the Southern Carso, and capture important positions and 9000 prisoners.

A Zeppelin raid on East Anglia.

May 24 (Thur.)

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians make further progress on the Southern Carso.

May 25 (Fri.)

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians continue to advance on the Southern Carso.

A raid by 17 German aeroplanes on Folkestone; three German aeroplanes are brought down on the return journey by British naval airmen from Dunkirk.

H.M.S. Hilary (armed merchant cruiser) is sunk by a submarine in the Atlantic.

May 26 (Sat.)

The British hospital ship Dover Castle is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean (6 lives lost).

May 27 (Whit Sunday)

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians reach the third Austrian line of defence; San Giovanni is captured.

May 28 (Mon.)

French Socialists resolve to attend the Stockholm Conference (see June 1).

May 29 (Tues.)

The French liner Yarra is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean.

May 31 (Thur.)

The Austrian Reichsrath is summoned for the first time during the war; the new Emperor Charles promises a more liberal constitution after the war.

June 1 (Fri.)

Great Britain:—Lord Devonport resigns the office of Food Controller (see June 15).

The French Premier, M. Ribot, announces the refusal of his Government to allow French Socialists to attend the Stockholm Conference (see May 9 and Aug. 13).

British naval aeroplanes bomb the German bases at Bruges, Ostend, and Zeebrugge.

June 2 (Sat.)

The British transport Cameronian is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean (63 lives lost).

June 3 (Sun.)

Great Allied air-raids on the German aerodromes at Zeebrugge, St. Denis Westrom, and Bruges.

A French air-raid on Trèves, as a reprisal for the bombardment of Bar-le-Duc.

June 4 (Mon.)

Resignation of General Alexeieff as Russian Commander-in-Chief; he is succeeded by General Brussiloff (see Aug. 1).

June 5 (Tues.)

An action at long range between British light cruisers and destroyers, under Commodore Tyrwhitt, and six German destroyers; one German destroyer, the S20, is sunk by gunfire.

Ostend is bombarded by British naval forces.

A daylight raid by 18 German aeroplanes on the south-eastern counties of England; two German aeroplanes are destroyed.

June 7 (Thur.)

A British offensive is launched between Ypres and Armentières (the Battle of Messines; see June 14): an attack in strength on the Messines-Wytschaete Ridge is preceded by the explosion of 19 mines; Messines, the Messines Ridge, the village of Oosttaverne, and the enemy's positions on a front of 9 miles are captured, with 7000 prisoners and many guns.

June 8 (Fri.)

The German proposal of an armistice on the Eastern Front is rejected by the Russian Government.

General Pershing, Commander-in-Chief of the United States Expeditionary Force, arrives in London.

German counter-attacks in the Messines area are repulsed.

June 10 (Sun.)

Publication of President Wilson's message to the Russian Government, defining the war aims of the U.S.A.

The Italian offensive on the Isonzo Front ends, but between the Brenta and the Adige the Italians attack and capture the Agnello Pass and the greater part of Monte Ortigara.

June 11 (Mon.)

Greece:—King Constantine abdicates, as demanded by the Allies, in favour of his second son Alexander.

The British gain ground on the right of their new front south-east of Ypres.

A British drifter destroys two German seaplanes in the Channel.

June 12 (Tues.)

A British naval force captures the Turkish fortress of Saliff, on the Arabian shore of the Red Sea.

June 13 (Wed.)

The Trentino Front:—An Austrian attack on Monte Ortigara is repulsed by the Italians.

A daylight raid by 15 German aeroplanes on London: 157 persons are killed, 432 injured; one enemy machine is destroyed.

June 14 (Thur.)

The end of the Battle of Messines (see June 7).

The British storm Infantry Hill, east of Monchy.

H.M.S. Avenger (armed merchant cruiser) is sunk by a submarine in the North Atlantic.

The Zeppelin L 43 is destroyed in the North Sea by British naval forces.

June 15 (Fri.)

Lord Rhondda is appointed Food Controller in Great Britain (see July 3, 1918).

The British capture further portions of the Hindenburg line near Bullecourt.

June 16 (Sat.)

Macedonia:—The British withdraw to the west of the Struma, owing to the approach of the malarial season.

Two Zeppelins raid the south-east of England; one is brought down in flames.

June 17 (Sun.)

The Italians make local progress on the Carso, and repulse Austrian attacks on the Asiago Plateau.

June 19 (Tues.)

Great Britain:—Enemy titles held by members of the Royal Family are abolished by the King.

June 20 (Wed.)

H.M.S. Salvia (sloop—employed as Special Service ship) is sunk by a submarine off the west coast of Ireland.

June 23 (Sat.)

Greece:—M. Zaimis, the Greek Premier, resigns (see May 3).

The P. & O. liner Mongolia is sunk by a mine off Bombay (23 lives lost).

June 24 (Sun.)

Dr. von Seidler forms a new Austrian Ministry (see Jan. 22, 1918).

The British gain ground south-west of Lens.

June 25 (Mon.)

British and German delegates meet at the Hague to discuss questions relating to prisoners of war.

June 26 (Tues.)

A new Greek Cabinet is formed with M. Venizelos as Premier.

The first fighting troops of the American army reach France (see Oct. 27).

The British gain ground south-west of Lens astride the Souchez River.

June 27 (Wed.)

Great Britain:—The report of the Commission on the Mesopotamian campaign is published.

The British transport Armadale is sunk by a submarine in the Atlantic (11 lives lost).

June 28 (Thur.)

The British enter Avion (south of Lens), and capture German trenches near Oppy.

June 29 (Fri.)

It is announced that General Allenby is appointed to succeed General Murray in command of the British forces in Egypt and Palestine.

June 30 (Sat.)

The British make further progress south-west and south of Lens.

East Africa:—German forces are driven from the border of Nyasaland to the Rovuma border.

The British destroyer Cheerful is sunk by a mine off the Shetland Islands.

July 1 (Sun.)

A great Russian offensive is launched in Eastern Galicia: important enemy positions and over 10,000 prisoners are captured.

July 2 (Mon.)

The Russians make further progress in Galicia.

July 3 (Tues.)

A German attack on the French lines between Jouy and Craonne is repulsed with heavy loss.

July 4 (Wed.)

The United States Navy Department announces that an attack on American transports by German submarines was beaten off by American destroyers, and that at least one of the enemy submarines was sunk.

A German aeroplane raid on Harwich (11 killed): two of the raiders are destroyed.

H.M.S. Aster (sloop) is sunk by a mine in the Mediterranean.

July 6 (Fri.)

Herr Erzberger's demand in the Reichstag for 'a peace without annexations or indemnities' provokes a political crisis in Germany.

A Conscription Bill is carried in the Canadian House of Commons.

The Russian advance in Galicia develops in the direction of Stanislau.

The British destroyer Itchen is sunk by a submarine in the North Sea (8 lives lost).

July 7 (Sat.)

A daylight raid on London by 22 German aeroplanes: 59 persons are killed and 193 injured; four of the raiders are destroyed on the return journey.

French air-raids on Essen and other German towns, as a reprisal for enemy raids on Nancy and Eperney.

July 8 (Sun.)

Austrian positions near Stanislau are captured by the Russians, with many prisoners; Russian cavalry pursue the retreating enemy.

July 9 (Mon.)

The Russians advance on Halicz.

H.M.S. Vanguard (battleship) is destroyed by an internal explosion with heavy loss of life, at Scapa Flow.

British naval airmen bomb the War Office at Constantinople and the Goeben and other ships in harbour.

July 10 (Tues.)

A fierce German attack on the British positions near the mouth of the Yser (the Battle of Nieuport): two British battalions are cut off and overwhelmed; the Germans win the right bank of the river at the mouth.

The Russians capture Halicz (see July 23).

July 11 (Wed.)

The Russians capture Kalusz (17 miles from Stanislau).

Mesopotamia:—The British defeat a Turkish force on the Euphrates.

July 12 (Thur.)

Great Britain:—Resignation of Mr. Austen Chamberlain, Secretary of State for India.

The Russians cross the Lomnica (Galicia).

July 13 (Fri.)

The Russians advance south-west of Kalusz (Galicia).

July 14 (Sat.)

The German Imperial Chancellor, von Bethmann-Hollweg, is dismissed by the Kaiser; Herr Michaelis is appointed to succeed him.

A fierce German attack on the Chemin-des-Dames meets with partial success; on the Moronvilliers Ridge (east of Rheims) the French capture an important enemy position.

Palestine:—The British raid the Turkish lines before Gaza.

July 16 (Mon.)

Disorders arise in Petrograd, and among Russian regiments, owing to Bolshevist intrigues.

The Russians fall back across the Lomnica (Galicia).

British light naval forces intercept and capture four German steamers off the Dutch coast.

July 17 (Tues.)

Great Britain:—The name of the Royal Family is altered to 'Windsor' by Royal Proclamation.

Ministerial changes:—Sir E. Carson enters the War Cabinet (see Jan. 21, 1918); Sir Eric Geddes becomes First Lord of the Admiralty; Mr. Churchill becomes Minister of Munitions; Mr. Montagu succeeds Mr. Austen Chamberlain as Secretary of State for India (see Dec. 10, 1916).

Mutineers from Kronstadt arrive in Petrograd.

Verdun:—The French win back on Hill 304 all ground lost since June 29 and capture 425 prisoners.

July 18 (Wed.)

The disorders in Petrograd are quelled by troops loyal to the Provisional Government.

July 19 (Thur.)

Herr Michaelis, the new German Chancellor, declares in the Reichstag for 'a victor's peace.'

The Germans attack in north-eastern Galicia and pierce the Russian Front; here and elsewhere mutinous Russian units refuse to fight.

East Africa:—The main German forces are defeated at Norongombe and driven in retreat to the Mbemkuru Valley.

July 20 (Fri.)

Galicia:—The Germans advance rapidly towards Tarnopol.

July 21 (Sat.)

Galicia:—The Russian retreat develops into a rout.

July 22 (Sun.)

Siam declares war on Germany and Austria.

Resignation of the Russian Premier, Prince Lvoff; he is succeeded by M. Kerenski.

The French repulse German attacks on the Chemin-des-Dames but lose ground at some points.

Loyal Russian units make a temporary stand near Krevo, east of Vilna.

A German aeroplane raid on Harwich and Felixstowe (11 killed).

July 23 (Mon.)

The Germans occupy Halicz and cross the Sereth south of Tarnopol; the Russians also retreat near Dvinsk and Smorgon; there are wholesale desertions in the Russian Army.

In Moldavia the Russians and Roumanians attack in the Susitza and Putna Valleys and capture guns and prisoners.

H.M.S. Otway (armed merchant cruiser) is sunk by a submarine in the North Atlantic.

July 24 (Tues.)

The Austro-Germans recapture Stanislau and Tarnopol.

July 25 (Wed.)

The Irish Convention meets in Dublin; Sir Horace Plunkett is appointed Chairman.

The Russian retreat in Galicia continues.

The Russians and Roumanians gain ground in Moldavia.

July 26 (Thur.)

The Austro-Germans are across the Sereth from Tarnopol to Czortkow; they occupy Kolomea, south of the Dniester.

H.M.S. Ariadne (mine layer) is sunk by a submarine in the English Channel (38 lives lost).

July 28 (Sat.)

The Austro-Germans enter south-western Russia on either side of the frontier town of Husiatyn.

The Roumanians still advance in Moldavia.

July 29 (Sun.)

An increasing artillery bombardment by the British in Flanders.

The Russian retreat continues.

July 30 (Mon.)

The French attack and gain ground south of La Royère, on the Aisne Front.

July 31 (Tues.)

Great Anglo-French attack in front of Ypres (the Third Battle of Ypres; see Nov. 6): St. Julien, Pilkem, Frezenberg, and other villages are captured by the British; the French force the passage of the Yser Canal and carry Steenstrasse and Bixschoote.

Aug. 1 (Wed.)

The Germans counter-attack and recapture St. Julien (see Aug. 3).

The Russian generals Brussiloff and Dmitrieff resign; General Korniloff is appointed Russian Commander-in-Chief.

Aug. 2 (Thur.)

The Germans carry British positions on Infantry Hill, east of Monchy.

Aug. 3 (Fri.)

The British recapture St. Julien (Ypres Front) and the positions lost on Infantry Hill (east of Monchy).

The Austro-Germans recapture Czernowitz.

Aug. 6 (Mon.)

Moldavia:—Roumanian positions are stormed north of Focsani by Mackensen's forces.

Aug. 7 (Tues.)

Moldavia:—Mackensen advances north of Focsani, and captures 3000 prisoners.

Aug. 8 (Wed.)

Moldavia:—Retirement of the Russians and Roumanians in the Trotus Valley.

Aug. 9 (Thur.)

Moldavia:—Mackensen continues to advance north of Focsani, and crosses the Susitza River on a wide front.

The British destroyer Recruit is sunk by a mine in the North Sea.

Aug. 10 (Fri.)

The British advance east of Ypres and enter Glencorse Wood; the French cross the Steenbeek.

A German air-raid on Nancy. A French air-raid on Frankfurt-on-Main.

Aug. 11 (Sat.)

Mackensen advances in Moldavia and captures many prisoners.

The British liner City of Athens is sunk by a mine near Cape Town.

Aug. 12 (Sun.)

A German aeroplane raid on Southend and Margate (32 killed).

Aug. 13 (Mon.)

The refusal of passports for the Stockholm Conference is announced by the British Government, as a measure agreed between the Allies (see May 9 and June 1).

H.M.S. Bergamot (sloop—employed as Special Service ship) is sunk by a submarine in the Atlantic.

Aug. 14 (Tues.)

China declares war on Germany and Austria.

Peace proposals by the Pope are delivered to the belligerent Governments.

Aug. 15 (Wed.)

The British attack from north of Loos to north of Lens: Hill 70 and several villages are captured and the defences of Cité St. Auguste penetrated in the northern sector; German positions are carried near Lens.

Aug. 16 (Thur.)

The British attack east and north of Ypres, and capture Langemarck.

The French advance near Craonne.

The Germans are checked by the Roumanians in Moldavia.

An action between British and German destroyers in the Bight of Heligoland.

Aug. 17 (Fri.)

The French gain ground east of Bixschoote.

Aug. 18 (Sat.)

German counter-attacks near Lens are repulsed with heavy loss.

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians bombard the Austrian positions from Monte Nero to the sea.

Aug. 19 (Sun.)

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians attack on a thirty-mile front, and capture the Austrian first line from Plava to the sea.

Aug. 20 (Mon.)

The French attack at Verdun on a front of 11 miles; they capture Avocourt, the Cumières Woods, and other strong positions, with 4000 prisoners.

The Germans advance on the Riga Front with little opposition.

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians make rapid progress.

Aug. 21 (Tues.)

The British gain ground north of Lens.

The French make further progress near Verdun.

A Zeppelin raid on the Yorkshire coast. A Zeppelin is brought down off Jutland by British light naval forces.

Aug. 22 (Wed.)

Lens is invested by the British on three sides.

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians continue to advance, 16,000 prisoners being claimed to date.

A German aeroplane raid on Ramsgate, Margate, and Dover; three raiders are brought down.

Aug. 23 (Thur.)

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians make further progress; they claim over 20,000 prisoners since the beginning of the offensive.

Aug. 24 (Fri.)

The British are driven back near the Ypres-Menin road.

Verdun Front:—The French capture Hill 304 and reach the southern bank of the Forges brook.

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians capture Monte Santo, north of Gorizia.

Aug. 28 (Tues.)

Moldavia:—A Russian division mutinies and leaves the field.

Aug. 31 (Fri.)

The French gain ground on the Chemin-des-Dames.

Sept. 1 (Sat.)

The Germans cross the Dvina at Uexküll, which constitutes a threat to the Riga-Petrograd Railway.

British light naval forces sink four German mine-sweepers off the coast of Jutland.

Sept. 2 (Sun.)

East Africa:—A German detachment surrenders at Kakera.

A German aeroplane raid on Dover.

A British naval air-raid on Adrianople.

Sept. 3 (Mon.)

Riga falls to the Germans, who occupy the town unopposed and advance in pursuit of the retreating and disorganised Russians.

A German aeroplane raid on the south-east of England.

H.M.S. Dundee (armed boarding-steamer) is sunk by a submarine in the entrance of the English Channel.

Sept. 4 (Tues.)

The Germans cross the Aa, 33 miles north-east of Riga.

The Isonzo Front:—The Italians capture enemy positions on Monte St. Gabriele.

A German submarine shells Scarborough (3 killed).

A night raid by German aeroplanes on London (11 killed).

Sept. 5 (Wed.)

The Russians lose the line of the Dvina as far as Friedrichstadt.

Sept. 7 (Fri.)

Resignation of M. Ribot, the French Premier (see March 19).

Sept. 8 (Sat.)

M. Kerenski dismisses General Korniloff from the post of Russian Commander-in-Chief; General Korniloff marches on Petrograd.

The United States Government discloses the 'sink without trace' incident in Germany's dealings in the Argentine through Sweden.

Verdun Front:—The French capture Chaume Wood.

Sept. 11 (Tues.)

Russia:—M. Kerenski assumes the position of Commander-in-Chief.

Sept. 12 (Wed.)

M. Painlevé succeeds M. Ribot as French Premier (see Nov. 13).

The Argentine Government hands Count Luxburg, the German agent in Buenos Ayres, his passports.

A British naval air-raid on Zeebrugge.

Sept. 13 (Thur.)

Russia:—General Korniloff's revolt fails.

The Allies advance in Southern Albania.

Sept. 14 (Fri.)

Russia:—General Korniloff surrenders to General Alexeieff and the Provisional Government.

Sept. 15 (Sat.)

Russia:—The Provisional Government proclaims a Republic; a new War Cabinet is appointed under M. Kerenski, who is virtually Dictator.

A British naval air-raid on enemy shipping between Ostend and Blankenberghe.

Sept. 16 (Sun.)

Allied air-raids on Stuttgart and Colmar.

Sept. 18 (Tues.)

The British destroyer Contest is sunk by a submarine in the English Channel.

Sept. 20 (Thur.)

The British attack on an eight-mile front east of Ypres: Inverness Copse, Glencorse Wood, and other important positions are captured, with 2000 prisoners.

Sept. 21 (Fri.)

East of Ypres the British repulse counter-attacks and make further progress.

The Russians evacuate the important bridge-head of Jacobstadt (on the Dvina, 70 miles south-east of Riga).

East Africa:—The British advancing from the direction of the port of Kilwa break up an enemy force and drive it in flight towards the Mbemkuru River.

Sept. 22 (Sat.)

The Germans occupy Jacobstadt (south-east of Riga).

Ostend is shelled by British ships of the Belgian coast patrol.

French air-raids on Stuttgart, Trèves, Coblenz, and Frankfurt.

Sept. 24 (Mon.)

A night raid on London by German aeroplanes (15 killed).

Sept. 25 (Tues.)

A British naval force bombards Ostend.

A night raid on London by German aeroplanes (7 killed); one raider is destroyed.

Sept. 26 (Wed.)

The British attack on a six-mile front east of Ypres; Polygon Wood and Zonnebeke are captured.

Sept. 27 (Thur.)

A raid by British naval airmen on the German aerodrome at St. Denis Westrem (near Ghent).

Sept. 28 (Fri.)

Mesopotamia:—The Turks are crushingly defeated by General Maude at Ramadieh on the Euphrates (the Battle of Ramadieh).

Sept. 29 (Sat.)

Mesopotamia:—The British victory at Ramadieh ends in the surrender of the Turkish force; over 3000 unwounded prisoners are captured.

A night raid on London by German aeroplanes (11 killed).

Sept. 30 (Sun.)

A night raid on London by German aeroplanes.

Oct. 1 (Mon.)

East of Ypres strong German counter-attacks are repulsed by the British.

East Africa:—An enemy detachment of 200 surrenders to the British north of the Central Railway.

A night raid on London by German aeroplanes (10 killed).

Oct. 2 (Tues.)

H.M.S. Drake (cruiser) is torpedoed off the north coast of Ireland; she makes harbour and sinks in shallow water (19 lives lost).

Oct. 4 (Thur.)

The British attack Passchendaele Ridge; positions of great importance and 4500 prisoners are captured.

Oct. 5 (Fri.)

An explosion occurs in a munitions factory at Chilwell, with heavy loss of life.

Oct. 6 (Sat.)

Peru and Uruguay break off diplomatic relations with Germany.

German counter-attacks at Passchendaele are repulsed with heavy loss.

Oct. 9 (Tues.)

Death of Hussein Kamel, Sultan of Egypt since 1914 (see Dec. 18, 1914).

The British and French attack between Passchendaele Ridge and Houthulst Forest; the villages of St. Jean, Mangelaere, Veldhoek, and Koekuit are taken, and the capture of Poelcappelle is completed.

East Africa:—A Belgian column occupies Mahenge.

A serious mutiny which occurred in the German Navy in August is announced in the German Reichstag.

H.M.S. Champagne (armed merchant-cruiser) is sunk by a submarine in the Atlantic (56 lives lost).

Oct. 11 (Thur.)

The British Government stops commercial cable communication with Holland until the transit of sand and scrap-iron by Dutch waterways from Germany into Belgium shall be discontinued.

Oct. 12 (Fri.)

The British again attack between Passchendaele and Houthulst Forest; their progress is checked by the mud.

The Germans attack the island of Oesel in the Gulf of Riga with naval and military forces; the greater part of the island is occupied.

Oct. 13 (Sat.)

The Germans capture Arensburg, the capital of Oesel Island.

Oct. 14 (Sun.)

The Gulf of Riga:—An indeterminate action between German and Russian naval forces is fought in the Sound between Oesel Island and Dago Island.

Oct. 16 (Tues.)

It is announced in Parliament that a British Air Ministry will be constituted.

The Germans complete the occupation of Oesel, taking many prisoners.

Oct. 17 (Wed.)

Gulf of Riga:—The Germans force Irben Strait; the Russians are compelled to sink and abandon their battleship Slava in Moon Sound.

Scandinavian merchantmen, convoyed by two British destroyers, are attacked by a German naval force in the North Sea: the two destroyers, the Mary Rose and the Strongbow, are sunk after a gallant fight (135 lives lost); most of the merchantmen are sunk, but three escape.

The U.S.A. transport Antilles is sunk by a submarine (67 lives lost).

Oct. 18 (Thur.)

The Gulf of Riga:—The Germans complete the capture of Moon Island.

Oct. 19 (Fri.)

The Gulf of Riga:—The Germans complete the capture of Dago Island.

A Zeppelin raid on the east and north-east of England and on London (27 killed); five of the raiders are brought down in France on their return journey.

H.M. armed merchant-cruiser Orama is sunk by a submarine in the Atlantic.

Oct. 20 (Sat.)

The Gulf of Riga:—The Germans capture Schilden Island.

Oct. 21 (Sun.)

The Gulf of Riga:—The Germans land at Verder, on the mainland of Esthonia (see Oct. 27).

British naval forces bombard Ostend.

Oct. 22 (Mon.)

The Germans counter-attack and gain ground in Houthulst Forest.

A German withdrawal south of Riga.

Oct. 23 (Tues.)

The French attack on the Aisne Front: the German defences are deeply penetrated; Malmaison Fort and other important positions are carried, 8000 prisoners being captured.

The Italian Isonzo and north-eastern fronts are heavily bombarded at many points by the Austro-Germans, the Austrians in this area having been strongly reinforced by Germans.

Oct. 24 (Wed.)

The Battle of Caporetto begins (see Nov. 18): the Italians are strongly attacked in the neighbourhood of Tolmino, on the Upper Isonzo, by Austro-German forces; the Italian Second Army gives way on a twenty-mile front.

Oct. 25 (Thur.)

Resignation of Signor Boselli and the Italian Cabinet.

A further French advance on the Aisne Front: many guns are captured.

The Italians retreat rapidly on the whole front between Plezzo and a point south of Auzza: the Austro-Germans capture Monte Matajur (south-west of Caporetto); they claim 30,000 prisoners in two days' fighting.

A British air-raid on the railways and factories at Saarbrücken.

Oct. 26 (Fri.)

The British advance on the Passchendaele Ridge; the French capture the village of Dvaeibank.

The Italians continue to retreat; their line is pierced on the Julian Front; 60,000 prisoners and 500 guns are claimed by the enemy to date.

Oct. 27 (Sat.)

The French and Belgians advance on either side of the Ypres-Dixmude road: Merckem is captured.

American troops are in action in France for the first time (see June 26).

The Gulf of Riga:—The Germans evacuate the mainland of Esthonia (see Oct. 21).

Italy:—The Germans capture Cividale and sweep into the Friulian plain; 80,000 prisoners are claimed to date.

An action between Allied and German destroyers off the Belgian coast.

Oct. 28 (Sun.)

A new Italian Cabinet is formed under Signor Orlando.

Fall of Gorizia: the Italians retreat towards the line of the Tagliamento; 100,000 prisoners and 700 guns are claimed by the enemy to date (see Aug. 8, 1916).

Oct. 29 (Mon.)

Italy:—The Austro-Germans occupy Udine.

Oct. 30 (Tues.)

Resignation of Herr Michaelis, the German Imperial Chancellor (see July 14).

The British advance on the Passchendaele Ridge and reach the outskirts of Passchendaele.

Oct. 31 (Wed.)

The remains of the Italian Second and Third Armies are withdrawn behind the Tagliamento River; 120,000 prisoners and over 1000 guns are claimed by the enemy to date.

Palestine:—The British, under General Allenby, resume the offensive on the Gaza Front; Beersheba is captured; 1800 prisoners and 15 guns are taken.

A night raid on London by German aeroplanes (8 killed).

Nov. 1 (Thur.)

Count Hertling succeeds Herr Michaelis as German Imperial Chancellor (see Oct 1, 1918).

Palestine:—General Allenby captures an important section of the defences of Gaza and advances north of Beersheba.

Nov. 2 (Fri.)

The Germans abandon the whole line of the Chemin-des-Dames; they retire from its northern slopes across the Ailette.

Italy:—The Austro-Germans reach the east bank of the Tagliamento.

A British naval force sinks a German auxiliary cruiser and ten German patrol craft in the Kattegat.

Nov. 3 (Sat.)

The French reach the Ailette on the whole front between Corbeny and the Oise-Aisne Canal.

French troops arrive in Italy.

Nov. 4 (Sun.)

British troops arrive in Italy.

The Austro-Germans force the passage of the Tagliamento north of Pinzano.

Nov. 5 (Mon.)

The Italians retreat from the Tagliamento towards the Piave.

Mesopotamia:—General Maude defeats the Turks before Tekrit (100 miles beyond Baghdad).

Nov. 6 (Tues.)

The British capture Passchendaele (this ends the Third Battle of Ypres: see July 31).

Palestine:—The British capture important positions eleven miles north of Beersheba.

Mesopotamia:—The British capture Tekrit.

Nov. 7 (Wed.)

A coup d'état in Petrograd by the Bolshevists under Lenin: Kerenski and the Provisional Government are overthrown; Lenin and Trotsky become masters of the situation.

The Italians reach the Livenza, the passage of which is forced by the Austro-Germans; 250,000 prisoners and 2300 guns are claimed by the enemy to date.

Palestine:—General Allenby captures Gaza.

Nov. 9 (Fri.)

It is announced that the Allied War Conference at Rapallo has decided to create a Supreme Council to ensure unity of command.

General Diaz succeeds General Cadorna as Italian Generalissimo.

The Austro-Germans advance in the Trentino and capture Asiago.

Palestine:—The Turks retreat on Hebron and Jerusalem with heavy loss in guns, prisoners, and other casualties.

Nov. 10 (Sat.)

The arrests of M. Kerenski and General Korniloff are ordered by the Petrograd Soviet; troops loyal to M. Kerenski occupy Tsarskoe Selo.

Italy:—The Austro-Germans attack on the Upper Piave and capture Belluno.

Nov. 11 (Sun.)

Italy:—Austro-German attacks in the Trentino (designed to turn the line of the Piave) are defeated.

The British monitor M15 and the destroyer Staunch are sunk by submarine off the coast of Palestine.

Nov. 12 (Mon.)

Mr. Lloyd George makes his 'Paris speech' declaring for an Allied War Council to ensure unity of command.

The Italians evacuate Fonzano and a part of the Val Sugano.

Nov. 13 (Tues.)

M. Kerenski's forces are defeated by the Bolshevists at Tsarskoe Selo; flight of M. Kerenski.

M. Painlevé's Government is defeated in the French Chamber (see Sept. 12).

Italy:—The Austro-Germans force the passage of the Lower Piave at Zenson.

Palestine:—General Allenby drives the Turks from strong positions north of Ascalon; the junction of the Beersheba-Damascus railway with the line from Jerusalem is occupied by the British.

Nov. 14 (Wed.)

Mr. Lloyd George announces to the House of Commons the terms of agreement between the Western Allies for a Supreme War Council.

Italy:—Austro-German attacks on a twenty-mile front, designed to turn the line of the Piave from the north, are repulsed.

Nov. 15 (Thur.)

The Italians retreat in the Val Sugano and the Austro-Germans occupy Cismon.

Palestine:—The British approach Jaffa (Joppa).

East Africa:—British troops occupy Chivata.

Nov. 16 (Fri.)

A new French Ministry is formed with M. Clemenceau as Premier and War Minister.

The Austro-Germans attack the line of the Piave on a twenty-mile front; they capture Monte Prasolan, the Italians retiring on Monte Grappa; the enemy cross the Lower Piave at two more points but are checked on the western bank.

Nov. 17 (Sat.)

Palestine:—The British enter Jaffa (Joppa).

A cruiser action in the Heligoland Bight: the German naval forces retire damaged to the protection of Heligoland.

Nov. 18 (Sun.)

Italy:—The end of the Battle of Caporetto (see Oct. 24).

Palestine:—The British approach Jerusalem.

Death of General Sir Stanley Maude in Mesopotamia (see Aug. 28, 1916).

H.M.S. Candytuft (sloop—employed as Special Service ship) is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean.

Nov. 19 (Mon.)

In the British House of Commons Mr. Lloyd George successfully defends his 'Paris speech' and the policy of a Supreme War Council.

Nov. 20 (Tues.)

A conference opens at Downing Street between the British War Cabinet and representatives of the U.S.A.

The British Third Army under Sir Julian Byng attacks and carries the Hindenburg line on a ten-mile front before Cambrai (the Battle of Cambrai; see Dec. 7): the advance through the German wire is led by tanks; Bonavis, La Vacquerie, Havrincourt, and other places are captured; the advance is continued to within five miles of Cambrai.

Nov. 21 (Wed.)

Russia:—The Lenin-Trotsky Government announces its intention to open negotiations for 'a democratic peace.' Ensign Krilenko is appointed Russian Commander-in-Chief.

The British continue to advance before Cambrai: Bourlon Wood is entered; Fontaine Notre Dame (2½ miles from Cambrai) is captured; Mœuvres is reached. The number of prisoners taken to date exceeds 8000.

Palestine:—General Allenby captures the Nebi Samwil Ridge (Mizpeh), five miles from Jerusalem.

Nov. 22 (Thur.)

Cambrai Front:—The Germans recapture Fontaine Notre Dame.

Nov. 23 (Fri.)

Cambrai Front:—The British capture Bourlon Wood.

Nov. 24 (Sat.)

Cambrai Front:—Fierce fighting in the northern outskirts of Bourlon Wood.

General Plumer is appointed to command the British forces in Italy.

Lieut.-General Marshall is appointed to command the British forces in Mesopotamia.

The German submarine U48 is destroyed by British drifters on the Goodwin Sands.

Nov. 25 (Sun.)

The French advance north of Verdun.

Nov. 27 (Tues.)

Cambrai Front:—The British gain ground towards Fontaine Notre Dame and the village of Bourlon.

East Africa:—Near Nevale 3500 German and native troops, under Colonel Tafel, surrender to the British.

Nov. 28 (Wed.)

The British Admiralty announces the formation of the Women's Royal Naval Service.

The Elder-Dempster liner Apapa is sunk by a submarine (79 lives lost).

Nov. 29 (Thur.)

Meetings of the Allied Conference open at Paris.

Count Hertling announces that Germany will treat with the Bolshevists.

Lord Lansdowne's letter advising a revision of war aims is published in the

Daily Telegraph

.

Nov. 30 (Fri.)

The Germans counter-attack in strength before Cambrai: they capture Lateau Wood and penetrate the British positions as far as La Vacquerie, Gonnelieu, and Gouzeaucourt; La Vacquerie is recovered by a British counter-attack; the Germans claim 4000 prisoners and 60 guns.

Dec. 1 (Sat.)

Cambrai Front:—The British recapture Gonnelieu.

East Africa:—The British drive the last enemy forces into Portuguese territory.

Dec. 2 (Sun.)

German and Bolshevist plenipotentiaries meet at Brest-Litovsk to negotiate an armistice.

Dec. 3 (Mon.)

The Russian General Staff surrenders to Bolshevist troops; General Dukhonin, the former Commander-in-Chief, is murdered.

Mesopotamia:—The Turks are driven out of the hills north of Deli Abbas; they retreat towards the Jebel Hamrin range.

Dec. 4 (Tues.)

Italy:—The Austro-Germans attack in the Asiago region and win Italian hill positions.

Dec. 5 (Wed.)

Cambrai Front:—The British evacuate Bourlon Wood.

Italy:—The Austro-Germans make progress on the Asiago Front: Monte Zomo and Monte Castelgomberto are carried.

Dec. 6 (Thur.)

An insurrection breaks out in Lisbon against the Government in power (see Dec. 11).

Roumania agrees to an armistice.

Cambrai Front:—Strong enemy attacks south of Bourlon Wood are repulsed by the British.

Italy:—The Austro-Germans capture Monte Sisemol.

Palestine:—The British occupy Hebron.

A German aeroplane raid on London in the early morning (7 killed); two raiders are destroyed.

Dec. 7 (Fri.)

The United States Government declares war on Austria.

The end of the Battle of Cambrai (see Nov. 20), the British gains having been largely abandoned.

Dec. 8 (Sat.)

Ecuador breaks off diplomatic relations with Germany.

The Russian peoples on the Don and in the Urals revolt against the Bolshevists.

Palestine:—The British advance isolates Jerusalem.

Dec. 9 (Sun.)

Palestine:—Fall of Jerusalem to General Allenby (see Dec. 11).

The Italians torpedo two Austrian battleships in the port of Trieste, sinking one of them (the Wien).

Dec. 10 (Mon.)

Panama declares war on Austria.

Dec. 11 (Tues.)

The Russian Constituent Assembly meets in Petrograd.

The Revolutionary party establishes itself in Lisbon, and forms a Government which declares its solidarity with the Allies (see Dec. 6).

Palestine:—General Allenby formally enters Jerusalem accompanied by the military attachés of France, Italy, and the United States.

A German submarine bombards Funchal, Madeira.

A British air-raid on Germany between Metz and the Rhine.

Dec. 12 (Wed.)

The Germans attack, and gain some ground near Bullecourt.

Palestine:—General Allenby advances north and north-west of Jerusalem.

A raid by German destroyers in the North Sea: they attack six merchantmen (five Neutral and one British) escorted by two British destroyers (the Partridge and the Pellew) and four armed trawlers; the merchantmen and the escort are all sunk with the exception of the destroyer Pellew, which is disabled.

Dec. 13 (Thur.)

The Russian Constituent Assembly is forcibly dispersed by the Bolshevists.

H.M.S. Stephen Furness (armed boarding-steamer) is sunk by a submarine in the Irish Sea.

Dec. 14 (Fri.)

The French cruiser Châteaurenault is sunk by a submarine (10 lives lost).

Dec. 15 (Sat.)

An armistice for one month from Dec. 17 is signed at Brest-Litovsk by representatives of the German Government and of the Russian Bolshevist Government.

General Guillaumet succeeds General Sarrail in command of the Allied forces at Salonika.

Dec. 16 (Sun.)

H.M.S. Arbutus (sloop—employed as Special Service ship) is sunk by a submarine off the Bristol Channel.

Dec. 18 (Tues.)

Italy:—The Austro-Germans attack from Col Caprile to Monte Pertica; they capture Monte Asolone with 2000 prisoners.

An evening raid by German aeroplanes on Essex, Kent, and London (10 killed); one raider is brought down.

Dec. 19 (Wed.)

The Ukraine Government demands recognition by the Bolshevist Government.

The Italians recapture part of Monte Asolone.

Dec. 21 (Fri.)

The Italians complete the recapture of Monte Asolone.

Palestine:—General Allenby advances northward.

Dec. 22 (Sat.)

Peace negotiations are opened at Brest-Litovsk between the German Government and the Russian Bolshevist Government; Herr von Kühlmann presides.

A German aeroplane raid on the Kentish coast; one machine is forced to land and its crew is captured.

Dec. 23 (Sun.)

Italy:—The Austro-Germans capture Val Bella and the Col del Rosso in the Frenzela Valley; they claim 9000 prisoners.

Three British destroyers, the Surprise, Tornado, and Torrent, are sunk by mines off the Dutch coast with considerable loss of life.

Dec. 24 (Mon.)

A British air-raid on Mannheim.

Dec. 26 (Wed.)

Vice-Admiral Sir Rosslyn Wemyss succeeds Admiral Sir John Jellicoe as First Sea Lord (see Nov. 29, 1916).

Dec. 27 (Thur.)

Palestine:—Turkish attacks north of Jerusalem are shattered and a British offensive is launched subsequently against the defeated enemy.

Dec. 28 (Fri.)

The Labour Memorandum on War Aims is adopted at a special British Labour Conference.

Palestine:—The British advance on a nine-mile front: they capture Ramah and Beitunia.

Dec. 29 (Sat.)

Palestine:—The British capture Bireh (on the Shechem road, nine miles north of Jerusalem).

Dec. 30 (Sun.)

The Germans attack Welsh Ridge on the Cambrai Front, and gain ground.

Palestine:—The British continue to advance; they capture Bethel and other villages.

The British destroyer Attack is sunk by a mine off Alexandria.

1918

Jan. 1 (Tues.)

Italy:—The Austrians are driven from Zenson, west of the Piave.

Jan. 2 (Wed.)

The German peace conditions are denounced by the Bolshevists as a policy of annexation.

Jan. 4 (Fri.)

The British hospital ship Rewa is sunk by a submarine in the Bristol Channel (three lives lost).

Jan. 5 (Sat.)

Mr. Lloyd George makes a declaration of 'War Aims' after consultation with Mr. Asquith, Lord Grey, and the leaders of the Labour Party.

Jan. 8 (Tues.)

President Wilson in an address to Congress lays down the 'fourteen points' on which, in his opinion, peace should be based.

Jan. 9 (Wed.)

H.M.S. Racoon (destroyer) is lost, with all hands, in a storm off the coast of Ireland.

Jan. 10 (Thur.)

In the peace negotiations at Brest-Litovsk the independence of the Ukraine Republic is accepted both by the Central Powers and the Bolshevists.

Jan. 12 (Sat.)

Verdun Front:—A German attack at Chaume Wood is repulsed.

British forces are disembarked at Port Amelia in Portuguese East Africa.

Two British destroyers are wrecked off the coast of Scotland (all lives lost except one).

Jan. 14 (Mon.)

The Italians attack and gain ground east of the Brenta in the Asolone district (491 prisoners).

Yarmouth is shelled by German destroyers (four killed).

Jan. 15 (Tues.)

The result of an inquiry into the operations before Cambrai (see Nov. 20-Dec. 7, 1917) is announced in the British House of Commons: the Higher Command is exonerated.

Jan. 18 (Fri.)

The Russian Constituent Assembly meets in Petrograd: it refuses to accept the dictation of the Bolshevist Government.

Palestine:—The British line is advanced north of Jerusalem.

Jan. 19 (Sat.)

The Russian Constituent Assembly is forcibly dissolved by the Bolshevists.

Jan. 20 (Sun.)

The Goeben and the Breslau make a sortie from the Dardanelles and are engaged by British naval forces: the Breslau is sunk by a mine; the Goeben also strikes a mine but escapes into the Straits, where she runs aground at Nagara Point; here she is attacked by British aeroplanes; H.M.S. Raglan (monitor) and a smaller British monitor (M28) are also sunk in the engagement.

The British armed boarding-steamer Louvain is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean (224 lives lost).

Two German destroyers are sunk by mines in the North Sea.

Jan. 21 (Mon.)

Sir Edward Carson resigns from the British War Cabinet (see July 17, 1917).

Jan. 22 (Tues.)

Dr. von Seidler, the Austrian Premier, tenders his resignation, which is refused (see June 24, 1917, and July 23, 1918).

Jan. 23 (Wed.)

Two meatless days a week are enforced in Great Britain by a Public Meals Order.

Jan. 26 (Sat.)

It is announced that the British have taken over an additional sector of the front in France, and that their line now extends southward beyond St. Quentin.

Jan. 27 (Sun.)

The Goeben is refloated and towed to Constantinople.

Jan. 28 (Mon.)

The Italians attack between Asiago and the Brenta Valley: they capture the Col del Rosso and 1500 prisoners.

A night raid by German aeroplanes on London (58 killed); one raider is destroyed over Essex.

The British submarine E14 is sunk by the Turks off Kum Kale (Dardanelles).

Jan. 29 (Tues.)

The Italians capture Monte di Val Bella.

German aeroplanes reach the outskirts of London.

Jan. 30 (Wed.)

An air-raid on Paris (49 killed); one raider is destroyed.

Jan. 31 (Thurs.)

Austrian counter-attacks on Monte di Val Bella are repulsed by the Italians.

Feb. 4 (Mon.)

The trial of Bolo Pasha begins in Paris (see Feb. 14).

Feb. 5 (Tues.)

The Anchor liner Tuscania, transporting American troops, is sunk by a submarine off Ireland (166 lives lost).

Feb. 8 (Fri.)

The Germans attack French positions north of the Chemin-des-Dames and are repulsed.

Feb. 9 (Sat.)

Peace is concluded between the Central Powers and the Ukraine Republic.

Feb. 10 (Sun.)

It is announced by Trotsky that Russia is out of the war ('while desisting from signing a formal treaty of peace the state of war with the enemy Powers is ended') (see March 2).

Feb. 11 (Mon.)

A French air-raid on Metz.

Feb. 13 (Ash Wednesday).

The French, assisted by American troops, capture the German salient between Tahure and the Butte du Mesnil.

Russia:—General Alexeieff's forces are defeated by the Bolshevists. General Kaledin commits suicide.

Feb. 14 (Thur.)

Bolo Pasha is condemned to death for high treason (see Feb. 4 and April 17).

Palestine:—The British advance east of the Jerusalem-Shechem road.

Feb. 15 (Fri.)

German destroyers raid the Straits of Dover and sink a British armed trawler and seven drifters. Dover is shelled by a German submarine (one killed, a child).

Feb. 16 (Sat.)

It is announced that Sir William Robertson has resigned his post as British Chief of Staff and that he is succeeded by Sir Henry Wilson.

A night raid by German aeroplanes on London (11 killed).

Feb. 17 (Sun.)

A night raid by German aeroplanes on London (19 killed).

Feb. 18 (Mon.)

The armistice between Germany and Russia terminates; the Germans cross the Dvina and occupy Dvinsk and Lutsk; further south, at the invitation of the Ukraine, they advance towards Kovel.

Armenia is evacuated by the Russians.

Feb. 19 (Tues.)

The German armies continue to advance rapidly into Russia; they claim to have captured 2500 prisoners and several hundred guns.

Palestine:—General Allenby attacks north-east of Jerusalem and advances on a front of 15 miles to a depth of 2 miles towards Jericho.

Feb. 20 (Wed.)

The German advance into Russia, towards Reval, Petrograd, Moscow, and Kieff, continues.

Palestine:—General Allenby advances to within 4 miles of Jericho.

Mesopotamia:—General Marshall occupies Khan Abu Rayat on the Euphrates, 14 miles north of Ramadie.

Feb. 21 (Thur.)

The German Government outlines the peace terms which it will grant to Russia.

Palestine:—General Allenby captures Jericho.

Feb. 22 (Fri.)

Palestine:—The Turks retreat north of Jericho.

Feb. 24 (Sun.)

Germany's peace terms are accepted by the Russian Central Executive Committee of Soviets.

Caucasus:—Trebizond is reoccupied by the Turks (see April 18, 1916).

The German auxiliary cruiser Wolf returns successfully to port after raiding commerce for fifteen months consecutively.

Feb. 25 (Mon.)

The first compulsory rationing comes into force in Great Britain (in London and the Home Counties).

Russia:—The Germans occupy Reval and Pskoff.

Venice is heavily bombarded by Austrian airmen.

Feb. 26 (Tues.)

Palestine:—The British occupy Rujm-el-Bahr (on the north shore of the Dead Sea) and the Mandesi ford of the Jordan.

The British hospital ship Glenart Castle is sunk by a submarine in the Bristol Channel (162 lives lost).

Mar. 1 (Fri.)

H.M.S. Calgarian (armed merchant cruiser) is sunk by a submarine off the coast of Ireland (67 lives lost).

Mar. 2 (Sat.)

Peace is signed at Brest-Litovsk between the Central Powers and Russia.

Roumania announces her submission to an ultimatum from the Central Powers requiring her to enter into peace negotiations.

Mar. 3 (Sun.)

Kieff is occupied by the Germans; the German military operations in Russia now cease.

Palestine:—General Allenby advances on a front of 12 miles to a depth of 3000 yards between Jerusalem and Shechem.

Mar. 5 (Tues.)

The preliminaries of a treaty of peace are signed between the Central Powers and Roumania.

German forces occupy the Aland Islands at the request of the Government of Finland.

Mar. 6 (Wed.)

Death of Mr. John Redmond, the leader of the Irish National Party.

Mar. 7 (Thur.)

A treaty of peace is signed between Germany and Finland.

Palestine:—General Allenby advances on a front of 18 miles to a depth of 3 miles across the Jerusalem-Shechem road.

A raid on a moonless night by German aeroplanes on London (20 killed); one raider is destroyed.

Mar. 8 (Fri.)

A German aeroplane raid on Paris (13 killed): one raider is destroyed.

Mar. 9 (Sat.)

Palestine:—A further advance by the British, who force the passage of the River Auja.

Mesopotamia:—Hit, on the Euphrates, is occupied by the British under General Marshall.

Mar. 10 (Sun.)

The British hospital ship Guildford Castle is torpedoed in the Bristol Channel but succeeds in making port.

Mar. 11 (Mon.)

The Germans raid the Western Front at a number of points.

Palestine:—A further advance by the British astride the Jerusalem-Shechem road.

Caucasus:—Erzerum is reoccupied by the Turks (see Feb. 16, 1916.)

Paris is attacked by 60 German aeroplanes; four of the raiders are destroyed.

Mar. 12 (Tues.)

German forces land at Abo in Finland.

Palestine:—The British advance near the coast.

A Zeppelin raid on the Yorkshire coast (one killed).

Mar. 13 (Wed.)

The Germans occupy Odessa.

A Zeppelin raid on Hartlepool (eight killed).

Mar. 14 (Thur.)

Palestine:—The British gain important positions commanding the Nablus road.

Mar. 15 (Fri.)

Prince Lichnowsky's memoir, dealing with the causes that led to the war, is published in Sweden.

Mar. 17 (Sun.)

Nikolaief, the Russian naval yard on the Black Sea, is occupied by the Germans.

Mar. 18 (Mon.)

The Germans bombard the Belgian Front and make a number of attacks there which are repulsed.

A British air-raid on Mannheim.

Mar. 19 (Tues.)

Great Britain:—Lord Pirrie is appointed Controller-General of Merchant Shipbuilding.

Mar. 21 (Thur.)

The great German offensive on the Western Front begins (the second Battle of the Somme; see April 5): the Germans attack, with immense weight of troops, the British Third and Fifth Armies on a fifty-mile front between the Scarpe and the Oise; they carry the British front-line positions over large sectors and penetrate more deeply at certain points.

Eighteen German destroyers raid Dunkirk. They are met by an Anglo-French flotilla consisting of two British destroyers (Botha and Morris) and three French destroyers, under the command of H.M.S. Botha. Three German destroyers are sunk and one disabled.

British monitors bombard Ostend.

Mar. 22 (Fri.)

The German offensive continues: the British line is broken west of St. Quentin but holds further north; the British fall back towards the line of the Somme; the Germans claim 16,000 prisoners and 200 guns.

Palestine:—General Allenby crosses the Jordan and advances towards the Hedjaz railway.

The British mine-sweeping sloop Gaillardia is sunk by a mine in the North Sea (68 lives lost).

Mar. 23 (Sat.)

The peace treaties concluded by the German Government are adopted by the German Reichstag.

The British fall back on new positions west and south-west of St. Quentin, 15 miles in rear of those held at the beginning of the offensive; the French enter the battle at Noyon, on the right of the British; the Germans claim 25,000 prisoners and 400 guns to date.

Paris is shelled by a long-range gun from a distance of 74 miles.

British air-raids on Bruges docks and Metz.

Mar. 24 (Sun.)

The Germans recapture Bapaume, Péronne, Nesle, Ham, and Chauny; they claim 30,000 prisoners and 600 guns to date.

A British air-raid on Cologne.

Mar. 25 (Mon.)

The Germans make further progress between Arras and Péronne and at other points further south; near Maricourt they reach their line of July 1916; the French evacuate Noyon.

Palestine:—General Allenby captures Es Salt and advances towards Amman on the Hedjaz railway (see April 1 and 30).

Mar. 26 (Tues.)

General Foch assumes supreme control of the Allied Armies in France.

The British line runs from in front of Arras south-west to Albert and thence south, behind the defences of 1916, to Bray; south of the Somme the Germans capture Chaulnes and Roye; the Germans claim to have taken to date 963 guns and to have destroyed 100 tanks.

Palestine:—British mounted troops approach Amman on the Hedjaz railway (see April 1).

Mesopotamia:—General Marshall defeats the Turks at Khan Baghdadie and takes 3000 prisoners.

Mar. 27 (Wed.)

The northern sectors of the British battle-line hold; the Germans capture Albert and in the valley of the Ancre are within 12 miles of Amiens; further south they capture Montdidier (between Amiens and Compiègne); German attacks are repulsed near Lassigny and Noyon.

Palestine:—The British destroy portions of the Hedjaz railway north and south of Amman.

The British destroyer Kale is sunk by a mine in the North Sea.

Mar. 28 (Thur.)

Strong German attacks on the British positions east and south-east of Arras are repulsed with heavy loss, but further south the Germans reach Hamel in their advance on Amiens.

Palestine:—The British attack Amman, but make little progress.

British destroyers capture and sink three German armed trawlers in the Heligoland Bight. H.M.S. Tithonus (armed boarding-steamer) is sunk by a submarine in the North Sea.

Mar. 29 (Good Friday)

The Germans make further progress towards Amiens between the Ancre and the Avre.

During the bombardment of Paris by the German long-range gun, a church is hit while a Good Friday service is in progress and many casualties are caused.

Mar. 30 (Sat.)

German attacks on the British Front north of the Somme (in the Boiry—Boyelles district) are repulsed with heavy loss. The French recapture Moreuil (south-east of Amiens).

Palestine:—The British attack on Amman is renewed with slight success.

April 1 (Mon.)

Palestine:—The British retire from before Amman and evacuate Es Salt (see March 25).

April 2 (Tues.)

The British recapture Ayette (between Arras and Albert).

April 4 (Thur.)

The Germans attack in great strength towards Amiens; they advance considerably on either side of Moreuil (south-east of Amiens); the French lose Morisel and Mailly-Raineval. The Germans claim to have taken 90,000 prisoners and 1300 guns since March 21.

April 5 (Fri.)

The British and French defences hold against strong German attacks; the Germans make little progress and suffer heavy losses; the French regain ground between Moreuil and Montdidier; this ends the second Battle of the Somme (see March 21).

British and Japanese marines under the command of Admiral Kato are landed at Vladivostok.

April 6 (Sat.)

The British recapture Aveluy Wood, north of Albert; the French yield ground near Chauny.

The Caucasus:—The Turks reoccupy Ardahan (see Jan. 3, 1915).

April 7 (Sun.)

Syria:—The Arabs capture Kerak, the Turkish headquarters east of the Dead Sea.

April 8 (Mon.)

The Germans bombard the whole British Front in the battle area and northwards to Armentières.

The French retire in the Coucy district, south of the Oise.

April 9 (Tues.)

The Germans attack in great strength on a ten-mile front between La Bassée and Armentières; they penetrate the centre of this sector, which is held by the Portuguese, and widen the gap made (the Battle of the Lys: see April 29).

April 10 (Wed.)

The new German offensive extends northwards; the British are forced back on the Messines Ridge and in front of Ploegsteert Wood; south of Armentières the Germans cross the Lys.

Palestine:—The Turks attack in the coastal sector; they are repulsed and the British line is advanced at some points.

April 11 (Thur.)

There is fierce fighting on the Messines Ridge, where the British 9th Division repulses strong enemy attacks; below Armentières the Germans rapidly deepen and widen the salient they have created; they capture Armentières and Merville, and force back the British to a line behind Ploegsteert, Steenwerck, and Estaires; German attacks on the lines covering Béthune are repulsed with heavy loss; the Germans claim 20,000 prisoners and over 200 guns in this battle to date.

April 12 (Fri.)

The Germans strike northwards from the salient; they reach Bailleul and capture Neuve Eglise; the British withdraw from the Messines Ridge; further south the Germans cross the Lawe and threaten St. Venant.

A Zeppelin raid on the east coast of England and the Midlands (five killed).

April 13 (Sat.)

The British repulse German attacks from Météren to Wulverghem and recapture Neuve Eglise.

The Caucasus:—The Turks capture Batoum and 3000 prisoners.

April 14 (Sun.)

The British withdraw from Neuve Eglise.

April 15 (Mon.)

The resignation is announced of Count Czernin, the Austrian Foreign Minister, following on the publication by M. Clemenceau of a letter by Emperor Karl, dealing with the claims of France to Alsace-Lorraine.

The Germans capture Bailleul and Wulverghem.

A British naval force sinks ten German trawlers in the Kattegat; their crews are saved.

April 16 (Tues.)

The British withdraw from the Passchendaele Ridge.

April 17 (Wed.)

Bolo Pasha is shot at Vincennes (see Feb. 14).

The Belgians repulse German attacks near Bixschoote and capture 700 prisoners.

The British withdraw from Wytschaete and lose Météren; a German attack on Kemmel Hill is completely repulsed by the British; French reinforcements enter the battle along the ridge south-west of Ypres.

April 18 (Thur.)

Lord Milner succeeds Lord Derby as British Secretary of State for War.

The Germans attack in strength from Givenchy to the Lys and are repulsed with heavy loss.

The French attack in the Avre Valley, south-east of Amiens, and advance to the outskirts of Castel.

April 19 (Fri.)

The British gain ground at Givenchy and Festubert.

April 20 (Sat.)

British and German light naval forces are engaged in the Bight of Heligoland.

April 23 (Tues.) St. George's Day.

Guatemala declares war on Germany.

The Germans attack on the Amiens Front, at the junction of the French and British armies; they capture the village of Villers-Bréttoneux from the British but elsewhere are repulsed.

British naval forces (Vice-Admiral Sir Roger Keyes in chief command) raid Zeebrugge and Ostend in the early morning with a view to blocking the entrances to the harbours. Storming parties land on the Mole at Zeebrugge, while three obsolete cruisers, the Intrepid, Thetis, and Iphigenia, filled with concrete enter the harbour; these are sunk at the entrance of the Bruges Canal. Two other block ships, the Brilliant and Sirius, are sunk near the entrance to the harbour at Ostend. In the action at Zeebrugge the British destroyer North Star is sunk.

The famous German airman, Baron von Richthoven, is shot down in the Somme Valley.

April 24 (Wed.)

On the Amiens Front the British recapture Villers-Bréttoneux.

Syria:—Arab forces seize 53 miles of the Hedjaz railway south of Maan.

April 25 (Thur.)

The Germans capture Kemmel Hill.

H.M.S. Cowslip (sloop) is sunk by a submarine off Cape Spartel.

April 26 (Fri.)

German attacks at Locre and Voormezeele are repulsed.

April 27 (Sat.)

Mesopotamia:—General Marshall captures Kifri.

April 29 (Mon.)

The Germans attack in strength the British and French positions on a ten-mile front between Météren and Voormezeele and are severely defeated; this ends the Battle of the Lys (see April 9).

Mesopotamia:—General Marshall defeats the Turks at Tuz Khartmatli, half-way between Baghdad and Mosul, taking 300 prisoners and 6 guns.

April 30 (Tues.)

Palestine:—General Allenby again advances towards the Hedjaz railway, and recaptures Es Salt (see April 1).

Mesopotamia:—General Marshall reaches the Tank River and captures 12 more guns and many more prisoners.

May 1 (Wed.)

The Germans create a military dictatorship in the Ukraine; Field Marshal von Eichhorn breaks up the Ukranian Rada and establishes a German military Government at Kieff.

Palestine:—The British suffer a reverse between Jisr-ed-Damieh and Es Salt and lose 9 guns.

May 2 (Thur.)

The French make progress on the Avre.

British airmen bomb the lock-gates at Zeebrugge.

May 3 (Fri.)

Palestine:—General Allenby is compelled to withdraw his forces to the west bank of the Jordan.

May 5 (Sun.)

Lord French is appointed Lord-Lieutenant of Ireland.

The British gain ground in the angle between the Ancre and the Somme.

East Africa:—A British success near Manunga (160 miles south of Lake Nyassa).

H.M.S. Rhododendron (sloop) is sunk by a submarine in the North Sea.

May 7 (Tues.)

The Peace of Bucharest is signed between the Central Powers and Roumania.

Mesopotamia:—General Marshall occupies Kirkuk (110 miles south-east of Mosul) (see May 24).

May 8 (Wed.)

Nicaragua declares war on Germany.

May 10 (Fri.)

H.M.S. Vindictive (obsolete cruiser), damaged in the raid on Zeebrugge, is successfully sunk across the entrance to Ostend harbour.

May 11 (Sat.)

Mesopotamia:—The British, advancing along the Baghdad-Mosul road, drive the Turks across the Lesser Zab (70 miles from Mosul).

A British submarine destroys a German submarine of the 'cruiser' type.

May 14 (Tues.)

An Italian motor boat enters the port of Pola and sinks an Austrian battleship.

The British destroyer Phœnix is sunk by a submarine in the Adriatic.

May 15 (Wed.)

The French advance their line north of Kemmel Hill.

May 16 (Thur.)

A British air-raid on Saarbrücken.

May 17 (Fri.)

Great Britain:—A number of Sinn Fein leaders are arrested in connection with the discovery of a German-Irish plot.

Albania:—French and Italian forces advance on a sixteen-mile front.

May 18 (Sat.)

British airmen raid Cologne by daylight.

May 19 (Whit Sunday)

Ville-sur-Ancre is captured by Australian troops.

The Italians capture Austrian positions at Capo Sile (north of the Venetian lagoons).

A night raid by German aeroplanes on London (44 killed); five of the raiders are destroyed.

German airmen bomb a group of British hospitals at Etaples and cause many casualties.

May 20 (Mon.)

The French gain ground near Locre.

May 21 (Tues.)

A German aeroplane raid on Paris (three killed); one raider is brought down.

A British air-raid on Mannheim.

May 22 (Wed.)

A German aeroplane raid on Paris (one killed).

British airmen raid Zeebrugge and sink a German destroyer.

May 23 (Thur.)

Costa Rica declares war on the Central Powers.

The British armed merchant cruiser Moldavia, while transporting American troops, is sunk by a submarine in the English Channel (56 lives lost).

May 24 (Fri.)

Mesopotamia:—The British withdraw from Kirkuk (see May 7 and Oct. 25).

May 26 (Sun.)

The Italians capture the Monticello Pass (in the Adamello district) with 870 prisoners and 12 guns.

The British transport Leasowe Castle is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean (92 lives lost).

May 27 (Mon.)

The Third Battle of the Aisne (see June 2): the Germans launch an offensive north-west of Rheims; they carry the whole line of the Chemin-des-Dames and advance rapidly to the Aisne, which they cross on a front of eighteen miles; on the left of the German attack British troops hold their ground north of Rheims.

Between Locre and Voormezeele the French repulse a German attack.

The bombardment of Paris by long-range guns is renewed.

May 28 (Tues.)

The Germans advance rapidly south of the Aisne; they force the line of the Vesle.

American troops capture a German salient at Cantigny, north-west of Montdidier.

May 29 (Wed.)

The Germans capture the Vrégny Plateau and Soissons (see Aug. 2), and advance south of the Vesle.

May 30 (Thur.)

The Germans reach Fère-en-Tardenois.

Macedonian Front:—Greek troops make a successful attack at Skra di Legen (west of the Vardar and near the Serbian border) and capture 1500 prisoners.

May 31, (Fri.)

The Germans reach the Marne from Château-Thierry to Dormans; they claim to have captured 45,000 prisoners and 400 guns since May 27.

The American transport President Lincoln is sunk by a submarine in European waters.

The British destroyer Fairy is sunk after ramming and destroying a submarine in the North Sea.

June 1 (Sat.)

The Germans attack at various points between the Oise and the Marne and gain ground slightly; down the valley of the Ourcq the Germans advance to the edge of the Forest of Villers-Cotterets, 40 miles from Paris.

June 2 (Sun.)

The end of the Third Battle of the Aisne (see May 27): German attacks near Château-Thierry make little impression on the French defence; at several points between the Ourcq and the Marne the French counter-attack and gain ground.

June 3 (Mon.)

The Lys Front:—Mont de Merris (west of Merris village) is captured by the British.

The Germans attack in considerable strength north of the Aisne, between Soissons and Noyon, but make slight progress.

June 5 (Wed.)

A German attack at Longpont and an attempt by the Germans to cross the Oise near Vingres are defeated.

H.M.S. Snaefell (armed boarding-steamer) is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean.

June 6 (Thur.)

French, British, and American troops counter-attack and regain ground at various points.

The Dutch hospital ship Koningin Regentes, engaged in carrying repatriated prisoners between England and Holland, is sunk by a submarine (four lives lost).

June 7 (Fri.)

French, British, and American troops again counter-attack successfully; the British regain Bligny, near Rheims; the French and Americans recapture Vinly and Veuilly-la-Poterie.

June 8 (Sat.)

A Conference of British and German delegates, to deal with questions relating to prisoners of war, opens at the Hague.

Palestine:—The British capture Turkish positions near the coast.

June 9 (Sun.)

The First Battle of Lassigny (see June 13): a new German offensive is launched on a front of 22 miles between Noyon and Montdidier.

June 10 (Mon.)

In their new offensive the Germans make progress, at great expense in casualties, towards Estrées St. Denis (west of Compiègne) and Ribécourt (south-west of Noyon); they capture Méry, Belloy, and St. Maur.

The Somme Front:—Australian troops make progress south of Morlancourt.

Italian torpedo-boats destroy an Austrian battleship, the Szent Istvan, in the Adriatic.

June 11 (Tues.)

The French counter-attack on a seven-mile front from Rubescourt to St. Maur; they recapture Belloy.

June 12 (Wed.)

The Germans attack between the Aisne and the forest of Villers-Cotterets towards Compiègne and make some progress.

June 13 (Thur.)

The end of the First Battle of Lassigny (see June 9): the Germans are held in check on the whole front between Noyon and Montdidier; they lose part of the ground won by them on the previous day in the direction of Compiègne.

The Italians defeat the Austrians at the Tonale Pass.

East Africa:—The British occupy Malema.

H.M.S. Patia (armed merchant-cruiser) is sunk by a submarine in the Bristol Channel.

June 14 (Fri.)

Northern Persia:—Tabriz is reoccupied by the Turks (see Jan. 30, 1915).

June 15 (Sat.)

Italy:—The Austrians launch an offensive on a front of 90 miles, from the Asiago Plateau to the sea; on the Asiago Plateau the British maintain their ground, and elsewhere the Austrians are either repulsed or make only slight progress; they cross the Piave at two points.

A German aeroplane raid on Paris.

June 16 (Sun.)

Italy:—The Austrians capture Capo Sile (north of the Venetian lagoons).

June 17 (Mon.)

Italy:—The Austrian offensive, which has met with little success, is definitely checked and the Allies begin to regain ground.

June 18 (Tues.)

Italy:—Capo Sile is recaptured by the Italians; further Austrian attempts to cross the Piave, which is in flood, are defeated.

June 19 (Wed.)

Italy:—The Austrians are driven back in the Montello sector.

June 20 (Thur.)

Italy:—The Italians complete the capture of Costalunga Redoubt and regain ground on the Montello and at other points.

June 21 (Fri.)

The British Government announce the abandonment for the present of Home Rule and Conscription in their policy towards Ireland.

Italy:—Austrian attacks in the Montello and Grappa areas are repulsed.

June 22 (Sat.)

Italy:—The Austrians begin to withdraw with difficulty across the flooded Piave.

June 23 (Sun.)

The British gain ground south of Météren.

Italian troops repulse a German attack on Bligny Crest, near Rheims.

Italy:—The Austrians recross the Piave in disorder pursued by the Italians; the Allies recover the whole of the right bank of the Piave except a small portion opposite San Dona di Piave.

June 24 (Mon.)

Italy:—The Italians clear the right bank of the Piave of the enemy and cross in places to the left bank; they capture many prisoners.

June 25 (Tues.)

American troops attack and defeat the Germans in a sharp engagement north-west of Château-Thierry; they take over 200 prisoners.

Italy:—The Italians capture the Austrian bridge-head at Capo Sile.

A British air-raid on Karlsruhe.

June 26 (Wed.)

The British capture a German position west of Vieux Berquin.

June 27 (Thur.)

General Franchet D'Esperey succeeds General Guillaumet in command of the Allied forces at Salonika.

The British hospital ship Llandovery Castle is sunk by a submarine 116 miles south-west of the Fastnet (234 lives lost).

A German aeroplane raid on Paris (11 killed).

June 28 (Fri.)

The British make progress on a front of 6000 yards east of the forest of Nieppe and capture over 400 prisoners.

The French advance between the Aisne and the forest of Villers-Cotterets and take over 1000 prisoners.

June 29 (Sat.)

The Italians capture Monte di Val Bella (on the Asiago Plateau) with 800 prisoners.

June 30 (Sun.)

The Italians capture the Col del Rosso (on the Asiago Plateau) with 2000 prisoners.

July 1 (Mon.)

The French capture St. Pierre Aigle; the Americans capture Vaux (near Château-Thierry) with 450 prisoners.

The American transport Corrington is sunk by a submarine (six lives lost).

British aeroplanes bomb the Austrian naval base at Cattaro with great effect.

A British air-raid on Mannheim.

July 2 (Tues.)

Italy:—The Italians advance on the Lower Piave and capture 1900 prisoners; they also make important progress on Monte Grappa.

July 3 (Wed.)

Death of Viscount Rhondda, the British Food Controller (see July 9, and June 15, 1917).

Death of Mohmed V., the Sultan of Turkey.

The French advance between Autrèches and Moulin-sous-Touvent and capture over 1000 prisoners.

July 4 (Thur.)

A hundred merchant ships are launched in the U.S.A. to celebrate Independence Day; the day is celebrated in London and the Dominions, in Paris, and in Rome.

Australian troops, assisted by Americans, capture Hamel (between Villers-Brétonneux and the Somme), and the woods south of it, with over 1500 prisoners.

Italy:—The Italians make further progress on the Lower Piave and on Mount Grappa.

July 5 (Fri.)

The Australians advance on a front of 2000 yards north-east of Villers-Brétonneux.

Southern Albania:—An offensive is launched by the French and Italians.

July 6 (Sat.)

The Silver Wedding day of King George V. and Queen Mary of England.

Count Mirbach, the German Ambassador at Moscow, is assassinated.

Italy:—The Italians clear the Austrians from the Piave delta.

Southern Albania:—The French and Italians make rapid progress between the coast and the Tomorica Valley.

July 7 (Sun.)

The Australians advance on either side of the Somme on a front of 3000 yards.

July 8 (Mon.)

Southern Albania:—The French and Italians continue to advance, assisted in the coast sector by British monitors.

Siberia:—Czecho-Slovak forces temporarily occupy Irkutsk (see Aug. 17).

July 9 (Tues.)

Mr. J. R. Clynes succeeds Lord Rhondda as British Food Controller (see July 3).

The resignation is announced of Herr von Kühlmann, the German Foreign Minister; he is succeeded by Admiral von Hintze.

July 10 (Wed.)

The French capture Courcy, north of the Ourcq.

Southern Albania:—The Italians capture Berat (see Aug. 26).

July 12 (Fri.)

Albania:—The Austrians retreat before the French and Italians.

The Japanese dreadnought Kawachi is blown up in Tokuyama Bay with a loss of over 500 lives.

July 14 (Sun.)

Palestine:—The Turks attack the British on the Jordan and north of Jericho and are repulsed.

The French liner Djemnah is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean with a loss of 442 lives.

July 15 (Mon.)

The Second Battle of the Marne begins (see Aug. 4): the Germans launch an offensive on a front of 50 miles, east and west of Rheims; west of Rheims, between Vrigny and Château-Thierry, they penetrate the Allied positions to a depth of several miles in places and capture Chezy and other villages; east of Rheims they carry the French outpost positions but are held on the main line of defence; they cross the Marne at Fossoy and other points.

July 16 (Tues.)

French and American troops regain ground south of the Marne and capture high ground overlooking the Marne Valley.

H.M.S. Anchusa (sloop) is sunk by a submarine off the north coast of Ireland.

July 17 (Wed.)

The Germans make progress towards Epernay and reach Montroison; east of Rheims they are defeated and driven back south of Prunay.

In the Somme area the Australians again make progress east of Villers-Brétonneux (see July 5 and 7).

The Cunard liner Carpathia is sunk by a submarine west of Ireland (five lives lost).

July 18 (Thur.)

The turning-point which leads to complete victory: the French counter-attack on a front of 35 miles between Belleau (5 miles north-west of Château-Thierry) and Vingres (north-west of Soissons); on the left, under General Mangin, they reach the Mont de Paris, near Soissons; in the valley of the Crise, they advance to a depth of 8 miles and capture 5000 prisoners and 30 guns. Further south they attack in co-operation with American troops, advance to a depth of 5 miles, and regain more than 20 villages; east of Rheims the French under General Gouraud recapture Prunay.

July 19 (Fri.)

The Lys Front:—The British recapture Météren (see April 17).

The French and Americans continue to attack between Soissons and Château-Thierry and approach the Soissons—Château-Thierry road; south of the Marne the Germans also yield ground.

July 20 (Sat.)

The Germans withdraw across the Marne (on the night of the 19th-20th); the Allied captures since the counter-stroke exceed 20,000 prisoners and 400 guns.

The White Star liner Justicia is sunk by submarines off the north coast of Ireland after fighting for twenty-four hours (16 lives lost); one of the submarines is sunk by the British destroyer Marne.

July 21 (Sun.)

The French recapture Château-Thierry; British, French, and Italian troops advance between the Marne and Rheims down the valley of the Ardre; they capture Courton Wood.

July 22 (Mon.)

The Allies cross the Marne near Dormans, at Chassins and Passy; the Germans retreat north and south of Fère-en-Tardenois; German counter-attacks between the Marne and the Ourcq are repulsed and the French advance beyond La Croix and Epieds; east of Rheims General Gouraud recovers all his original positions between the Suippes and Massiges.

July 23 (Tues.)

Dr. von Seidler, the Austrian Premier, and his Cabinet resign.

The forced retreat of the Germans in the Soissons-Rheims salient continues; north of the Ourcq they are pressed back to the outskirts of Taux; south of the Ourcq the French approach Fère-en-Tardenois.

On the Amiens Front the French advance towards the Avre Valley; they capture Mailly-Raineval and 1850 prisoners.

H.M.S. Marmora (armed merchant cruiser) is sunk by a submarine off the south coast of Ireland (ten lives lost).

July 24 (Wed.)

Progress is made by the Allies north of Château-Thierry towards Fère-en-Tardenois and at various other points.

July 25 (Thur.)

The Allies capture the forest of Fère, Oulchy-le-Château and other important positions on the Marne Front.

July 26 (Fri.)

The German retreat on the Marne Front extends.

July 27 (Sat.)

The German retreat on the Marne Front continues.

July 28 (Sun.)

The Marne Front:—The Allies capture Fère-en-Tardenois and force the passage of the Ourcq.

July 29 (Mon.)

The Lys Front:—Australian troops capture Merris, near Météren.

The Marne Front:—The French capture positions north-east of Oulchy-le-Château and Grand Rozoy.

July 30 (Tues.)

The Marne Front:—The German resistance stiffens; the Allies capture Remigny and St. Gemme.

July 31 (Wed.)

The Marne Front:—The Americans capture Seringes after fierce fighting.

Aug. 1 (Thur.)

The French and British advance north of the Ourcq and capture important high ground commanding Soissons.

Aug. 2 (Fri.)

It is announced that Admiral Scheer is appointed Chief of the German Admiralty Staff.

The Allies recapture Soissons (lost on May 29); the Germans are again in full retreat in the Soissons-Rheims salient, closely pressed by the Allies, who advance rapidly.

North Russia:—Allied forces are landed at Archangel; they occupy the town and the surrounding district.

Two British destroyers, Vehement and Ariel, are sunk by enemy mines in the North Sea (97 lives lost).

Aug. 3 (Sat.)

The Marne Front:—The Allied advance continues; the Germans are driven across the Vesle.

The Albert Front:—The Germans retire behind the Ancre, evacuating Hamel, Dernancourt, and other villages.

British troops are landed at Vladivostok.

The British ambulance transport Warilda is sunk by a submarine (123 lives lost).

Aug. 4 (Sun.)

The Marne Front:—The Americans capture Fismes; the French cross the Vesle: this ends the Second Battle of the Marne (see July 15).

The Germans retire on a front of ten miles south-east of Amiens.

The Caspian:—A British military mission reaches Baku; it is subsequently reinforced (see Sept. 14).

Aug. 5 (Mon.)

Five Zeppelins fail in an attempt to cross the east coast of England; one of them (the L70) is brought down in flames at sea.

Aug. 6 (Tues.)

General Foch is created a Marshal of France.

The Germans attack the British lines south of Morlancourt and gain ground.

The British destroyer Comet is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean.

Aug. 7 (Wed.)

The British counter-attack and recapture the greater part of the ground lost near Morlancourt.

The Marne Front:—The French and Americans cross the Vesle between Braine and Fismes; the French advance north of Rheims.

Aug. 8 (Thur.)

The Battle of Amiens begins (see Aug. 12): the 4th British Army (Rawlinson) and the 1st French Army (Débeney) attack, aided by tanks, on a front of twenty miles east of Amiens (both armies under the command of Sir D. Haig), from the neighbourhood of Morlancourt, north of the Somme, to Braches, on the Avre; the German lines are deeply penetrated and 400 guns and over 16,000 prisoners captured. The advance attains a maximum depth of seven miles.

Aug. 9 (Fri.)

The Franco-British advance proceeds: the British capture Rosières; the French capture Pierrepont and reach Arvillers; the battle-front extends southwards, the French attacking below Montdidier with their 3rd Army (this marks the beginning of the Second Battle of Lassigny; see Aug. 15).

The Lys Front:—The Germans evacuate a number of positions; the British advance between Merville and Locon to a depth of over a mile.

The Rheims—Soissons Front:—The Americans capture Fismettes.

Aug. 10 (Sat.)

The Franco-British advance continues on the whole front from the Ancre to south of Montdidier; the British capture Rainecourt, Méharicourt, and Bouchoir; the French capture Montdidier.

Aug. 11 (Sun.)

The Allies make fresh progress, particularly between the Avre and the Oise.

Japanese contingents land at Vladivostok.

An engagement off the Frisian coast between British naval light forces and aircraft and German aircraft: a German airship is destroyed.

Aug. 12 (Mon.)

The end of the Battle of Amiens (see Aug. 8): it has disengaged Amiens, freed the Paris-Amiens railway, and seriously weakened the enemy's position; captures by the British during the battle amount to 21,850 prisoners and 400 guns.

British airmen destroy a German airship off the Frisian coast.

Aug. 13 (Tues.)

The Czecho-Slovaks are officially declared to be an Allied nation.

The French approach Lassigny.

Aug. 14 (Wed.)

The Germans extend their withdrawal on the Ancre Front, their whole line in this area being threatened by the British advance further south: they evacuate Beaumont Hamel, Serre, Puisieux, and Bucquoy.

The French capture Ribécourt, on the Oise.

Aug. 15 (Thur.)

The British advance across the Ancre.

The French complete the capture of the Lassigny massif: this ends the Second Battle of Lassigny (see Aug. 9).

A German aeroplane raid on Paris.

H.M.S. Scott (flotilla leader) and H.M.S. Ullswater (destroyer) are sunk by submarine in the North Sea.

Aug. 16 (Fri.)

The French make further progress south of Lassigny.

Aug. 17 (Sat.)

The French (under General Mangin) advance between the Oise and the Aisne.

Siberia:—The Czecho-Slovaks recapture Irkutsk, having lost it to the Bolshevists during July (see July 8).

Aug. 18 (Sun.)

The Lys Front:—The British attack on a four-mile front between Vieux Berquin and Bailleul and capture Oultersteene and over 400 prisoners.

The French offensive between the Oise and Aisne develops.

Aug. 19 (Mon.)

The Lys Front:—The British capture Merville.

The French advance in the Ribécourt sector towards Noyon.

Aug. 20 (Tues.)

The French continue to advance between the Oise and the Aisne and reach Lombray; they capture over 8000 prisoners.

Aug. 21 (Wed.)

The Battle of Bapaume begins (see Aug. 31): the British 3rd Army (Byng) attacks on a ten-mile front between Albert and Arras; Beaucourt, Achiet-le-Petit, Courcelles, and Moyenville are captured.

Between the Oise and the Aisne the French outflank Noyon, reaching the line Pontoise—Cuts—Camelin.

British air-squadrons bomb Frankfurt, Cologne, Mannheim, and Trèves (night of Aug. 21-22).

Aug. 22 (Thur.)

The British attack on a six-mile front between Albert and Bray; they capture Albert and penetrate the German positions to a depth of two miles.

The French continue to advance south of the Oise and capture St. Aubin and Pommières.

The Austrians launch a counter-offensive in Albania.

The Bolshevists defeat the Trans-Caspian forces and capture Merv.

Aug. 23 (Fri.)

The British attack and advance on a thirty-mile front from Mercatel (5 miles south of Arras) to Lihons (8 miles south of the Somme): they capture Boyelles, Hamelincourt, Ervillers, Gommiécourt, and Achiet-le-Grand in the northern sector of the attack, and in the south Chuignolles and Chuignes.

Aug. 24 (Sat.)

The British continue to make rapid progress in the Bapaume area: they capture Biefvillers and reach the outskirts of Bapaume at Avesnes; nearer Albert they capture Thiepval and the Thiepval ridge, Pozières, Courcellette and Martinpuich; further south they capture Bray.

Aug. 25 (Sun.)

The British advance continues: the whole of the road between Albert and Bapaume is captured (with Le Sars and Warlencourt), also Le Barque, Mametz, and other ruined villages; the prisoners captured since the battle began exceed 17,000.

Aug. 26 (Mon.)

The British offensive develops northwards; this marks the beginning of the Battle of the Scarpe (see Sept. 3); the British attack along both banks of the Scarpe and advance to the line south-of-Gavrelle—Rœux—Wancourt—Monchy.

Albania:—The Austrians recapture Berat and Fieri (see July 10 and Oct. 1).

The Caspian:—The Turks attack Baku and are repulsed by British and local troops (see Aug. 4).

Aug. 27 (Tues.)

The British make progress north of the Scarpe and capture Gavrelle; further south, amongst other places, they capture Beugnatre, Longueval, Delville Wood, and Maricourt.

The French capture Roye.

Aug. 28 (Wed.)

The Germans retreat at most points on the whole front between the Scarpe and the Aisne; the British and the French advance; the latter occupy Chaulnes and Nesle.

Aug. 29 (Thur.)

The British capture Bapaume.

The French capture Noyon, and cross the Ailette.

The British Embassy at Petrograd is attacked by Bolshevist troops, and the Naval Attaché, Captain Cromie, killed.

Aug. 30 (Fri.)

The British cross the Somme south and west of Péronne.

The Germans begin to withdraw on the Lys Front; the British occupy Bailleul.

The French cross the Canal du Nord and capture Chevilly.

Aug. 31 (Sat.)

The end of the Battle of Bapaume (see Aug. 21); this battle, by turning the flank of the German positions on the Somme, compels the enemy to withdraw from the area protected by the Somme and the Ancre; his new positions are henceforward in process of being turned from the north by the Arras offensive, which continues. In the Battle of Bapaume the British captures amount to 34,250 prisoners and 270 guns.

The Germans retreat on most sectors of the entire front between Ypres and Soissons, especially on the Lys Front where they evacuate Kemmel Hill and Steenwerck.

The Caspian:—The Turks again attack Baku (see Aug. 26) and gain ground slightly.

Sept. 1 (Sun.)

The enforced retirement of the Germans continues: the British capture Bullecourt, Heudecourt, Bouchavesnes, Rancourt, Péronne, and, on the Lys Front, Neuve Eglise.

Macedonian Front:—The British gain ground on the right bank of the Vardar.

Sept. 2 (Mon.)

Arras Front:—The Canadians with other British troops break through the Drocourt-Quéant switch line on a front of six miles.

The French capture Neuilly and Terny Sorny.

Sept. 3 (Tues.)

The British widen the breach in the Hindenburg defences, capture Drocourt, and advance on Inchy and Mœuvres; this marks the end of the Battle of the Scarpe (see Aug. 26), in which the British captures amount to 200 guns and over 16,000 prisoners.

The Germans evacuate Lens.

The French cross the Somme at Epanancourt.

Sept. 4 (Wed.)

The British make progress toward Cambrai, exerting pressure on the retiring enemy; they capture Ecourt and reach the outskirts of Mœuvres; on the Lys Front they capture Ploegsteert village.

Sept. 5 (Thur.)

The French strike north-east of Noyon towards St. Quentin; on the Soissons Front they reach the Aisne from Condé to Vieil-Arcy.

Sept. 6 (Fri.)

Between the Somme Canal and the Oise the French capture the Autrécourt massif, Ham, and the railway junction at Chauny.

The Germans retreat rapidly from the line of the Somme south of Péronne towards the Hindenburg line from which they launched their offensive on March 21.

Sept. 7 (Sat.)

The German retreat, pressed by the French, towards St. Quentin, La Fère, and Laon continues.

Sept. 9 (Mon.)

The British reach Gouzeaucourt and Epéhy.

The French cross the Crozat Canal.

Sept. 11 (Wed.)

The British capture Vermand and Vendelles, north-west of St. Quentin; south-west of La Bassée they capture the 'Railway Triangle.'

Sept. 12 (Thur.)

The Americans, under General Pershing, attack both flanks of the St. Mihiel salient (the Battle of St. Mihiel): they capture Thiaucourt and other important positions with 8000 prisoners.

The Battle of Havrincourt and Epéhy begins (see Sept. 18): the British capture Mœuvres, Havrincourt, Trescault, and Gouzeaucourt Wood.

West of St. Quentin the British take Holnon Wood and the French capture Savy.

H.M.S. Sarnia (armed boarding-steamer) is sunk by a submarine in the Mediterranean.

The Union Castle liner Galway Castle is sunk by a submarine (154 lives lost).

Sept. 13 (Fri.)

The Battle of St. Mihiel ends in the complete capture of the salient by the Americans, with 15,000 prisoners and 200 guns.

Sept. 14 (Sat.)

The Caspian:—The British evacuate Baku (see Aug. 4).

Sept. 15 (Sun.)

The Austrian Government issues a 'Peace Note'; Germany offers peace terms to Belgium.

The Germans, after evacuating the St. Mihiel salient, retire on a front of 33 miles, pressed by the Americans and the French, towards the Conflans-Metz-Longwy railway.

Macedonian Front:—The Battle of the Vardar begins, an offensive being launched by the Serbians and the French south-east of Monastir (see Sept. 30).

Sept. 16 (Mon.)

Macedonian Front:—The Serbians and the French advance on a front of 16 miles to an average depth of 4½ miles; they capture over 4000 prisoners and 30 guns.

An aeroplane raid on Paris (6 killed): two of the raiders are brought down.

Sept. 17 (Tues.)

Macedonian Front:—The advance of the Allies continues and develops; the French and the Serbians reach the Tcherna; the movement extends to a front of over 20 miles and attains a maximum depth of over 12 miles.

Sept. 18 (Wed.)

The end of the Battle of Havrincourt and Epéhy (see Sept. 12): strong German counterattacks are repulsed; and Mœuvres, which had been lost, is retaken by the British. In this battle the British 3rd and 4th Armies have captured the outer Hindenburg defences, with nearly 12,000 prisoners and 100 guns.

Macedonian Front:—Serbian cavalry advance rapidly on the Tcherna Front; British and Greek troops attack east and west of Lake Doiran and advance against fierce resistance.

Sept. 19 (Thur.)

Macedonian Front:—The Serbians and the French advance rapidly, at many points in pursuit of a routed enemy; British attacks are stubbornly resisted.

Palestine:—General Allenby launches an offensive in great strength; he breaks the Turkish defences near the coast on a front of 16 miles and his infantry and cavalry advance rapidly through the breach; the infantry reach Tul Keram, the cavalry strike towards Shechem and Beisan to cut off the enemy's retreat; nearer the Jordan the British attack and advance against a stiffer resistance.

Sept. 20 (Fri.)

The French capture Benay, south of St. Quentin.

Palestine:—The battle develops into a decisive victory: British cavalry enter Beisan and Nazareth.

Sept. 21 (Sat.)

Macedonian Front:—Serbian and French forces reach the Vardar in the direction of Negotin.

Palestine:—The British infantry reach the line Bir Asur—Samaria—Beit Dejan; captures to date exceed 18,000 prisoners and 120 guns.

Sept. 22 (Sun.)

Macedonian Front:—The Bulgarians are in full retreat along the whole line between Monastir and Lake Doiran; the Allies capture Ghevgeli.

Palestine:—General Allenby reports the complete destruction of the Turkish 7th and 8th Armies.

Sept. 23 (Mon.)

Macedonian Front:—The French capture Prilep.

Palestine:—The British capture Acre and Haifa and, east of the Jordan, Es Salt; Arab forces capture Maan.

Sept. 24 (Tues.)

Macedonian Front:—The Bulgarians retreat in disorder beyond Veles.

Sept. 25 (Wed.)

Macedonian Front:—The Serbians capture Ishtip and Veles; the British enter Bulgaria near Kosturino; the Bulgarian Government proposes an Armistice.

Palestine:—The British advance continues with increasing rapidity: Tiberias, on the Sea of Galilee, and Amman, on the Hedjaz railway, are occupied; captures to date approximate 45,000 prisoners and 265 guns.

Sept. 26 (Thur.)

The Americans and the French attack in the region of the Argonne on a front of over 40 miles, from the Meuse to the Suippe: Montfaucon, Varennes, and many villages are captured; the advance attains an average depth of several miles.

Macedonian Front:—Strumnitza is occupied by the British.

Sept. 27 (Fri.)

The Battle of Cambrai and the Hindenburg Line begins (see Oct. 5): the British attack in front of Cambrai, break through the Hindenburg defences, and capture Beaucamp, Graincourt, Bourlon Wood, and other important positions, with over 10,000 prisoners and 200 guns.

The Argonne Front:—The Americans and French make further progress; the number of prisoners to date exceeds 23,000.

Palestine Front:—Arab forces capture Deraa.

Sept. 28 (Sat.)

The Fourth Battle of Ypres: the Belgians attack from Dixmude to Ypres, the British from Ypres to Ploegsteert; very rapid progress is made by the Belgians, who capture the whole of Houthulst Forest; the British advance on their right beyond the furthest points reached by them in 1917.

The Argonne Front:—The French capture Somme-Py and Maure; the Americans reach Brieulles and Exermont.

Sept. 29 (Sun.)

The British capture Messines and the Messines Ridge; Dixmude is occupied by the Belgians; the Allied front is carried to the neighbourhood of Roulers, Courtrai, and Menin, an important salient being thus driven into the enemy's northern front which endangers his positions on the Belgian coast: this ends the Fourth Battle of Ypres.

Cambrai—St. Quentin Front:—The British, assisted by the 2nd American Corps, reach the outskirts of Cambrai and carry an important section of the Hindenburg defences between Cambrai and St. Quentin.

In the Oise-Aisne area the French reach the line of the Ailette.

Sept. 30 (Mon.)

Serbia:—The Battle of the Vardar (see Sept. 15) ends in complete victory for the Allies; the French capture Uskub.

An Armistice (signed on the previous day) comes into force between the Entente Powers and Bulgaria.

Palestine Front:—Damascus is captured by British and Arab forces.

Oct. 1 (Tues.)

The resignation of Count Hertling, the German Imperial Chancellor, is announced (see Nov. 1, 1917).

The French capture St. Quentin.

The Argonne Front:—The French advance on a front of 14 miles and capture Vaux, Autry, Condé, and Binarville.

Albania:—The Italians recapture Berat (see Aug. 26).

Oct. 2 (Wed.)

The British capture Ledeghem and cross the Lys between Werwicq and Comines.

The British break through a further line of the enemy defences between Cambrai and St. Quentin.

The Germans retreat rapidly between the Vesle and the Aisne, from Rheims westward.

The Adriatic:—Italian and British naval forces attack Durazzo and destroy it as a naval base.

Oct. 3 (Thur.)

Prince Max of Baden succeeds Count Hertling as German Imperial Chancellor (see Nov. 9).

Armentières is occupied by the British.

The British attack on an eight-mile front north of St. Quentin and make progress.

Oct. 4 (Fri.)

A Note from the German Government to President Wilson proposes that peace negotiations should be opened on the basis of his 'fourteen points'.

King Ferdinand of Bulgaria abdicates in favour of his son Prince Boris.

The British advance east and south of Armentières.

The Americans renew their offensive between the Meuse and the Argonne and make progress.

The Japanese liner Hiramo Maru is sunk off the Irish coast with a loss of 292 lives.

Oct. 5 (Sat.)

The British advance east of the new breach they have made in the Hindenburg line and capture Montbrehain, Beaurevoir, and high ground further north: this marks the end of the Battle of Cambrai and the Hindenburg Line (see Sept. 27), by which victory, the main Hindenburg defences having been breached, the British directly threaten the enemy's chief line of communications.

The French advance on a front of 25 miles east of Rheims: they capture Fort Brimont, Nogent l'Abasse, and the Moronvilliers Ridge; the German retreat in this sector develops.

Oct. 6 (Sun.)

The British capture Fresnoy (north of the Scarpe, opposite Douai).

H.M.S. Otranto (armed merchant cruiser), carrying United States troops, is sunk in a collision (431 lives lost).

Oct. 7 (Mon.)

North of the Scarpe the British capture Oppy and Biache St. Vaast.

North-east of St. Quentin the French capture Remancourt.

The French capture Berry-au-Bac (north-west of Rheims).

Palestine Front:—The British occupy Sidon; the French occupy Beirut.

Albania:—The Italians capture Elbasan.

Oct. 8 (Tues.)

The Second Battle of Le Cateau (see Oct. 10): the British 3rd and 4th Armies, with the 30th American Division, attack and make rapid progress on a front of 17 miles from Sequehart to south of Cambrai.

The French make important progress in Champagne, and the French and Americans east of the Meuse.

Oct. 9 (Wed.)

The British capture Cambrai and advance upon Le Cateau.

The French advance east of St. Quentin.

In the valley of the Aisne the French capture Grand-Ham and Lançon.

Oct. 10 (Thur.)

The British carry the whole Cambrai—Le Cateau road and enter Le Cateau; this ends the Second Battle of Le Cateau (see Oct. 8), by which the enemy is driven to the line of the Selle.

On the front north of Arras the British advance rapidly after the retiring enemy towards Douai.

The French reach the line of the Oise east of St. Quentin.

Serbia (where the advance of the Allies continues against the Austro-Germans):—The French occupy Prishtina.

The Irish mail boat Leinster is sunk by a submarine between Kingstown and Holyhead with a loss of 527 lives.

Oct. 11 (Fri.)

The German retirement develops in the south, forced by the threat of the Le Cateau salient: the Germans evacuate the Chemin-des-Dames, and, further east, the line of the Suippe; the French and Americans advance, pressing the retreat, on a front of 37 miles.

Serbia:—The French capture Prisrend.

Oct. 12 (Sat.)

Serbia:—The Serbians recapture Nish (see Nov. 5, 1915).

Oct. 13 (Sun.)

The British reach the west bank of the Sensée Canal near Douai.

The Germans retire on a front of a hundred miles, from the Oise opposite St. Quentin to the Argonne; they evacuate St. Gobain Forest and the bend of the Aisne facing Rethel; the French capture Laon and La Fère.

Palestine Front:—The British capture Tripoli.

Oct. 14 (Mon.)

The British, French, and Belgians renew the offensive in the north between Dixmude and the Lys: rapid progress is made; Roulers and Iseghem are captured.

The French capture Sissomme on the 'Hunding' line.

Serbia:—Ipek and Novi Bazar are occupied by the Allies.

Albania:—The Italians capture Durazzo.

Oct. 15 (Tues.)

President Wilson's reply to Germany's peace overtures is published.

The British capture Menin, in the northern offensive; south-west of Lille, they cross the Haute Deule Canal.

Palestine Front:—Homs, 80 miles north of Damascus, is occupied by the British.

Oct. 16 (Wed.)

The Northern Offensive:—The British 2nd Army (Plumer) captures Werwick, Comines, Halluin, and Wevelghem, and reaches the outskirts of Courtrai; the French and the Belgians capture Ingelmunster and Lichtervelde and outflank Thourout.

Oct. 17 (Thur.)

Owing to the threat caused by the Allied advance in Central Belgium, the Germans begin to retire from the Belgian coast north of the salient and, below the salient, to the line of the Scheldt; in consequence, Ostend, Douai, and Lille fall to the Allies (Ostend is occupied by a British naval detachment under Sir Roger Keyes and by Belgian troops; Douai by the British 1st Army under General Horne; Lille is surrounded and captured by the British 5th Army under General Birdwood). The King and Queen of the Belgians visit Ostend.

Further south, the Battle of the Selle begins (see Oct. 25): the British 4th Army, with the 2nd American Corps, attacks the line of the Selle; south of Le Cateau the passage of the river is forced, and the capture of Le Cateau is completed. The French advance in cooperation on the right, south of Bohain.

Oct. 18 (Fri.)

On the Belgian coast the Allies occupy Blankenberghe; north-east of Courtrai the British cross the Sensée; further south the British occupy Roubaix and Tourcoing.

In the Battle of the Selle, British and American troops make further progress from Le Cateau southwards to east of Bohain; they capture Ribeauville and Wassigny. North of the Sensée Canal, Denain is captured by the British 1st Army.

Oct. 19 (Sat.)

Zeebrugge and Bruges are captured by the Belgians.

The French, operating between the Oise and the Serre, break the 'Hunding' line on a front of three miles.

Oct. 20 (Sun.)

The Belgian coast is completely cleared of the Germans, who retire at a number of points on the whole front between the Dutch frontier and Valenciennes.

In Central Belgium, the British 2nd Army approaches the Scheldt.

The Selle Front:—The British attack from Denain to Le Cateau and carry the line of the river.

Serbian Front:—French and Serbian forces approach the Danube near the Roumanian border.

The British monitor M21 is mined off Ostend.

Oct. 21 (Mon.)

The Germans temporarily gain the protection of water (the Scheldt and its canals and other waterways) from the Dutch frontier to the neighbourhood of Valenciennes.

The British 5th Army reaches Tournai.

Oct. 22 (Tues.)

The French and Belgians advance upon Ghent; they cross the Lys Canal.

The British 1st Army enters the western outskirts of Valenciennes.

Further south the French advance on the River Serre Front.

Serbian Front:—The French occupy Negotin.

Oct. 23 (Wed.)

The British 3rd and 4th Armies attack on a twenty-mile front north-east of Le Cateau; they advance to a depth of four miles. The British 1st Army, advancing between Tournai and Valenciennes, captures Bruay, Bleharies, and Espain.

Further south the French cross the Souche against strong resistance.

Mesopotamian Front:—The British advance (east of the Tigris) along the road Kifri—Kirkuk—Alton Keupri.

Oct. 24 (Thur.)

The British 3rd and 4th Armies advance between the Scheldt and the Sambre; they approach Landrecies and the Forest of Mormal.

Italy:—The Allies launch an offensive on a wide front against the Austrian positions in the Trentino and on the Middle Piave; the Italians capture Monte Solarolo, the French Monte Sisemol; the British attack to force a crossing of the Piave.

Oct. 25 (Fri.)

The British 1st Army advances north of Valenciennes; the British 3rd Army captures eight miles of the Valenciennes-Avesnes railway: this ends the Battle of the Selle (see Oct. 17), which has forced the Germans from the line of the river, driven a new salient into their front, and cut their chief lateral communication, the Valenciennes-Metz railway. Captures in the battle amount to 21,000 prisoners and over 450 guns.

The French attack and advance on a front of twenty-five miles between the rivers Oise, Serre, Souche, and Aisne.

Italy:—Lord Cavan, in command of the 10th Army (of British and Italians), crosses the Piave against fierce resistance.

Mesopotamian Front:—The British capture Kirkuk (see May 24) and force the passage of the Lesser Zab.

Oct. 26 (Sat.)

General Ludendorff, the German First Quartermaster-General, resigns.

The British make progress south of Valenciennes.

Palestine Front:—British and Arab forces capture Aleppo; by this the conquest of Syria is completed and the Baghdad railway cut.

Oct. 27 (Sun.)

Austria asks for an Armistice, which is refused.

The Germans retreat before the French between the Oise and the Aisne towards Hirson.

Italy:—Lord Cavan's army advances several miles east of the Piave.

Albania:—The Italians capture the port of Alessio.

Oct. 28 (Mon.)

An Allied Conference opens at Versailles.

The Italians cross the Piave in the Montello area.

Mesopotamian Front:—General Marshall captures Kalat Shergat on the Tigris.

Oct. 29 (Tues.)

Italy:—The Allies advance rapidly against the yielding Austrians from the Brenta Valley to the sea; Lord Cavan's army forces the passage of the Monticano north of Oderzo; the Allies enter Asiago.

Mesopotamian Front:—General Marshall attacks and routs the Turks five miles north of Kalat Shergat.

Oct. 30 (Wed.)

A Czecho-Slovak State is proclaimed at Prague.

Mesopotamian Front:—The remaining Turkish forces on the Tigris surrender to General Marshall; the number of prisoners captured, including those taken in the last seven days' fighting, exceeds 11,000. This ends the Tigris campaign.

Oct. 31 (Thur.)

An Armistice (signed on the previous day) comes into force between the Entente Powers and Turkey.

Count Tisza is assassinated.

The Hungarian National Government at Budapest assumes power and proclaims Hungary a Republic; this ends the Dual Monarchy.

Italy:—In the plains, the Austrian disorderly retreat becomes a rout; the Italians approach the Tagliamento in pursuit; in the Trentino, the Italians also advance rapidly against the disorganised enemy. The Austrian dreadnought and flagship Viribus Unitis is sunk at Pola by an Italian naval motor boat.

Nov. 1 (Fri.)

The Battle of the Sambre begins (see Nov. 11); the British attack south of Valenciennes, force the passage of the Rhonelle, capture Maresches, Aulnoy, and other villages, and reach the southern outskirts of Valenciennes.

In Belgium, British, French, and American troops advance and reach the Scheldt in the neighbourhood of Gavere, ten miles south of Ghent.

Between the Aisne and the Meuse American and French troops attack and advance.

Italy:—The Austrian rout continues along the whole line from the Venetian Alps to the sea.

Serbia:—Belgrade is reoccupied by the Serbians.

Nov. 2 (Sat.)

The British complete the capture of Valenciennes.

The French capture Semuy and the south bank of the Canal des Ardennes from Semuy to Neuville; the Argonne Forest is completely cleared of the enemy; the Americans advance rapidly in the Meuse sector.

Nov. 3 (Sun.)

The sailors of the German Fleet at Kiel mutiny.

The Belgians advance south of the Dutch frontier and capture Baasvelde and Steydinge.

Between the Upper Aisne and the Meuse the Americans and French advance rapidly on a front of thirty miles.

Italian troops enter Trent and Udine; Italian military and naval forces occupy Trieste.

Mesopotamian Front:—The British occupy Mosul.

Nov. 4 (Mon.)

An Armistice (signed on the previous day) comes into force between the Entente Powers and Austria.

Revolution spreads in Germany.

The British 1st, 3rd, and 4th Armies, in conjunction with General Débeney's Army on their right, attack on a front of over thirty miles, from east of Valenciennes to Guise: the British force the passage of the Sambre-Oise Canal; they capture Landrecies, the Forest of Mormal, and Le Quesnoy with its garrison; the French make equally rapid progress.

On the Aisne—Meuse Front the French reach the line of the Ardennes Canal and capture Le Chesne; the Americans approach Beaumont and Stenay.

Northern Albania:—The Italians occupy Scutari.

Nov. 5 (Tues.)

The German Government is informed through President Wilson that application for an Armistice must be made to Marshal Foch in the usual military form.

The French advance between the Oise and the Aisne towards Hirson.

The Aisne—Meuse Front:—The French cross the Ardennes Canal; the Americans capture Beaumont.

Nov. 6 (Wed.)

German delegates start for the Western Front to receive the terms of Armistice from Marshal Foch and Admiral Sir R. Wemyss.

The German retreat becomes general from the Scheldt north of Valenciennes to the Meuse at Sedan.

The British 1st, 3rd, and 4th Armies pursue the enemy towards Mons, Maubeuge, and Avesnes.

The French capture Vervins and Rethel.

The Americans enter Sedan.

Nov. 7 (Thur.)

The Bavarian Republic is proclaimed. Kiel and Hamburg fall into the hands of revolutionaries.

The British 1st Army makes a formal entry into Valenciennes.

The British capture Bavai and reach Haumont (in the valley of the Sambre).

Nov. 8 (Fri.)

The German delegates receive the terms of Armistice of the Allies.

Prince Max of Baden, the German Imperial Chancellor, resigns.

The revolutionary movement spreads rapidly through Germany.

The British capture Maubeuge, enter Tournai, cross the Scheldt south of it, capture Condé and Avesnes, and advance on Mons.

The French advance towards Mézières and Charleville.

Nov. 9 (Sat.)

The Kaiser abdicates and flies to Holland.

Herr Ebert succeeds Prince Max as Chancellor (see Oct. 3).

The pursuit of the enemy by the Allies continues.

H.M.S. Britannia (battleship) is sunk by a submarine off Cape Trafalgar.

Nov. 10 (Sun.)

The French occupy Hirson, surround Mézières, and cross the Meuse.

The Americans advance towards Montmédy and the Briey basin.

Nov. 11 (Mon.)

The Belgians enter Ghent; the British (3rd Canadian Division) enter Mons at dawn.

The Armistice with Germany is signed in the Forest of Compiègne, near the Chateau Francport (in the train of Marshal Foch), at 5A.M.Fighting ceases at 11A.M.

Note.—The Battle of the Sambre struck at and broke the enemy's last important lateral communications, turned his positions on the Scheldt, and forced him to retreat rapidly from Courtrai. This victory completed the great strategical aim of the Allies, viz. to divide the enemy's forces into two parts, one on each side of the great natural barrier of the Ardennes. The pursuit of the beaten enemy all along the Allied line was only stopped by the Armistice.

The Chief Events connected with the War, between the Signing of the Armistice on the 11th November 1918 and the Signature on the 28th June 1919 of the Treaty of Peace with Germany.

1918

Nov. 12 (Tues.)

The Emperor Karl of Austria abdicates.

The Allied fleets pass through the Dardanelles, British and Indian troops occupying the forts.

Nov. 13 (Wed.)

The Allied fleets reach Constantinople.

Nov. 14 (Thur.)

East Africa:—The last of the German forces surrender, in compliance with the terms of the Armistice, on the Chambezi River in Northern Rhodesia.

Nov. 17 (Sun.)

In accordance with the terms of the Armistice, the advance of the Allies on the Western Front begins.

The Caspian:—British and Russian troops occupy Baku.

Nov. 18 (Mon.)

Belgian troops enter Brussels.

Nov. 19 (Tues.)

General Pétain, created a Marshal of France on this day, formally enters Metz at the head of French troops.

Belgian troops enter Antwerp.

Nov. 21 (Thur.)

British troops enter Namur.

The first and main instalment of the German High Sea Fleet (5 battle-cruisers, 9 battleships, 7 light cruisers, and 49 destroyers) surrenders to Admiral Sir David Beatty off the Firth of Forth.

Nov. 22 (Fri.)

King Albert re-enters Brussels after four years of exile.

Nov. 25 (Mon.)

Marshal Foch makes a ceremonial entry into Strasbourg.

Nov. 27 (Wed.)

The last German troops leave Belgium.

Nov. 28 (Thur.)

The Kaiser formally abdicates the crown of Prussia and the German Imperial crown.

Dec. 1 (Sun.)

British troops cross the German frontier.

Dec. 2 (Mon.)

Marshal Foch, M. Clemenceau, Signor Orlando, and Baron Sonnino visit London and receive a public welcome.

Dec. 6 (Fri.)

British troops enter Cologne.

Dec. 12 (Thur.)

British troops cross the Rhine and occupy the Cologne bridge-head.

1919

Jan. 18 (Sat.)

The Peace Conference (the 'Conference of Paris') is opened by M. Poincaré, President of the French Republic, at the Quai d'Orsay; M. Clemenceau is unanimously elected Chairman. On the same date, forty-eight years earlier (Jan. 18, 1871), the German Empire was proclaimed in the Galerie des Glaces, Versailles.

Feb. 11 (Wed.)

Herr Ebert is elected first President of the German Republic.

Feb. 12 (Thur.)

Herr Scheidemann, the first German Prime Minister, forms a Cabinet.

Mar. 25 (Tues.)

To draw up the Treaties of Peace a Council of Four (President Wilson, Mr. Lloyd George, M. Clemenceau, Signor Orlando—the 'Big Four') is substituted for the Council of Ten.

April 23 (Wed.)

President Wilson issues a public statement with regard to Fiume, which concludes with an appeal to the people of Italy as distinct from their Government.

April 24 (Thur.)

Signor Orlando leaves Paris for Italy as a protest against President Wilson's attitude and his published message on the Fiume question.

April 28 (Mon.)

The League of Nations is created by the adoption at the Peace Conference of the amended League of Nations Covenant.

The Peace Conference adopts the 'Labour Charter,' viz. those sections of the Peace Treaty which create an International Organisation to deal with the needs and problems of Labour.

May 7 (Wed.)

The Peace Terms are presented to the German delegates at the Trianon Palace Hotel, Versailles.

June 2 (Mon.)

The Allied Terms of Peace with Austria, incomplete in certain respects, are handed to the Austrian delegates at St. Germain.

June 19 (Thur.)

Italy:—Signor Orlando and his Cabinet resign.

June 20 (Fri.)

The German Ministry under Herr Scheidemann resign, having disagreed as to acceptance of the Peace Terms.

June 21 (Sat.)

The Germans scuttle their fleet interned at Scapa Flow.

A new German Ministry is formed with Herr Bauer as Premier. The German National Assembly debates the Peace Treaty, and resolves in favour of signature by 237 votes to 138.

Italy:—Signor Nitti forms a Ministry.

June 23 (Mon.)

The Government of the German Republic declares 'that it is ready to accept and sign the conditions of peace imposed by the Allied and Associated Governments.'

June 28 (Sat.)

The Treaty of Peace between the Allied and Associated Powers and the German Republic is signed in the Galerie des Glaces, Versailles, the ceremony beginning at 3P.M..

Sept. 10 (Wed.)

The Treaty of Peace between the Allied and Associated Powers (except Roumania and Jugo-Slavia) and Austria is signed in the Stone Age Hall in the Château de Saint Germain.

Nov. 27 (Thur.)

The Treaty of Peace between the Allied and Associated Powers (except Serbia and Roumania) and Bulgaria is signed at the Mairie at Neuilly-sur-Seine.

1920

Jan. 10 (Sat.)

The Treaty of Peace between the Allied and Associated Powers and the German Republic is formally ratified in the Clock Room in the French Foreign Office, Paris, the ceremony beginning at 4P.M.